Foreword

“A Comprehensive Outline of World History” was written and self-published by Dr. Jack E. Maxfield.

The structure of the work is innovative. Each chapter covers a period of historical time (e.g. a century). Sections within chapters describe what was going on in every geographical region of the world; each section provides a reference for that region in the subsequent chapter, i.e. in the next time period. The reader can thus get a snapshot of the entire world at a point in time by reading one chapter, or can follow the history of a region through time by linking to sections in successive chapters.

This modular, linked structure is ideally suited to web-based online implementation, especially to the Connexions platform. I am pleased to make this content available on Connexions for the enjoyment and enlightenment of everyone with an interest in the history of our world.

Robert Maxfield

October 2008

More Details on the Origin of this Material

My father, Dr. Jack Eldred Maxfield, was an orthopedic surgeon with a deep interest in history. He self-published three editions of “A Comprehensive Outline of World History.” The 1959 first edition consisted of 200 pages with 8 references in the bibliography, and included a unique time-line, hand-drawn and hand-colored by him, showing the rise and fall of civilizations. An original and six carbon copies were typed from his hand-written manuscript. He put these copies into binders and presented them to me and my friends as high-school graduation gifts.

The second, hardbound edition, published about 1975, was a single volume of 474 pages, 47 bibliographical references, and numerous hand-drawn, hand-colored maps. I do not know how many copies were printed.

The third edition, typed by my father on an electronic typewriter and published in 1984, consisted of three hardbound volumes totaling 1303 pages and 322 bibliographic references. Well over one hundred copies, in batches of 20, were eventually published as demand grew. The following letter was included with each set he gave away:

Dear friends:

These three volumes are in no way to be considered a formal publication. They simply represent the end result of some 25 years of reading, writing and re-writing historical material arranged in a chronological way to suit my own fancy and for the use of my family if they so desired. I am happy now to include a few friends who have expressed an interest.

Before using this manuscript for reference or even for casual reading, I would suggest that you first peruse the pages numbered with Roman numerals in Volume I. They give the general plan of the outline and suggest its purposes as well as defining some of its limitations. Please excuse any remaining typographical and/or spelling errors and I am sure there are many.

Best regards,
Jack E. Maxfield

Jack Maxfield died on September 14, 2006, at age 93. The original 1984 typed manuscript of “A Comprehensive Outline of World History” was found on a shelf in his closet. In 2007, a special print edition was published for his grandchildren, future generations of our family, and for special friends. Thanks to the World Wide Web and Connexions it is now available to everyone.

Foreword to this Derivative Version

by Infogrid Pacific

About this derivative version

Jack E. Maxfield's amazing work A Comprehensive Outline of World History, has generously been made available under a Creative Commons license. The topic based nature of this is an ideal content source to illustrate multi-format, remixable content from a valuable, well referenced book or content source.

We had multiple objectives behind deciding to produce this book into multiple digital formats:

It is a valuable reference resource and deserves to be widely available for educational purposes of all types in as many possible formats as possible.
The topic based nature of the structure makes it ideal for demonstrating content remixing which actually delivers useful results from a single work.
It's a large book in terms of word count and structure (number of sections or topics), and has the ability to stretch e-book devices to the limit.
There are sufficient linking references to make the reading navigation experience interesting, and again, push e-book devices to their limit.
The maps contain sufficient detail to be valuable.
The styling is conventional and does not require a lot of treatment or customization.

Remixing the book

The book has been comprehensively retagged into IGP:FoundationXHTML using IGP:Digital Publisher. The original HTML pages were imported into IGP:Digital Publisher using the manuscript import feature. This converted the HTML to XHTML automatically. Once the XML has been created and is available in IGP:Digital Publisher the content is ready for action in a number of ways.

The book is available in multiple formats.

There you can see this book as a Print PDF, and in various e-book formats. All of these are produced with one click from the IGP:Digital PublisherFormats On Demand processor. Most importantly we have created several variants using different combinations of the content.

The entire book using the original structure map is available as 6in x 9in academic style, and A4 manual style PDFs.
The same content is available as an e-pub and a mobipocket file. Please take note of the file sizes before deciding to download it onto your preferred device.
There are two remixed versions which combine objects horizontally through the content at 5000-8000 B.C. and the 19th century. These are also available in the  same format combinations above.
There is one vertical remixed version covering Africa available in the same format combinations.

How this version differs from the Connexions online version

The core content remains substantially intact. There has been limited editorial changes made as explained below to make the book relevant for a remixable topic based content approach.

Map References

Map references have been editorialized to remove page position indicators. For example: The positional references "map on the opposite page", has been changed to Map 2.3, or whatever the appropriate numbered references.

Internal navigation

Because the purpose was to turn each topic into a self-contained, remixable object, all internal navigation references such as forward and back have been removed. This left the issue of how to resolve internal inter-topic links. Because we have tried to create a stand-alone topic based reference work, inter-section links have been left as unlinked references in this edition.

For e-book devices with limited processing power and memory it is appropriate to limit, or even prevent inter-section links as much as possible to improve navigation performance. This is even more important where there are a large number of links.

Map positioning

Maps have been positioned for Online and e-book  presentation in proximity to their reference in text following the rule, "where possible a figure or map must follow its first reference in text". Maps are floated page-top or page-top-next in the PDF output editions.

Additional Notes

Additional notes have been treated as footnotes. This allows them to remain in their context, creates an easy to reference print book, and footnotes are processed to return section end-notes automatically for e-books. Notes and footnotes all have return links processed in automatically by the IGP:Digital Publisher Formats On Demand processor.

References

Reference processing was particularly difficult. We wanted to create all sections as self-contained objects, so references for a section were accumulated in a References section at the end of each topic. References have been renumbered linearly within each section which means they loose their original context. We felt it was appropriate for the original context to be maintained, so original reference numbers are included in brackets after the newly generated linear number thus [243] and have a direct external link to the connexions site. These numbers have an XML element on them which allows them to be hidden for any particular format using CSS selectors.

***

 Infogrid Pacific is pleased to make all variant formats of this book available for anyone to reuse anywhere for any purpose within the terms of the Creative Commons license.

I would like to give a special thank you to our Demonstration Production Editor Milan Bishwakarma for his tireless efforts in producing this edition. It was a labour of love spanning many months of his spare and own time.

Lastly we would like to acknowledge the work of Jack E. Maxfield and his family for their generousity in contributing this life-hobby-work to the greater good of mankind.

Richard Pipe
CEO Infogrid Pacific
May 2010

The Mechanics of and Some Problems of the Presentation

Material is arranged in one sense chronologically and in another sense geographically so that the reader may review historical situations either in a "satellite" cross-sectional view of the entire world in one time-frame, or may follow events in any one geographical area through the many centuries in more or less brief narrative form by following the simple (Continued on page so and so) after each section. An attempt has been made to give a brief resume of the political status, important philosophies, scientific developments and religious trends while devoting proportionately more time to a description of the status of the common people of an area at any given moment. Hopefully most of the world's outstanding personalities in all fields have been given some space, but it is admitted that many aspects of art, literature, music and architecture may, in some opinions, be slighted, as these are not the major fields of the author's interests.

The textual data is presented in multiple chapters, each representing a definite period of time. The earlier chapters span several millennia each, but beginning with the 7th century B.C. each chapter contains the events of one century only. Within each chapter or time-frame in addition to some general remarks pertinent to the period as a whole, the world situation will discussed under eight main headings or sections, representing eight great areas of the globe. These areas and their subdivisions have been somewhat arbitrarily chosen, but seem to lend themselves satisfactorily to an orderly consideration of the various societies and civilizations. One cannot prevent certain over-lappings and certain difficulties with such a plan due to the changing political boundary lines from century to century. As one example it will be remembered that the Great Wall of China ended at Jiayuguan in the west, marking the border of traditional China, and beyond this on westward lies Central Asia. Yet today much of this land to the west belongs to the present Chinese Peoples Republic, even though the inhabitants are still chiefly Turkish and Mongolian peoples. So, in spite of the political shift certain areas currently under the domain of China, such as Sinkiang-Uighur (present spelling Xinjiang Uygur) and Tibet, will be considered in this manuscript under the heading of CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA. Manchuria is considered an entity in itself, as part of the Far East complex.

Another matter which may annoy or confuse the reader as he progresses through the text is the spelling variations. One must realize that language is a spoken phenomenon and that what we call "written language" is really only a notation system that attempts to recall the spoken words to the observer. Thus when anyone attempts to write down a notation that seems to him to record a spoken foreign word his rendition will depend on his own language background and phonetics. The result may be only a rough approximation at best, and the spelling will vary greatly with the nationality of the translator. One of the most fascinating examples of this would be in the spelling variations for the great Mongol leader whose name has been variously written as "Jenghis Khan", "Chingis Khan", "Genghis Khan", "Chinggis Khan" and perhaps others. The Mongols as a group have been named "Khalkas", "Tatars", "Tartars", "Cumans", "Kipchaks", or "Poloritse" depending on the writer, his nationality and the location of the particular Mongol tribe at the moment. It is well known that the English often use a "k" where Americans use "c" as in such words as "Keltic"-"Celtic" and "Khosru-"Chosroes", etc. Although this author has attempted to be as consistent as possible there are probably many exceptions for which apology is asked.

There is still another source of confusion concerning names. When the first names of the monarchs of medieval and later Europe are all Anglicized we get an amazing succession of Charles, Henrys, Johns, Williams, etc. In one world history index I counted about sixty-five rulers named Charles. In this manuscript in so far as possible the monarchs’ names will be given in their own language so that differentiation may be aided. Thus in the Scandinavian and Germanic countries Charles will be Karl and William will be Wilhelm. Similarly the French Henrys will be Henris and the Portugese John will be the native Joao while Peter will be rendered as Pedro. Other examples will be apparent.

But that is not all! The Chinese emperors present special problems in nomenclature, as all Chinese have traditionally had several kinds of personal names, and special names were often added according to interests or achievements. Posthumous names were often given prominent individuals also to further complicate the situation. The old rulers of China were seldom referred to by their personal names but rather by the epithets of ancestral temple ceremonies, including the terms "tsu" (grandfather), "tsung" (clansman or ancestor) or "ti" (emperor). Founders of dynasties are commonly designated "Kao-tsu" (exalted grandfather) or "T'ai-tsu" (grand progenitor). In addition the emperors of the Ming and Ch'ing dynasties commonly coined era names indicating what they hoped the future would bring and subsequently they might be called by their era-name. One trouble is that some changed era-names several times during their reigns. Hucker gives the example: "Ming T'ai-tsu began his reign in traditional fashion with the era-name Hung-wu (swelling military power) -- 'the Hung-wu' emperor is a technically correct alternative way of referring to Ming T'ai-tsu."1 But one does not correctly say that his name was Hung-wu"!

One last warning. As this edition is being written almost all the Chinese cities and places are being spelled anew, in an attempt to come closer to the true phonetic rendition of the Chinese words. Since at the moment this only seems to add to the confusion and since it will be some years before most maps and texts will change to the new format, the old system of spelling will be followed in this manuscript. Peking will still be "Peking" and not "Beijing".

This text will occasionally also have special sections on selected subjects or appropriate summaries of certain eras. Terminology with reference to dates will be the traditional "B.C." referring to either years or centuries before the birth of Christ, and "A.D." for a specific year after Christ. The latter abbreviation, of course, is for Anno Domini, meaning "in the year of our Lord" and is therefore not properly used to refer to a century.

Thus, for those centuries after the birth of Christ we shall use the designation "C.E.", indicating the "Christian Era". Footnotes will be indicated by number on each page, as demonstrated on this one. References to the bibliography will be by number in the form (Ref. 2, 3) and usually will be grouped at the end of paragraphs or sections to minimize confusion during the reading of the text. Some "additional notes" will be found at the end of the text, beginning on page 1181. Triple asterisks - *** - in the text proper indicate that these additional notes are appropriate to that paragraph. In some instances the page number is listed with the asterisks, but otherwise the notes are easily found under the proper time-frame and then the geographical division, just as in the main outline.

1. [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

2. [34] CLARK, SIDNEY, All the Best in Scandinavia. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1968).

3. [102] Hume, Ivor Noel, "First look at a Lost Virginia Settlement," National Geographic. June, 1979, page 735.

1.  Hucker (Ref. 1), page 288n

Africa: 8000 to 5000 B.C.

AFRICA

About 7,000 B.C. a two-man plough was used in Egypt, one man ahead pulling on a rope and the other pressing down the point. (Ref. 1) It is assumed that hunters and pastoral peoples lived in great parts of Africa, particularly the north and east at this time, but there is little or no evidence of their culture except in the Sahara, itself. Some of the Tassili pastoral rock paintings of that area may date back to 6,000 B.C. During the climatic optimum from about 7,000 to 3,000 B.C. the Sahara was bush country, well stocked with game. It well could have been a zone of human interbreeding of races, in that today there are a number of Saharan and Sudanese tribes which appear to be intermediate between Caucasoids and African Negroes. Mediterranean dark-white Hamitic Caucasoids appear to have come from Asia, bringing Cushitic languages about 8,000 B.C. and spreading south along the Rift Valley of Africa to settle by the lakes in Kenya. They were fishermen, using stone instruments and making pottery. (Ref. 2) But to return to the area of the Sahara, certainly before 6,000 B.C. this was a region of lush valleys, wooded hills and fertile rolling plains, and the rock drawings of this early period suggest that the people were like the present day Bushmen, now found only in the South African desert. But with the disappearance of the big game, particularly the buffalo, these people were apparently replaced by herdsmen from the east, perhaps the ancestors of the present day nomadic Fulani peoples (Ref. 3, 4) Elsewhere in Africa from about 6,000 B.C. on, some groups living near lakes or rivers adopted a more settled way of life, using bone harpoons for fishing. Remains of these have been found near Lake Chad, Lake Edward and Khartoum on the Nile. (Ref. 5)

1 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

2 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

5 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

Africa: 5000 to 3000 B.C.

NORTHEAST AFRICA

In this period there were Cushitic speaking Hamitic people along the Red Sea and the Gulf of Aden on the coastline of the horn of Africa. In Egypt, sometime between 4,500 and 3,100 B.C. the Badarian Culture existed, with agriculture, irrigation, clearing of jungles and swamps and pictographic writing, which may have been imported from Sumeria. These Badarians may have come from south of Egypt via the Red Sea and Wadi Hammarat, but it is possible that immigrants from Jericho also arrived, bringing food-producing techniques. The overall population of the lower Nile was probably less than 20,000 at 5,000 B.C. (Ref. 1) The climate was cold and damp and the people wore kilts or long skirts made of linen or skins with the fur inward. They lived in some type of tents or perishable wall homes.

Hippopotami and crocodiles were in evidence, and in the area of el Badari there are bodies of dogs, sheep and oxen wrapped in matting or linen. This suggests possible reverence for these animals. Lower Egypt had domestic grazing animals from the Levant by about 4,500 B.C., but the Badarians lived primarily in middle Egypt and their pottery dates to the second half of the 5th millennium by thermoluminescence. That they had outside contacts is evidenced by ivory spoons, shells from the Red Sea and turquoise beads from the Sinai. Recent finds of a vast number of reed ships, many with masts and sails have been made in the long dried-up wadi between the Nile and the Red Sea which may well date back to this period. The Egyptians are basically Hamitic, but may well have added mixtures of Nubian, Ethiopian and Libyan natives, coming from the Sahara as it slowly dried, along with immigrant Semitic or Armenoid tribes. Cattle were used as beasts of burden perhaps by 4,000 B.C. The sail was used from about 3,500 B.C. on, and pottery dating to 3,100 bears paintings of sickle-shaped sailing vessels, apparently built with reeds and complete with cabins and centerboards. Egypt was first united as the "Old Kingdom" under Menes1, who, as king of Upper Egypt, subdued Lower Egypt and united the two with a new capital established at what was later called Memphis. Although Egypt had no copper or tin, it did have gold and there were fabulous goldsmiths in Memphis (actually a clan of dwarfs) from the early days of the United Kingdom. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6)

1A. Hoffman of the University of South Carolina (Ref. 9) writes of the factors allowing the development of the "first nation", under Narmer (Menes). At Hierakonopolis, in Upper Egypt, about 3800 B.C., there was slight seasonal rainfall, wooded grasslands, fertile flood plains and easy access to the Nile. There were two settlements in the area with mud-brick and wattle-and-daub houses spread over a 100 acre area and having perhaps as many as 10,000 people. This is called the Amratian period (also Naqada I) and excavations have produced maceheads, as symbols of central authority. A huge pottery industry was present, making Red Ware pottery which was traded up and down the Nile. Some was used in the elaborate burials which were part of the Egyptians' religious beliefs. Just after 3500 B.C., however, with the area becoming more arid, potteries were abandoned and the Amratian period came to an end, as people moved into more thickly settled villages along the wetter Nile flood plain, initiating the Gerzean or Naqada II period, which lasted until 3100 B.C. An elite class in the new villages built temples, palaces, larger tombs and possibly an irrigation system, rendering the flood plain able to produce bigger and more reliable harvests. But the water management and excess grain storage problems demanded more central control. Various kings fought for dominance and finally it was Narmer, who succeeded in political unification of the entire Egyptian Nile valley

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

A Neolithic Hamitic culture was present in Algeria and Morocco with agricultural settlements and pottery by 5,000 B.C. The Sahara was quite wet from 7,000 to 2,000 B.C. and the many lakes reached their maximum extent about 3,500 B.C. when Lake Chad covered some 200,000 square miles. It is now the only remaining lake with 15,000 square miles of water. The rivers of the Sahara ran inland so that alluvial material gradually filled up the inland basins, blocking and slowing the streams. In the fierce sun that followed the changing climate, the water evaporated and the marshes dried out. Salt deposits are still worked at such places as Amadror, Teghaza and Taoudenni which are simply old inland basins. The people of the wet Sahara were Negroid and they raised domesticated cattle and left beautiful works of art on rocks with some figures as high as twenty-six feet. Elephants, antelope, water animals and fish were abundant. The Negroid people of this era were not the Bushmanoid, round-headed people pictured on the rock drawings before 6,000 B.C. (Ref. 10, 11)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

At 4,000 B.C. there were two languages of the western Sudan family - Yoruba and Idoma - but they were already very different and had apparently been diverging for several thousand years. (Ref. 12) In tropical Africa there were probably scattered bands of peoples whose descendants are the pygmies of the Zaire forests and Bushmen of the Kalahari Desert. The first true Negroes probably lived as fishermen along the Nile and the Niger rivers and the savannah north and west of the forest about 4,000 B.C. (Ref. 13, 14)

1 [83] Hallett Robin, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

3 [94] HEYERDAHL, THOR, "Tigris sails into the Past, National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

4 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

5 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

8 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

9 [316] HOFFMAN, MICHAEL ALLEN, "Where Nations Began", Science 83, Oct. 1983, pp.42-51.

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

12 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

13 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

14 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

1.  Menes is now considered to be one and the same with the legendary King Narmer of Hieraconopolis, so eulogized by Professor Toynbee. (Ref. 7, 8)1

Africa: 3000 to 1500 B.C.

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Out on the horn of Africa, men in Somalia were producing frank incense and myrrh for sale to Egypt as early as 3,000 B.C. The Cushitic-speaking people continued expansion south of Egypt and into Nubia. Due to the change in the Sahara climate, more Negro and Sudanic people settled just west of the Cushites (also Kushites), increasing the population there (Ref. 1)1

1 Egypt of the Middle Kingdom had to deal with these Nubians and did so with forts at Senna, some 270 kilometers north of Kerma. The city itself was an extensive urban development, particularly after 2000 B.C. The large tombs of "royalty" contained animal sacrifices and some of them even had up to 400 human sacrificed retainers. The Nubian culture spread over central and northern Sudan. This particular culture of Kerma almost completely disappeared after colonization of the area by the pharaohs of the XVIII Dynasty of Egypt. (Ref. 2) After 1,520 the New Kingdom of Egypt used Nubian gold to hire charioteers as a professional force. (Ref. 3)

A map of Egypt of this period may be found in the early pages of the next chapter. The exact dating of the various dynasties and eras of ancient Egypt continue to be debated.

NOTE: Insert Map taken from Reference 97 (page 61)

The dates used in this manuscript are those given by Professor Easton in The Heritage of the Past (Ref. 4) and these are fairly well coordinated with those used in The Columbia History of the World (Ref. 5) and other recent publications. The first stone constructed sepulchre of pyramidal design was built at Saqqara, near Memphis, during the reign of Zoser (also Djoser), an early king of the 3rd dynasty, between 2,700 and 2,630 B.C. This was called the "Step Pyramid" and was actually the creation of Imhotep, chief minister of the king, a man who was later deified. Recent desert studies would suggest that this step pyramid and the larger ones to follow were actually shaped after nature's own desert, wind-swept dunes of the western desert. Sand-stone and solid rock mountains and dunes all seem to have naturally assumed a conical shape, as the winds spiral about them to exhaust their energy at the pointed top. It is very possible that the man-made structures were modeled after these natural ones, and it is said that a rocky knoll of unknown size underlies the Great Pyramid and that there is a natural stone out-cropping at the tomb of Queen Khent-Kawes. It is thus suggested that the ancients not only simply enlarged and refined already existing natural conical structures, but that the very nature of these shapes have allowed them to withstand the winds and sand storms of all the ages since they were built1. Still more intriguing is the finding in the desert of forms very much like the sphinx, indicating that where constantly directed winds hit certain geological formations an unusual shape somewhat like that of a reclining dog with raised head, is formed.

Can the sphinx simply be a dressed-up natural formation of this type? Similar shapes have been found in the desert as far back as 1909 (Ref. 7, 8) and there are suggestions of the same phenomenon in parts of Utah today. Copper mines were developed in the Sinai by Pharaoh Snefu, a successor of Zoser. He also used large ships to increase sea trade (Ref. 9).

Bronze was in use in Egypt by 3,000 B.C. and the great pyramids were started about 2,600 B.C. in the time of Cheops of the 4th dynasty2. Because of the fertility of the Nile flood basins in this 3rd millennium, the average peasant produced three times as much food as his family needed and thus he was capable of feeding the flood control workers and the builders of public buildings and Pharaoh’s tombs. The first wooden boats were made in exact imitation of the old reed boats. An entire such vessel of Cheops', dating to 2,700 B.C., has recently been excavated from his pyramid. It has a length of 143 feet and appears more graceful than a later Viking ship, but could only have been used for ceremonies on the smooth Nile, as it had no internal ribs and could not have survived ocean sailing. Only the papyrus ships from which it was copied could withstand the ocean waves.

All subsequent rulers of the Old Kingdom built great pyramids such as that of Cheops and these edifices had great religious significance. There is no doubt that great numbers of slaves were used in their construction, and they were obtained chiefly from Nubia and some of these were even exported on to Iraq. Toynbee (Ref. 11) feels that the 4th dynasty (2,600 to 2,500 B.C.) represents the height of Egyptian Society culture and growth. The population at that time was probably about three million, or more (Ref. 12). Disintegration of the society or "time of troubles", according to Toynbee, began in the 6th dynasty (2,300 to 2,200 B.C.) and for four centuries there was no central control but only small feudal states ruled by provincial governors, the "nomarcha", who levied taxes and kept small armies. Kings did exist, but in name only. About 2,000 B.C. Amenemhet I, a Thebian nomarch, marched down the Nile and established the 12th dynasty as a central ruling government, beginning the "Middle Kingdom" of Egyptian history. Toynbee considers this the "Universal State" of the degenerating Egyptian Society, in which the sins of the pyramid builders were visited on their successors, but Professor Cheilik (Ref. 13) describes this as a period of increasing trade and contacts with other countries, in spite of some political deterioration. When a mummy of Wah, an official of this Thebes Dynasty, was unwrapped at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York they estimated that about 365 square meters of linen had been used. This craft of mummification had been developed over a long period and all the technique is still not known. Certainly the first step was removal of the internal organs of the deceased, sometimes by an abdominal incision, sometimes by a corrosive agent introduced in an enema. The second step was dessication with the use of natron, either dry or in solution. Finally the body was anointed with balms and ointments and the extensive bandaging began. All of this was simply to preserve the body as an eternal repository for the soul. (Ref. 14)

The port of Byblos on the Phoenician coast was a large emporium for Egyptian products and Egyptian wares were wanted in Crete and Mesopotamia. With the conquest of Nubia a large supply of gold was obtained and a high point of prosperity was reached under Senusert (also Sesostris) III (1,878-1,840 B.C.). Egypt had a population at that time of seven to eight million (Ref. 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22).

The Middle Kingdom ended with about two hundred years of turmoil and disputes for the throne, until 1,680 B.C. when the nomad Semitics called "Hyksos" (probably Canaanites) invaded from the Arabian area. These invaders brought the domesticated horse with chariot warfare and men using composite bows and were thus invincible at that time. They made their capital in the Nile delta at Avaris and their overlords called themselves "pharaohs". Previous to the advent of the Hyksos' horses the Egyptians had used only the donkey as a beast of burden but the invaders did not penetrate the country far from the Nile delta, and the Egyptians considered themselves a distinct and separate people and did not easily accept strangers or new ideas so they refused to adopt either the horse-drawn chariot or the composite bow. The population as a whole was thus not greatly influenced (Ref. 23)

About 1,567 B.C. another Thebian king, Kamose, started a war of liberation from upper Egypt and recovered most of the territory from the invader Semites. The job was completed by his brother, Amosis I, a few years later. The Hyksos movement probably presented the final upheaval in the Amorite series of expansions that will be discussed under the section on the NEAR EAST, below. It was probably at the time of this Semitic domination that the Biblical Joseph moved into Egypt (Ref. 24, 25, 26, 27)

The bow-drill was used in Egypt from 2,500 B.C. on and rules of measurement, the plumb-line, construction of a right angle and the shaping of stones with a mason’s square were all features of this society. Ahmes calculated the area of a circle about 1,600 B.C. and Ptah-Hotep was a great philosopher of the 3rd millennium B.C. The Middle Kingdom was also a period of fine craftsmanship. A beer called haq was commonly drunk and was made from red barley of the Nile valley. Bread was supposedly also first made here in the dynastic period because of the development of a new kind of wheat which could be threshed without the application of heat. The ass, of African origin, was first used for regular trade between Egypt and Iraq sometime after 2,000 B.C.

Our knowledge of Egyptian medicine (except for commentaries from Greek and Roman writers) comes from seven medical papyruses discovered in the last century. The oldest of these, the fragmentary Kahun Papyrus, deals with veterinary medicine and women's diseases. The next, dating to about the 17th century B.C., is concerned with surgical matters beginning at the top of the head and working down to the mid-chest. The longest of the papers, the George Ebers Papyrus, dates to about the 16th century B.C. and is an extensive therapeutic text written a millennium before Hippocrates and containing prescriptions dating back to 3,700 B.C. It was probably a copy of older documents. This papyrus, twelve inches wide, unwinds to a length of sixty-six feet. Egyptians rather routinely removed all internal organs after death, saving them in special containers as the body proper was mummified, but they knew very little about the functions of these organs. Although they paid much attention to cleanliness, having almost a national fetish of keeping the gastro-intestinal tract clean with multiple purges, emetics and enemas of every conceivable kind, disease was still rampant. Mummies show evidence of tuberculosis of the spine with accompanying spinal deformities and cold abscesses, club foot, polio and measles, not to mention the undoubted parasitic infestations they must have obtained, and still do, from the Nile. Eye diseases, particularly trachoma, leading to blindness, were and are still common in Egypt. It responds some to copper preparations and it is interesting that Egyptian women wore green eye make-up, probably made from copper salts. In general, treatment was a mixture of religio-magical gestures and the use of an extensive pharmacopoeia and some limited surgical procedures such as cauterization, circumcision and occasional trepanning of the skull, if indeed, this was actually a medical procedure. Dentistry was advanced with prosthesis construction as early as 2,600 B.C. Egyptian physicians had good reputations throughout the ancient world and at home. There was apparently a definite medical hierarchy, beginning at the top with the Pharaoh's physician. Special training schools for physicians were attached to temples (Ref. 28, 29, 30, 31).

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

The Hamitic Berbers had a well established Neolithic Culture in a large area along the coast of North Africa, but they had no copper. They were probably descendants of the ancient Mediterranean peoples and related to the Iberians and Basques. There were two major subgroups:

The nomadic Tauregs of the desert who maintained strict hereditary classes, with an ancient alphabet and using artistic trappings on their camels and jewelry on themselves, and
The Kabyles, particularly of Algeria, living as a settled tribe, long famous for pottery made without the use of the wheel. (Ref. 32, 33)

Dessication of the Sahara set in about 3,000 to 2,500 B.C., causing some pastoralists to move into the jungles of the Nile Valley and others to move south with the rains. This shift to arid conditions in the Sahara may have stimulated the emergence of civilization in Egypt. By 2,000 B.C., as reflected in the Sahara rock drawings, rhinoceroses, hippopotamuses and giraffes had already vanished from this area. Southward expansion of cereal-growing occurred during the 2nd millennium B.C. as millet and sorghum were domesticated as tropical crops (Ref. 34, 35, 36)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

The southern shift of the cereal-growing belt, due to the change in the Sahara climate, resulted in an increase of the Negro populations. (Ref. 37)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [303] BONNET, CHARLES, "Kerma: An African Kingdom of 2nd and 3rd Millennia, B.C., Archaeology 36, No.6: 38-45, Nov./Dec. 1983.

3 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

4 [57] EASTON, STEWART C. The Heritage of the Past. (Alternate Edition). (Rinehart & Co., Inc. New York, 1957.

5 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

6 [59] EL-BAZ, FAROUK, "Desert Builders Knew a Good Thing when they saw it", Smithsonian April, 1981, pages 116-121.

7 [59] EL-BAZ, FAROUK, "Desert Builders Knew a Good Thing when they saw it", Smithsonian April, 1981, pages 116-121.

8 [243] EL-BAZ, FAROUK, "Egypt's desert of Promise", National Geographic 161: 190-221, Feb. 1982.

9 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

10 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

11 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

12 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

13 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

14 [246] BIANCHI, ROBERT S., "Egyptian Mummies: Myth and Reality", Archeology 35: 18-25, Mar./Apr. 1982.

15 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

16 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

17 [57] EASTON, STEWART C. The Heritage of the Past. (Alternate Edition). (Rinehart & Co., Inc. New York, 1957.

18 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

19 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

20 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

21 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

22 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

23 [246] BIANCHI, ROBERT S., "Egyptian Mummies: Myth and Reality", Archeology 35: 18-25, Mar./Apr. 1982.

24 [231] WENTE, EDWARD F., "Tutankhamun and his World", Treasures of Tutankhamun. (The Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1976).

25 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

26 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

27 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

28 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

29 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. ANDPETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

30 [15] BOOKS AND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

31 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

32 [44] Dales, George F., "Strange Relics of the Crumbling, Still-puzzling Indus Culture", Smithsonian 89:56-65, July, 1977.

33 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

34 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

35 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

36 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

37 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1.  The conical shapes of primitive shelters from the American Indian tepees to African and Arabian Desert tents and Mongolian and Kazak yurts in central Asia may all resist the winds in the same way (Ref. 6)

2.  Thomas (Ref. 10, page 32) dates the Great Pyramid at 2,900 B.C. and comments on its exactly squared base, the 50 degree slope of all surfaces and the fact that the stones are so well fitted together that a blade cannot be inserted between them

Africa: 1500 to 1000 B.C.

NORTHEAST AFRICA

The story of Northeast Africa in this period is essentially that of Egypt with little change occurring in the adjacent regions, except for Cush or (Kush). After the overthrow of the foreign Hyksos rulers local control was resumed within the establishment of the New Kingdom of the Egyptian Empire, with the great pharaoh, Thutmose III, taking over part of the coast of the Near East and bringing Egypt in contact with other cultures. He even took an interest in Asiatic flora and fauna and brought specimens home. Extensive commercial ties resulted in imports of Cretan wares, Syrian amphorae and African gold, ebony, ivory, hides and exotic animals. At about 1,500 B.C. the Egyptians had pushed south to become the masters of Kush, "to protect their security" and incidentally to obtain gold. The Kushites, who may have descended from C-group Caucasoids, became increasingly Egyptianized. (Ref. 1) The greatest geographical expansion, however, was reached under Amenhotep III, about 1,390 B.C. This ruler had his likeness constructed in two colossal statues across the Nile from Luxor, by transporting huge pieces of quartzite1 some four hundred miles from a quarry down stream on the Nile. Recent scientific research, identifying the rock, would indicate that the transport had to have been accomplished on a specially built lighter drawn upstream by oars and gangs of draggers on the banks. About a century earlier such a great barge was engraved on the walls of the temple of Queen Hatshepsut at Deir-el-Bahri. (Ref. 2, 3)

NOTE: Insert Illustration (page 103)

Amenhotep IV allowed some political decline, but, changing his name to Akhnaton (or Ikhnaton) he attempted to force a new, strictly monotheistic religion on the Egyptian people, but the new faith did not last long. Tutenkhamon ruled in 1,355 and Rameses II, who exhausted his resources in wars against the Hittites and then married an Hittite princess, ruled about 1,250 B.C. He built the first Suez Canal, a task not too difficult then, as the sea was higher than at present. A victory inscription of Pharaoh Merneptah (about 1,224-1,214 B.C.) mentions the Hebrews, and this may have been when Moses led the Hebrews back to Palestine. After 1,165 Egypt lost all territory beyond the Nile valley itself. In the early part of this period under the Ramessid kings of the XX dynasty, the dominant religion had returned to the worship of the Sun God Re and Amon, but gradually the Osirian church began to take over among the majority of the people. This involved the worship of the God Osiris and his sister-wife, the nature Goddess Isis and their infant son, Horus. The mysteries of this religion, including the death and resurrection of Osiris and the interpretation of Isis as the "Mother of God" spread throughout the Near East in the next many centuries, and eventually served at one time as both a model and a rival for Christianity, persisting well up to the 6th century C.E. However, at about 1,100 B.C. the high priest of Amon took over the throne and the empire became a stagnant theocracy. Even Kush was able to regain its independence. Invasions of "Sea peoples" - mixed armies of Cretans and Luvians, perhaps - probably contributed to Egyptian decline. Ref. (28, 46, 38, 8, 224)

The glory of Egyptian science was medicine. Public sanitation was promoted and all were circumcised and taught to use enemas as cleansing procedures. They used glass, linen, paper and ink, the calendar and waterclock, geometry and an alphabet. The empire had a peaceful, internal government with a regular census and post, both primary and secondary education for some and technical training schools for administrators. Wheeled vehicles were common, and they utilized bronze and such tools as blacksmith bellows. The Nile valley lacked iron ores so the Egyptians were limited in the use of the new military technology that appeared in adjacent regions late in this period. In dynastic Egypt the basic diet of the peasant consisted of bread, beer and onions, the first being a flat bread called "ta", but nobles and priests could choose from some forty types of breads and pastries.

Chickens were available and later the Nile marshes supplied eel, mullet, carp and perch, and some of these fishes, dried and salted, were exported to Syria and Palestine. (Ref. 5, 6)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Neolithic Berbers continued to live in North Africa. The population of Libya was added to by Anatolian Sea People, perhaps Cretans and/or Luvians, who attacked Egypt about 1,400 B.C. and then colonized Libya. Many of these invaders were later employed in the Egyptian navy. Herodotus, Pliny and other ancient writers, described a people called "Garamantes" who lived in present day Fezzan (375 miles northeast of Timbuktu) and who traveled in two-wheeled chariots drawn by horses. Rock engravings in this area have confirmed this. Were they part of the Sea Peoples? Some say the Tauregs are their descendants. Definitely among the Sea People were Shardana (or Sherden) who carried round shields, broad swords and who wore feathered war-bonnets. Phoenician immigrants settled in Morocco about 1,100 B.C. and these areas later became part of the Carthaginian Empire.

This was confirmed by the Greek historian, Procopius, who wrote that this Phoenician migration came at the time of King David's Hebrew wars. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10)

The Canary Islands in the Atlantic just off the coast of northwest Africa were inhabited before the known arrival of Europeans by the Guanche, who were a mixed Caucasoid and Negroid people, varying somewhat from island to island, with blond and bearded men living next to dark-skinned, clearly Negroid individuals. This has been confirmed both by early descriptions and by mummies found on the islands. The "Canary Current" is a strong, westward flowing Atlantic ocean current going straight from these Canary Islands to the Caribbean Sea and the base of the Yucatan peninsula. It is of great interest that the Olmecs, living at the western end of this Canary current in America at this era, were identical physically with those Guanche of the Canaries. The distance from these islands to Middle America is equal to that from Asia Minor to the islands, but the former trip is infinitely faster and simpler on anything, such as a reed-boat or even a raft. (Ref. 11)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

Negro farmers inhabited the Sudanic belt and their population continued to increase as fruits, vegetables and cereals were cultivated in the forest zone. Ghana, in west Africa, had domestic cattle and goats by 1,500 B.C. There was also pottery, stone axes, shale arm-rings and fine stone points, whose use is unknown. In southern Mauretania, on the southern fringe of the Sahara, excavations at Dar Tichitt have revealed the so-called Naghes phase, dated from 1,200 to 1,000 B.C. and showing circular compounds with evidence of cattle and goat herding, fishing and some hunting. The people had stone axes, arrowheads, gouges, and pottery. In central and southern Africa nomadic black Bushmen lived in the Stone Age. (Ref. 12, 13)

By 1,000 B.C. additional Caucasoid groups called "Azanians" brought cattle and cereals to join the previously settled dark whites in the Kenya highland and adjoining northern Tanzania. They left stone burial chambers, hut circles, terraced fields, roads and traces of irrigation. By tradition the Azanians were tall, bearded and red-skinned. In later centuries these people were absorbed by the Nilo-Hamites and the Bantu Negroids. (Ref. 14)

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [231] WENTE, EDWARD F., "Tutankhamun and his World", Treasures of Tutankhamun. (The Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1976).

3 [90] HEIZER, Robert F., "Source of the Colossi of Memnon of the Theben Plain, Egypt, National Geographic Society Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 287-304. (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

4 [90] HEIZER, Robert F., "Source of the Colossi of Memnon of the Theben Plain, Egypt, National Geographic Society Research Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 287-304. (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

5 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

6 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

7 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

8 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

9 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

10 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

11 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

12 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

13 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

14 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

1. The pedestal blocks with each statue made a total weight of 720 metric tons each (Ref. 4)

Africa: 1000 to 700 B.C.

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

At the beginning of the last millennium B.C. Kush (or Nubia) was an area of fertile grassland, although now it is desert. Prosperity then in the area depended on exports of ivory, ebony, gum, hides, ostrich plumes and slaves. The northern Nubians were dark-skinned but probably of Asian origin, while farther south around present day Khartoum, there were Negroes. Ethiopia began to be colonized by Semites from Sheba in Yemen in the 10th century B.C. Ethiopian legend says that their country was founded by Menelik, eldest son of Solomon and the Queen of Sheba. In the 8th century B.C. Kush was strong enough to conquer Egypt, perhaps with the help of those Ethiopians, and they established the XXV dynasty in 725 B.C. (Ref. 1)

In Egypt the post-empire period of the New Kingdom lasted from 1,090 intermittently until 525 B.C. The internal decay of the theocracy was soon followed, as is common in history, by invasion and dominance by foreign powers. About 950 B.C. Shishonq, chief of the Shardana tribe of the Sea People who had faded into the Libyan desert some two centuries earlier, revolted against the Egyptian monarch and installed himself as pharaoh in the city of Bubastis, establishing the Libyan Dynasty, ruling both Egypt and Libya. Egypt then became a maritime power, exporting alabaster vases with various seals to Spain. The name "Shishonq" has also been found on some American inscriptions, although the relationship is not clear at this time. As mentioned above, the Libyans were followed in 722 B.C. by the Kushites (and perhaps some Ethiopians) coming from the south. No cultural advance occurred in Egypt in those troubled times. (Ref. 2, 3, 4).

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

While the Libyans were in control of Egypt their influence and language spread far and wide, even to the Indo-Pacific region where the Egyptians had long mined gold (particularly Sumatra). Fell (Ref. 5) says the Libyan language spread with Greek influences into Melanesia. In the Mediterranean after 813 B.C. there were coastline colonies of Phoenicia, notably the growing Carthage, located in the Bay of Tunis near the modern city of Tunis. Archaeologists, however, have found nothing at Carthage that can be dated before 735 B.C. Like the parent Phoenicia, Carthage also manufactured a purple cloth by a secret dyeing process utilizing the pigment from a sea snail, called "Murex", and the Greeks named the traders who sold this, "Phoinikoi" or "The Purple People". The Romans then called them "Punici" and later the word "Punic" came to refer exclusively to the Carthaginians.

In Mauretania this period saw a decrease in rainfall and fishing was no longer possible, but millet was cultivated in the fields. This was the Chebka phase of the Dar Tichitt Culture. By 1,000 B.C. a new, Hamitic speaking people from the north, ancestors of present day Berbers, had established themselves in the Sahara region, with chariots, horses, goats and cattle. (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

Most of southern Africa remained much as in the previous centuries. Sometime in this 1st millennium B.C. a break in the forest belt in the east allowed Stone Age farmers, herdsmen and perhaps cereal growers to spread down the Rift valley from Ethiopia into central Kenya and northern Tanganyika. (Ref. 10)

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [46] DURANT, Will, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

3 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

4 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

5 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

6 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

7 [84] HAMBLIN, Dora Jane, "Carthage must be destroyed' It was but now it is reappearing", Smithsonian 9: 442, Feb. 1979.

8 [66] Fell, Barry, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

9 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

Africa: 700 to 601 B.C.

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Overpopulation in Yemen, on the Arabian Peninsula, forced bands of Arabs to cross the Red Sea and settle on the northeastern edge of the Ethiopian plateau. They were good farmers and irrigators and got along well with the local Cushitic speaking people who had a similar degree of culture. (Ref. 1) There is some evidence that Phoenicians, with the Egyptian pharaoh's support, were making sailing trips south out of the Red Sea at this time, and perhaps they even circumnavigated Africa.

Early in the century, the Assyrians under General Esarhaddon, then at the height of his power, swept down and subjected priest-ridden Egypt to tribute and restricted the kings of the 25th (Kushite) dynasty to the country upriver from Thebes. Esarhaddon put Necho, local prince of Sais, in control of the delta region, but subsequently Necho's son, Psammeticus I broke away from the Assyrians and re-established an independent Egyptian kingdom again (26th dynasty-655 B.C.) and even pushed the Nubians and Kushites out of upper Egypt. The chief contribution of the Assyrians to this region was the introduction of iron, which soon spread up the Nile, as the Kushites, retiring back to their capital at Napata, took the knowledge of iron for weapons and tools with them. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6)

In mid-century there were many Greek immigrants to Egypt, including mercenaries, colonists and traders. New crops were introduced such as figs from Turkey, vines from Greece, sheep from Arabia and pigs from Sicily. Currency replaced barter and caravan routes were developed. Slave labor was used in mines and quarries. After 609 B.C. Pharaoh Necho (also Niku II) attempted to run a wide canal from the Nile to the Red Sea and expended the lives of some 120,000 men in the process, but it was never completed. Necho also had an army conquer Palestine, but the Babylonians ran them out after about four years. (Ref. 7)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Cyrene, Libya, was the site of an important Spartan Greek colony by about 630 B.C. Carthage had contined to develop and had iron-working in its various settlements, a skill which then crossed the desert through trans-Saharan trade routes. It was at this period that the Assyrians were attacking the Phoenician homeland, and Carthage became increasingly more important as a center for that civilization. Gradually the Carthaginian or Punic dialect and alphabet came to differ from that of the Lebanese Phoenicians. By the end of the century Carthage was receiving Etruscan metals and pottery. Some of the latter was of truly Italian origin and some imitations of Corinthian ceramics. (Ref. 8, 9, 10)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

On the west side of Africa there was further climatic deterioration after 700 B.C. The spread of people down the Rift Valley into east Africa continued and both cattle and sheep were kept. The central and southern regions had little change from the situation described in the last chapter.

1 [83] HALLETT Robin, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [136] McEVEDY, Colin, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

3 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

4 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

5 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [66] Fell, Barry, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

10 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

Africa: 600 to 501 B.C.

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

As the century opened Egypt was again attempting expansion into Asia under native rulers and a punitive expedition was sent south to sack the Kushite Napota (591 B.C.) forcing the movement of this Kushite capital south to Meroe. Another view, however, is that the Kushite rulers simply elected to move their capital 300 miles south because wood for smelting iron ore was becoming scarcer and the land was being overgrazed. At any rate, Meroe then became a major iron center. Kush had a mixed Caucasian and Negro population and thereafter remained independent of the various Egyptian rulers. The nation owed its prosperity to trade in ivory, ebony, gum, hides, ostrich plumes, iron and slaves, all of which were carried either down the Nile to Egypt or across the Red Sea to Arabia and Mesopotamia. They also had great herds of cattle and adequate agriculture1.

Egypt maintained close commercial relations with both the Greeks and Lydians. In the latter part of the century, the Egyptians were pushed back out of the Asiatic mainland again by the rampaging Persians, and by 525 B.C. half of Egypt itself had been conquered by the Persian Cambyses, son of Cyrus. After Cambyses committed suicide in 521 B.C., Darius continued to rule most of this area. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

By this time Carthage had developed an empire of its own, with settlements in western Sicily and Sardinia and with contacts in Spain and along the African coast. In 520 B.C. Admiral Hanno landed 30,000 settlers from 60 vessels at the mouth of the Rio de Oro in what is now Western Sahara. The colony lasted about fifty years. (Ref. 6) Herodotus says that Phoenicians circumnavigated Africa in 600 B.C., starting in the Red Sea and going clockwise. Himilco, sailing from Carthage, touched the shore of Ireland and found it a fertile land. All of this exploration and expansion brought some troubles closer to home. Although they had previously been trading partners, the competition between the Etruscan Caere and Carthage now became so acute that conflict became inevitable. Malchus, of Carthage, consolidated the Punic position in western Sicily and then tried to do the same in Sardinia, although the native Sardinian states fought back viciously and they were soon helped by the maritime Phocaean Greeks. Caere threw in its lot with Carthage on this occasion. Herodotus, writing in the next century, said that the Phocaeans2 won but in so doing lost forty ships and had another twenty severely damaged. They returned to Alalia, got their women and children and resettled in Rhegum in south Italy, leaving Corsica also to the Carthaginians and Caeritans. In 509 B.C. Carthage signed a treaty with the rising Rome, defining respective spheres of influence. (Ref. 7)

Barry Fell (Ref. 9) infers that after the Persian conquest of Egypt and the rise of the Greek and Roman empires, the eastern Mediterranean was closed to Carthaginian shipping, so Carthage retaliated by closing the straits of Gibralter to all European vessels. Then under the guise of supposed Spanish and north African trade, they exploited North American silver, copper, hides and furs, bringing them back for the manufacture of bronze and the marketing of the furs. He feels that this secrecy is the reason Roman annals have no mention of the trans-Atlantic voyages. To date no one has come forth with any direct confirmation of this hypothesis.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

That part of Africa south of the Sahara and the Abyssinian massif was one of the five great remaining reservoirs of savage or barbarian life. The other four areas were the monsoon forests of Southeast Asia with the islands of Indonesia, the steppe and forest zones of northern Eurasia, Australia and finally the Americas. (Ref. 10)

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

5 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

6 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

7 [84] HAMBLIN, DORA JANE, "Carthage must be destroyed' It was but now it is reappearing", Smithsonian 9: 442, Feb. 1979.

8 [92] HERODOTUS, The Persian Wars. (Translated by George Rawlinson). (Random House, Inc., 1942).

9 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

10 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

1.  Today this area of ancient Kush is almost completely desert. (Ref. 1)

2.  Herodotus described the Phocaeans as plunderers and looters. (Ref. 8, Book 1, pp. 89, 90)

Africa: 500 to 401 B.C.

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Perhaps as early as this century the art of iron smelting was imported into Sudan from Egypt via Kush, which had become an immensely rich country. The early inhabitants of Axum on the Ethiopian plateau south of Kush were probably of mixed Asian and Negro origin, and they were joined about 500 B.C. by settlers from southern Arabia, some of whom were apparently Jews. An Ethiopian-Jewish community, as well as a later Christian one, has existed in Ethiopia1 up to the present time. From those contacts arose the legend that the Queen of Sheba bore a son by Solomon, who became emperor of Ethiopia and founded the Solomaic Dynasty. (The Queen of Sheba, of course, lived in the 10th century B.C.)

Egypt continued to be ruled by the Persians, with no advance in their own civilization except that their economic isolation was eliminated and they did complete the Nile-Red Sea canal which had been begun by Necho. Apparently the original Egyptian cotton was a poor product and linen from flax dominated Egyptian clothing. (Ref. 3) The Egyptian science of previous centuries began to be picked up by Greeks who had colonies at Naucrates on the Nile delta, with others along the coast towards Libya. All of this was further developed in the subsequent Hellenic Culture. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

In addition to the Greek settlements along the Libyan coast there were Phoenician colonies all along the western half of the North African shore from Leptis (east of Carthage) to the Pillars of Hercules. Carthage was rapidly developing an empire of its own, controlling the old Tartessus area of Spain by 480 B.C. and later gaining all of the western half of the African Mediterranean shore line. It was mentioned in the last chapter that at the end of that century Hanno, of Carthage, had established a large colony down the Atlantic coast of Africa. Other writers have dated this colony, some 2,600 miles down the Atlantic, at 490 B.C., but in any event, archeologists have shown that Hanno was not the first, as there were already ruins of a large megalithic city of Lixus, far south of Gibralter, just where the ocean current sweeps past to go directly to the Gulf of Mexico. The Romans later called this ancient city the "Eternal City" or by a still older name, "Sun City", as it was apparently built by sun-worshippers who included astronomers, architects, masons, scribes and expert potters. The Sumerians, Assyrians, Hittites, Phoenicians, Egyptians and the Lixus people were all fanatic sun-worshippers, just as were the Olmecs and the Mochica in Mexico and Peru, respectively. The Carthaginian Himilco also continued his trips up to the northern shores of Europe to obtain tin for bronze . In his effort to find the ultimate source of that metal, and avoid the Celtic middle men of France, Himilco finally found the channel islands and then the coast of Britain, either at Cornwall or Devon, eventually to discover the tin mines of Cornwall. (Ref. 8, 9, 10, 11) The Carthaginian position in the Mediterranean was weakened in 480 B.C. when a large Carthaginian force suffered an humiliating defeat at the hands of Greek Syracusans in northern Sicily. Carthage then seemed to also lose its former Etruscan ally, the city-state of Caere. Perhaps this occurred because Caere had tried to establish a colony on the Atlantic island of Madeira as a means of interrupting the Carthaginian merchant marine's monopoly of the tin supply from Gaul and Cornwall. (Ref. 12)

In addition to the civilized centers of Egypt, Kush and Carthage, the 4th century center of Cyrene, in present day east Libya, must be mentioned. This was a Greek city, settled in the previous- century but which now dominated an entire community area which was prosperous and cultured. (Ref. 13)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

The climate continued to deteriorate in the Sahara and life in the Akan jeir Culture of the Tichit Valley of southern Mauretania was becoming progressively more difficult. In this century the areas of Ghana and Kanem began development, probably with the help of Berbers from the north, and with the economic foundation of the export of gold and slaves. Excavations south of Lake Chad give evidence of people, stone and bone implements and cattle-raising at the beginning of this century. (Ref. 14) In Nigeria an iron industry developed on the Jos Plateau, and sculptured heads and figurines in terracotta dating to 500 B.C. have been found near Nok, in that country. About the same time, the Negroes, starting northwest of the rain forests, migrated down through the forest along the great rivers to the central part of the southern savannas and then spread out in all directions to the eastern part of the continent and toward the south. They spoke the Bantu language, which is the ancestor of most African languages today. These men took knowledge of mining and iron with them. (Ref. 15, 16, 17) Hottentots and Bushmen still lived in the far south.

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [240] WORLD BOOK ENCYLOPEDIA. (Field Enterprises, Inc., Chicago 1950).

3 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

4 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

5 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

6 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

7 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

8 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

9 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

10 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

11 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

12 [75] GRANT, MICHAEL, The Etruscans. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, New York, 1980).

13 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

14 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

15 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

1.  The word "Ethiopia" is Greek for "burnt-face". Actually this region was usually called "Abyssinia" until 1923. (Ref. 1, 2)

Africa: 400 to 301 B.C.

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Kush continued its prosperity with extensive trade routes. The ruins of both Napata and Meroe still stand today and there are the remains of pyramids like those of Egypt but also Hellenistic pillars, Arabian arches and even hieroglyphs with Hindu-like symbols, all suggesting a cosmopolitan atmosphere. Axum continued to exist still farther south. (Ref. 1)

The Egyptians revolted successfully against the Persians under the 28th, 29th and 30th dynasties, but late in the century, as we shall see, the Macedonian-Greek Alexander took over the old Persian territories, including Egypt. The city of Alexandria was founded just before Alexander's death in about 323 B.C. and there was soon accumulated there a great research library containing perhaps 400,000 manuscripts in literature, mathematics, astronomy and medicine. Later, as Alexander's empire was divided, the Macedonian general, Ptolemy, took over Egypt and helped make it into a great commercial nation.

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

A portion of what is now Libya went with Egypt as part of the Persian Empire and then later Alexander's. Otherwise the chief point of interest was Carthage which in- creased in population and power and participated in intermittent wars with Sicily. Between 310 and 306 B.C. the navies of Carthage and the Sicilian Greeks were in a terrible conflict with the Carthaginians gathering a great invasion force of about 1,500 vessels. In so doing, however, they had to leave the gates of Hercules unguarded, thus making it possible for the first time in some years for the ships of other Mediterranean nations to reach the Atlantic. (See WESTERN EUROPE, this chapter). To pay their soldiers, after conquering Sicily, the Carthaginians engaged the finest Sicilian Greek artists to make dies for casting new Sicilian-Carthaginian coins, and these were soon circulating wherever the north Africans had business dealings.

In the post-Alexander period at the end of the century the Libyan Greeks of Cyrene became the major source of learned men at the court of the Ptolemies in Alexandria. Cyrene exported chiefly horses and silphium, an herb used in Roman cooking. (Ref. 2, 3)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

By 300 B.C. permanent settlement in the Tichit Valley in the southwest Sahara had ended because of desiccation. The Sudanese Negroes, stretching across the continent just south of the Sahara now had iron technology and with greater population, better agricultural methods and possibly greater social cohesion, they were able to expand southward throughout Africa at the expense of indigenous inhabitants whom they conquered, absorbed or displaced. In the early centuries they confined themselves to the drier regions where their cereals could grow. These were the people known in the east and south as "Bantu", although actually the name refers to their language, rather than to any particular tribe. (Ref. 4, 5)

1 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

2 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

3 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

4 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

5 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

Africa: 300 to 201 B.C.

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

One thousand miles south of the Mediterranean (in what is now the Republic of Sudan) the Kingdom of Meroe flourished through this period. At first the culture was Egyptian but later it developed a unique African character with its main industry being iron working. It also had gold. This society was a successor to Kush, simply with a new capital at Meroe. Still farther south was the Semitic Habashat Kingdom, established by migrating Yemenites, with a capital at Axum. The local Cushites soon began to accept the language and customs of these Semites and the country began to prosper, exporting ivory, tortoise shell, rhinoceros horn and finally gold, through the Red Sea. (Ref. 1)

The real story of this corner of Africa, however, remained in Egypt. In spite of the Greek conquest of the previous century most of Egypt remained Egyptian and there was a return to Egyptian political ideas. Ptolemy II (Philadelphus), reigning from 309 to 246 B.C. took the title of Pharaoh, the God-King, although personally he was a modest man, intelligent and creative. Under him there was continued expansion along the Phoenician and Asia Minor coasts. Ptolemy III (283 - 221) followed. An interesting aspect of Ptolemaic Egypt is its extensive experiment in state socialism. Although royal ownership of the land had long been a custom, the king now supervised all economic activity. The government decided which fields were to be planted and with what, where crops were to be sold and for how much. It regulated transportation, processing, manufacturing, trade and banking, sold abandoned babies and taxed everything. From about 275 to 215 B.C. this system made the Ptolemies the richest Hellenistic rulers. This wealth was lavished on the city of Alexandria which became the greatest trade center in the world and acted as a fusion center for people of many religions, including a great number of Jews. The Alexandria Museum was actually a university, engaged in research and records and a certain amount of teaching. During its active phase it helped to produce Euclid, Eratosthenes, Apollinus, Hipparchus, Hero and Archimedes.

At this time the center of Greek medicine also shifted to Alexandria, with Herophilus, anatomist, and Erasistratus, regarded by some as the founder of physiology. He distinguished between motor and sensory nerves, gave names to the heart valves and studied arteries, veins and lymphatic ducts. Actually a number of different sects of medicine such as Dogmatism, Empiricism, Methodism, Pneumatism and Eclecticism developed or radiated out from Alexandria. One of the Dogmatists, Herophilos, was responsible for a number of human anatomical descriptions including various parts of the brain, the intestinal tract, lymphatics, liver, genital organs, eye and the vascular system. The Museum functioned at a high level for only a century, however, and after Ptolemy II it was swallowed up by the Egyptian priestcraft. Attic-Greek was the language of education and administration. (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

The Alexandria library was more permanent. Included in the tremendous collection of some 700,000 volumes1 was the "corpus Hippocratum" made up of some genuine Hippocratic writings but also treatises and notes of his pupils and even some material from a rival medical school at Cnidus. Eratosthenes became librarian in 235 B.C. and became the founder of the science of geography by making maps and conceiving the idea of projections. In 239 B.C. he calculated the circumference of the earth at 28,000 miles, an error of only 13%. This means that a degree of latitude was thought to be 60 miles, rather than the true 69 miles, an error not great enough to forestall ocean crossings with a fair degree of certain landing. He based his calculations on the proposition that the earth was a sphere and that the sun's rays for practical purposes may be considered to be parallel. Longitude was calculated by dead reckoning. Eratosthenes also reported that papyrus ships, with sails and rigging as on the Nile, sailed as far as the mouth of the Ganges and Ceylon, taking perhaps twenty days to go from the former to the latter, thus averaging about 75 miles per day, a speed of more than three knots an hour. (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9)

Toward the end of the century radical decay set in, with bureaucratic corruption and slackness. As the century ended the aggressive Syrian king, Antiochus III, defeated the child Ptolemy V and took the Mediterranean coastal possessions of Palestine, Phoenicia and Asia Minor away from the Egyptian Dynasty. There is some indication that bubonic plague, or something very similar, made its first appearance in Egypt and adjacent Libya in this century and then disappeared again for another 800 years. (Ref. 11)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Carthage was now the richest of the Mediterranean cities, trading in slaves, Egyptian linen, ivory, animal skins, Greek pottery and wine, iron from Elba, copper from Cyprus, silver from Spain, tin from Britain and incense from Arabia. Some Carthaginian planters occupying fertile land in Libya may have had as many as 20,000 slaves. (Ref. 12) In 261 B.C. Carthage supposedly had 1,500 ships with approximately 150,000 crewmen. This is to be compared with the famous Spanish Armada of A.D. 1588 when Spain had 120 ships and 27,000 crew-men, Carthage soon reduced Numidia to a series of vassal states and became the capital of a Semitic empire which spread all along north Africa as well as in the islands of the Mediterranean and in Spain. Although the level of civilization was high in most respects, some of their customs were barbaric, such as sacrificing living children to certain male and female gods. The details of Carthage's great struggles with Rome will be given in later sections under ITALY and SPAIN. It will suffice to say at this time that at the end of the First Punic War a local revolution broke out in Carthage which raged for forty months. And still Carthage bounced back to fight the greater Second Punic War with Rome. At the end of this second conflict, when Hannibal was defeated by Scipio at the gates of the city, it was the beginning of the end of this great city-state, although it struggled on until the middle of the next century. (Ref. 13, 14)

It is somewhat difficult for us today to grasp the magnitude of the Punic Wars. The First was marked by some of the greatest sea battles in history. Consider the following, as collected from ancient historians by Fell (Ref. 15):

Date | Name | Roman Ships | Carthage Ships | Carthage Losses
260 B.C. | Battle of Mylae | 150 ships | 150 ships | 50 ships
256 B.C. | Battle of Economus | 230 ships | 230 ships | 84 ships
255 B.C. | Battle pf Hermaean Cape | 200 ships | 200 ships | 100 ships
242 B.C. | Battle of Aegates Island | 200 ships | 100 ships | 100 ships
Total ships lost |   |   |   | 334 ships

Table 1

Each Carthaginian ship had a crew of at least 250 rowers, with 120 more officers and marines. The losses of men in these great sea battles must have been staggering.

Another interesting fact about Carthage at this period is that their coins changed from silver to gold, but with just a small amount of gold - the amalgam called "electrum" - at about 300 B.C. The design also changed to depict the native Carthaginian goddess, Tanith, spouse of Bel. Based on findings since 1976 of alleged Carthaginian coins of this period found in various north American sites, Fell (Ref. 16) believes that the source of the Carthaginian gold was America, obtained from Amerindians in bartering with bronze manufactures of the Cypriot Phoenicians. Such bronze works are now held in storage rooms in Cuenca, Brazil, collected by Professor Paul Cheeseman. This region was a former Inca northern capital, noted for burial hoards and underground valuables. Fell also believes that these same North African mariners traded with North American Algonquin tribes for timber which they used for ships. After the terrible naval defeats by Rome and the absence of a navy, trade with America was no longer profitable or even possible.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

In northern Nigeria the so-called Nok Culture has been identified with terra-cotta figurines, and evidence of iron slag and tin-mining, dated by radio-carbon technique to about 300 B.C. Along the high cliffs of Bandiagara on the edge of the Hombori Mountains near the bend of the Niger River in Mali, the Toloy people built granaries of mud coils and stored them in giant caves in the cliffs, while their villages were probably on the plains below. (Ref. 17) Along the Congo River there were Stone Age gathers and fishermen about 270 B.C. In the east and south there was a continued take-over by the Sudanese Negroes who were now called Bantu, after their language. (Ref. 18, 19)

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [47] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part II - The Life of Greece. (1939).

3 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. and PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

4 [15] BOOKSAND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

5 [224] VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

6 [15] BOOKSAND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

7 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

8 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

9 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

10 [15] BOOKSAND MEDICINE, (Editors), M.D. Medical News Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 8, Aug. 1959.

11 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

12 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

13 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

14 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

15 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

16 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

17 [251] BEDAUX, ROGIER M.A., "Rediscoverring the Tellem of Mali", Archeology 35: No. 3, pp. 28-34, May/June 1982.

18 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

19 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1.  Equal to 50,000 modern books. (Ref. 10)

Africa: 200 to 101 B.C.

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

In the southern part of this area Kush as well as Axum continued to flourish. About 200 B.C. Egypt lost all its acquisitions outside of continental Africa as the Ptolemaic armies were defeated by the Seleucids at Panion. The Macedonian dynasty continued to reign, however, and their administrations promoted continued intellectual and commercial activity, particularly at Alexandria. The welding of Egypt and Syria onto the rejuvenated Ionic Greek world created a high economic unit and allowed cities of the magnitude of ninety to one hundred and fifty thousand people to develop, the first of these being, of course, Alexandria. By the end of the century the Egyptians were chafing under the Hellenic Ptolemy ruling class, however, and eventually the Egyptian priesthood swallowed up the Ptolemies as they also destroyed the Aristotelian mentality of the Museum, and scientific energy was extinguished. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Carthage recovered from the Second Punic War and regained considerable prosperity although it was subjected to frequent raids from neighbors such as King Massinissa of the Numidians, who were the ancestors of the Berbers. In 151 B.C. Carthage finally declared war on Numidia (now primarily Algeria) and a year later Rome joined the battle, initiating the Third Punic War. For three years Carthage valiantly withstood the Roman siege engineered by Scipio Aemilianus, but the city finally fell and in 146 B.C. the Romans brutally plundered and burned it, possibly to prevent its falling into the hands of the Numidians. (Ref. 4) This pretty well terminated the old Phoenician Empire, but the Punic cisterns remained and street plans were preserved and later used as patterns for Roman reconstruction.

After this last Punic War Massinissa's son, Micipsa, ruled Numidia and remained an ally of Rome. Misipsa's heirs included a nephew, Jugurtha, along with his own two sons. By 116 B.C. Jugurtha had one of the sons assassinated and had run off the other and taken his own case for control of Numidia before the Roman Senate. The latter gave most of Numidia to Jugurtha except for the city of Cirta which was granted to the remaining son of Misipsa, Adherbal. Jagurtha promptly set siege to Cirt, killing off all the inhabitants including some Roman business men, thus incensing Rome and particularly the Equestrian business community. Armies were sent to North Africa once again, this time against Numidia, but Jugurtha was not defeated until his father-in-law, Bocchus, King of Mauretania, was persuaded by Lucius Cornelius Sulla to betray him. The African struggle ended in 105 B.C. with Jugurtha a prisoner and strangled in Rome. The Romans then spread west from Carthage, also controlling Morocco. (Ref. 5, 6, 7)

Polybius, the Roman historian, regarded the North African Greeks as a people considerably different from those of Greece, itself. They were olive-skinned and represented a fusion of Greek and North African natives. These were the Libyans and they were devoted to the sea, living all along the North African coast from Cyrene next to Egypt, west to Mauretania on the Atlantic. The area included not only what we now call Libya but also Tunisia, Algeria and Morocco. A long chain of ruined, once great, beautiful, marble and limestone cities now mark the places where these seafarers once lived. When Libyan kings ruled Egypt their ships sailed to the Atlantic ports of Spain and Fell (Ref. 8) says to the Americas across the Atlantic and to the Pacific via the Indian Ocean and the Malacca Strait. The ancient Libyans living west of Cyrene spoke a dialect of pre-classical Arabic containing many Berber loan words. According to Fell's hypotheses this may be the origin of the Arabic found in some American locations.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

Radio-carbon datings from the walls and potsherds of the mud buildings in the Mali region caves of the Toloy people indicate that they were still there in this century, but not subsequently. (Ref. 9) This was an era of continued Negro migrations down the entire continent. This gradual occupation of almost the whole of the arable soil of Africa in the west by Negroes and of the east and south by the Bantu-speaking groups, overall took about 1,500 years, during which time sub-Saharan Africa was largely cut off from the rest of the world.

1 [46] DURANT, WILL, The Story of Civilization. (Simon and Schuster, New York). Part I - Our Oriental Heritage. (1954).

2 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

3 [206] STILLMAN EDMUNDAND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

4 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

5 [53] DURANT, WILL and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

6 [28] CHEILIK, MICHAEL, Ancient History. (Barnes & Noble Books of Harper & Row New York et al, 1969).

7 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

8 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

9 [251] BEDAUX, ROGIER M.A., "Rediscoverring the Tellem of Mali", Archeology 35: No. 3, pp. 28-34, May/June 1982.

Africa: 100 B.C. to 0

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Meroe, now the Republic of Sudan, continued to flourish one thousand miles south of the Mediterranean and Axum continued with some prosperity in the area of northern Abyssinia, now Ethiopia.

In the first part of this century Egypt remained under the Macedonian Ptolemy Dynasty but Caesar marched into the country and took control between 48 and 47 B.C., making the famous alliance with Cleopatra, Egyptian queen. Upon his death Cleopatra made a similar alliance and dalliance with Marc Antony and such was her apparent charm that in 37 B.C. Antony gave up all interest in his government and settled with the queen in Alexandria to a life of pleasure. Stripped of his office by the Roman Senate and defeated at sea by Octavian, he committed suicide in 30 B.C. along with Cleopatra. Egypt was then formally annexed to the Roman Empire under the Emperor Octavian, although the life of the average Egyptian was probably little affected by these administrative changes. At the end of this century there were about 8,000,000 people in this country.

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Numidia, now Algeria, joined Carthage to become Roman during this century. The thick belt of megalithic tombs which have been found across north Africa date to this and the next century and thus have no chronological relationship to the similar but much more ancient ones of Europe. No explanation has been offered. The Roman historian, Sallust, of this century, writes that the Libyans were descended from a people who came from Asia Minor and were allied to the Phoenicians through their language. Arab historians have recorded similar beliefs. (Ref. 1, 2, 3) Cyrene, with its large Greek component, became a province of Rome in 74 B.C. (Ref. 4) In the Sahara, itself, water holes had essentially disappeared and there was now truly desert. The great dunes called "ergs" had formed and the rains had become most irregular.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

There was no great change in the southern two-thirds of the continent. Iron working continued to spread at a slow pace in the Niger Basin. The camel was introduced into the Sahara from Asia about 100 B.C. The Bantu speakers continued their slow migration down the eastern lands. (Ref. 5) One theory, based on archaeological and skeletal remains, suggests that at about the end of the century a few of the Caucasoid pastoralists descended from the eastern highlands into South Africa. From them some Bushmen acquired cattle and evolved into the culture of the Hottentots. (Ref. 6)

1 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

2 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

3 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

4 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

Africa: 0 to A.D. 100

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

In the south of this region the kingdom of Meroe continued its iron-making and gold production, unmolested. The kingdom of Axum in north Ethiopia and southwestern Arabia now became a strong empire, with a capital city of the same name and Adulis (now Massawa) as the Red Sea port and with a wealth founded on ivory. Axum was a pagan city of palaces and temples which now had many Jew1 and Greek immigrants. The country had many Greek insignias and a Greek educated king. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

Egypt continued under Roman rule. In Alexandria the Jewish population increased reaching perhaps to 40% of the total of the city. Among those was the Jewish philosopher and theologian, Philo, who developed the Logos ideas of the Greek Stoics into a concept which has come straight down through the centuries in the Christian theology. "God, in Philo's writings, is the essential being of the world, incorporeal, eternal, indescribable; reason can know his existence, but can ascribe no quality to him--."2 In order to create the world and establish relations with man, Philo felt that God used a group of intermediary beings. While these had been called diamones by some Greeks and Ideas by Plato, they were called angels by the Jews. Although popularly conceived as persons, Philo thought they existed only in the Divine Minds as the thoughts and powers of God, such powers as the Stoics called Logos, which created and then guided the world. "Philo sometimes thinks of the Logos as a person. In a poetic moment he called the Logos 'The first-begotten of God', son of God by the virgin Wisdom, and says that through the Logos God has revealed himself to man. Since the soul is part of God, it can through reason rise to a mystic vision, not quite of God, but of Logos3. Durant (Ref. 5) felt that Philo's Logos was one of the most influential ideas in the history of thought, although its antecedents in Heracleitus, Plato and the Stoics are obvious. "Philo was a contemporary of Christ, but he apparently never heard of him although he shared unknowingly in forming Christian theology. Philo tried to mediate between Hellenism and Judaism. From the Judaic point of view he failed; from the historical point of view he succeeded, and the result was the first chapter of the Gospel of John”.4

During the period of the Roman administration of Egypt the irrigation systems were raised to great efficiency. While the government remained Roman, the people remained Egyptian (and Jewish in the cities).1

1From this century on until the 19th century first the Aksumite and then the Christian Amhara were expansionist, seizing land and incorporating people. (Ref. 9)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Roman Carthage was the capital of proconsular Africa and second only to Rome, itself, in the western Mediterranean. It became a center for education and soon a strong- hold for early Christianity. Plutarch, living in this century, allegedly described voyages of the Carthaginians to North America (Epeiros, in his language) via Iceland (Ogygia) and a return route following the anti-trade winds around latitude 40 degrees north, back to Spain and Carthage. Diodorus of Sicily described a southern route when he spoke of the discovery of an island by Carthaginians which may have been Cuba. (Ref. 10, 11)

The ruler of Mauretania (northern Morocco and western Algeria), another Ptolemy, was murdered in A.D. 40 on the order of the Roman Caligula, but it did not destroy the Berber spirit of independence and they never completely gave up to the Romans. The dromedary, one-hump camels first were brought to the Sahara in this century but they were not used to any great extent for another seven hundred years with the Arab invasion. (Ref. 12)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

In West Africa on the inland delta of the great Niger River there existed at this time, and probably it had existed for over two hundred years, the village of Jenne-jeno, which has just recently been excavated. Situated only about 300 miles up river from Timbuktu it is probable that even in this early time there were beginning trade relationships by water. Pottery in use through this period was of a design seen several centuries earlier in the southern Sahara, indicating that the original population may have originated there. We shall hear much more about this community which did not reach its peak of development until about A.D. 100. (Ref. 13)

Madagascar had probably been unknown to men until about the time of Christ, when Indonesians arrived with out-rigger canoes and eventually sails. Beginning in this century these sea-farers brought "wet-zone" crops like the Asian and Coco yams and banana to Madagascar and thus to East Africa5. Madagascar had probably been unknown to men until about the time of Christ, when the Indonesians arrived with out-rigger canoes and eventually sails. With their new crops the Negroes found it possible to start moving into the humid forests and low-lying river valleys, thus beginning the settlement of more central Africa. The Bantu-speaking people continued their slow migration down the east coast of Africa. There was iron smelting in Kenya by A.D. 100. (Ref. 14)

1 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

2 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

3 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

4 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

5 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

6 [86] HANSEN, JAMES, "Knights of Malta, mini-nation based on Chivalry", Smithsonian 12: 112-127, Jan. 1982.

7 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

8 [311] CAPUTO, ROBERT, "Ethiopia: Revolution in an Ancient Empire", National Geographic 163, No. 5: 614- 644, May 1983.

9 [84] HAMBLIN, DORA JANE, "Carthage must be destroyed' It was but now it is reappearing", Smithsonian 9: 442, Feb. 1979.

10 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

11 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

12 [268] McINTOSH, SUSAN & RODERICK, "Finding West Africa's Oldest City", National Geographic 162: 396-417, Sept. 1982.

13 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

14 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

1.  The Falasha of today are the descendants of these Jews (Ref. 4)

2. As quoted from Durant (Ref. 6), page 501

3. The translations of these ancient writing are those of Fell (Ref. 7), page 54, and to my knowledge not otherwise confirmed

4. Quotation taken from Durant (Ref. 8), page 502

5. Hallett (Ref. 15) puts this at the 4th century C.E.

Africa: A.D. 101 to 200

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

The kingdoms of Meroe and Axum continued to develop. (See page 292) Egypt was under the rule of the Roman emperor, but beyond the mouth of the Nile, the country was actually little touched by Romanization. The royal custom of brother-sister marriage had been copied by the lower classes, and it has been estimated that by this century two-thirds of the citizens of Arsinoe were off spring of sibling unions. Alexandria was now a great trade center containing some 500,000 people, receiving goods from Red Sea ports and exporting its own manufactured products such as linen, processed Arabian drugs, Indian perfumes, papyrus, glass-ware and Egyptian grain. This city which originally was one of the greatest of the Greek cities, gradually became more and more oriental. Strife between Greeks and Jews resulted in massacres; soldiers mutinied and taxes soared.

Ptolemy, or Claudius Ptolemaeus1, was a great scientist concerned with the Alexandrian library in this century. Inspired by Hipparchus, who appeared to have provided one of the links between Babylonian and Greek science, Ptolemy wrote a mathematical treatise which became known as the Almagest. The 360 degree circle of the Babylonians was used, trigonometry was promoted and astronomy advanced, although with some errors. With 1,002 stars catalogued the heaven was considered spherical and as rotating around the immobile earth sphere. This concept made Ptolemy's theories very acceptable to the theologians of the later Middle Ages. He did have a system showing relationships of stars and planets which was effective from the practical standpoint. He also wrote a Geographical Treatise which included the geography of Marinus of Tyre. (Ref. 1)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

North Africa remained the granary of Rome, with the Moors as the dominant people of the area now developing considerable sea-power and prestige. The Moors were of Berber origin (later with an Arab mixture) and came originally from south of Morocco in the country of present Mauretania, on the great Atlantic bulge of Africa. In about A.D. 125 a locust invasion destroyed large areas of cropland and this was followed by a plague which killed perhaps 500,000 in Numidia and possibly 150,000 more on the coast. (Ref. 2)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

The changes in central, eastern and southern Africa were very slow. As noted in the last chapter, the introduction of wet zone crops like the yam and banana allowed better penetration of the Bantu-speaking blacks into the forest and low-lying river valleys and coastal plains. They also continued to drift south along the Indian Ocean coast. (Ref. 3)

1 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

2 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

1.  Not to be confused with the pharoahs of the B.C. centuries

Africa: A.D. 201 to 300

AFRICA

NORTHEASTERN AFRICA

The kingdom of Kush fell prey to desert nomads but in Ethiopia Axum continued as a powerful, well developed entity. Coins were minted and much of the Sudan to the west was conquered. Ivory, rhinoceros horn, hippopotamus hides and slaves were all exported through the Red Sea harbor of Adulis. Unfortunately even at this early period excessive rains with flooding, along with forest clearing and cultivation of hilltops and slopes had started soil erosion that was to eventually be part of the downfall of this unusual kingdom. (Ref. 1, 2)

Egyptian prestige1 began to decline under destructive factionalism, a massacre of all adult males capable of bearing arms (by Emperor Caracalla) to prevent revolt, high taxes, listless forced labor and Rome's annual exaction of grain. Sea trade from the Mediterranean went principally up the Nile to Thebes, then over to the Red Sea and on by boat. The refurbished Nile-Red Sea canal was a disappointment to the Romans (as it had been to the Ptolemies and the Persians) because winds in the northern Red Sea were unreliable and merchants did better with the Nile to Thebes route. At the last of the century (266 to 272), Queen Zenobia's conquering of Egypt and siege of Alexandria resulted in the death of half the population and helped Egypt's decline. (See IRAQ AND SYRIA, below) In A.D. 272 Egypt was reconquered by Rome. (Ref. 3)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWESTERN AFRICA

Rome continued to dominate the coast line of north Africa, but in the far northwest Moorish (chiefly Berber) culture and activity increased with expansion of the territory they controlled. The cities of the Sahara had a flourishing commerce with coastal cities, probably sending precious stones, slaves and ivory for trade. (Ref. 4)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

At this time there was the beginning of the development of the Empire of Ghana at the northern curve of the Niger River. The village of Jenne-jeno, which we have previously mentioned, may have been a part of this process. On the east the iron and cattle cultures spread almost completely to the southern tip of Africa. Blackburn was established in A.D. 105 and the use of iron spread from the Funa River (off the Congo) to Katanga and the Lakes region. In the southwest, the Khoikoi peoples, speaking the Khoisan language, only slowly gave way to the aggressive Bantu-speakers. Indonesian traders appeared in increasing numbers along the east coast in this and the following centuries.

1 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

2 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

4 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

1. Diophantus, a Greek of Alexandria, wrote a treatise of algebra, solving determinant quadratic and indeterminate equations up to the 6th degree, in about A.D. 250.

Africa: A.D. 301 to 400

AFRICA

NORTHEASTERN AFRICA

In the region of Sudan the old Kushite Kingdom had been replaced by the Kingdom of Meroi, although the basic population remained a Kush people. The new kingdom had a unique African character but it did not thrive long, apparently conquered sometime between 320 and the end of the century by neighboring Axum of northern Ethiopia. The name "Kush" now disappeared, to be replaced by "Nubia". The Nobatae, coming from Kordofan and the Blemmyes (Bela) coming from the Nile Valley to the east, blended with the old Kushites to form the population of medieval Nubia. Before Christianity came to this area there are indications that this was, in modern terminology, a "swinging place". Remnants of a large tavern constructed in the middle of the century at Ibrim indicate that the wine flowed freely up to about A.D. 500. (Ref. 1, 2) The populous Axum had adopted the Monophysite Christian faith and this new religion was the foundation of the kingdom which was soon to be called Abyssinia. By 362 this kingdom also included a portion of the southern Arabian area. A distinguishing feature of Axum was the use of stone-masonry without mortar. There is still standing a 23 meter high obelisk, simulating a nine-story palace, constructed in this 4th century when this state was considered one of the four world powers. (Ref. 3) The Axum emperor, King Ezana, had been converted to Monophysitism by the Syrian Frumentius who had originally been shipwrecked on the Red Sea coast.

The resulting Ethiopian Orthodox Church, actually a branch of the Egyptian Coptic, spread over the highland of north Ethiopia. (Ref. 4, 5)

In Egypt there was political and cultural decline. Christianity made many converts along the coast but of the Monophysite variety. This sect believed that there was only one nature in God and Jesus, with a complete denial of the Trinity. This faith survives today in some eastern areas and, as suggested above, particularly in Ethiopia. Arianism, another great "heresy" which was mentioned above, also originated in Alexandria. In contrast to the dogma of the Monophysites, Arius preached that Christ was not one with God but rather the Logos (See Philo, page 297), the first and highest of all created beings. The Son was neither coeternal with nor consubstantial with the Father. Politically, Egypt remained nominally under the Roman Empire, even as it began to collapse. A popular literature in the Coptic language appeared in this century. (Ref. 6, 7)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

The coast line of North Africa remained subject to Roman control as the Christian faith spread across the area. As in the last century, in the west the Berber-Moors became more and more prolific and independent. Although camels had been present in Africa previously they now came into extensive use by the Berbers, a feature which helped them to become formidable opponents to all foreigners along the coast. In the 370s Firmus, a Moorish chieftain, rebelled against the Roman Valentian I and was stopped only after a series of massacres. (Ref. 8, 9)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

There was very little significant change from the last century. In the west the Empire of Ghana continued its development, while all along the east coast the Bantu-speakers expanded and more Indonesian traders appeared bringing the Asian yam and taro from Southeast Asia. The latest estimate of the time of the establishment of Great Zimbabwe by Bantu-speaking blacks is A.D. 320 (150 years). These were the Gokomere people and they may either have lived there or simply used it as a camp. There is some evidence that they had iron. (Ref. 10, 11, 12, 13)

1 271. ANDERSON, ROBERT D., "Qasr Ibrim: Watchdog of the Nile", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 58-60, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

3 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

6 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

7 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

8 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

9 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

10 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

13 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

Africa: A.D. 401 to 500

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Ethiopia continued to be a Christian area in communication with southern Arabia and Egypt. Axum expansion in the first half of the century was followed by a period of stagnation in the last half although Byzantine missionaries and traders continued to visit the region. Nominally under Axumite control, Nubia apparently was not really Christianized in this century. The religious and political confusion of this period is apparent in four papyri recently discovered at Qasr Ibrim. Three were written in Sahidic Coptic and the fourth in provincial Greek. The Coptic ones were all addressed to Tantani, Governor of Nubia and apparently Christian. The Greek document is from a pagan king of the Blemmyes to the king of Noubades and refers to a former supreme king of Nubia, called Silco. (Ref. 1, 2)

Nominally still under control of Rome, Egyptic Society, according to Toynbee (Ref. 3), became extinct in this century leaving no "off-spring" in any subsequent society, to date. The little intellectual activity that remained in the remnants of the Roman Empire was now centered in Byzantium, but considerable religious maneuvering continued in Alexandria. Cyril, Patriarch of Alexandria, and later one of the two or three St. Cyrils, led a great struggle against Nestorianism which finally culminated in the Council of Ephesus in 431. Cyril presided and had the support of Pope Celestine 1. His doctrines, although considered orthodox at the time, were actually in part those of Monophysitism and after him this became the national faith of Egypt - eventually the Coptic Church. (Ref. 4)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

In contrast to Egypt this part of Africa was a very busy place. In the far west Morocco was invaded and conquered by Berbers coming from the southwest, and then they even attacked the Roman holdings, using newly domesticated camels. In 427 Bonifatius, Roman military commander in north Africa, was about to be cut out of command by enemies in the emperor's court in Ravenna, so he rebelled and called upon the Vandals of Spain to come to his aid. In the following year, Asding Vandals from Spain did go to north Africa, sailing with a large fleet under King Gaiseric who proceeded to conquer most of north Africa, eventually even Carthage (A.D. 455) and then Sardinia, Corsica and the western part of Sicily. The total number of Vandals leaving Spain was probably not over 80,000 but they had the advantage of local social unrest and the cooperation of Bonifatius and thus met little local resistance. Many Berbers and the Donatist heretic group of Christians with about one-half of their bishops also helped the invaders against the Romans. The Donatists were the followers of the once Bishop of Carthage, Donatus, who denied the efficacy of sacraments administered by priests who were themselves in a state of sin, and the Church, willing to risk so much on the virtues of the clergy, repudiated the idea.

As a result of their persecution the Donatists became bands of revolutionists, at once both Christian and communist, condemning poverty and slavery and ending in fanaticism, happy to help the Vandals, who were Arian Christians. Once Gaiseric had obtained Carthage he used the facilities there to greatly augment his navy and subsequently was able to actually sack Rome, itself. Barry Fell (Ref. 5) believes that some orthodox Christians actually sailed to North America at this time to escape the Vandals. According to Herodotus, the Garamantes of Fezzan in the desert had horse-drawn chariots, probably obtained from Egypt. (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10)

Among the more orthodox Christians of North Africa was St. Augustine, who had become converted from paganism and sin as a youth and who later wrote extensive theological dissertations rationalizing the religion and establishing many Catholic doctrines, as he introduced some element of Greek philosophy into Christianity. It was mentioned in the last chapter that Thomas (Ref. 11) considers him one of the four great "fathers" of the Catholic church. He was killed during one of the Vandals' sieges.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

In the Sudan, the roots of the great African Kingdom of Ghana may date back to A.D. 400. Certainly the town of Jenne-Jeno was prospering at the inland delta of the Niger. The eroded foundation of a house has been excavated along with pottery and urns for burial and remains of a wall about three meters wide and four or more meters high that girded the city. All of these things have been dated to this or the next century or two. In central Africa there was continued proliferation of the black people, particularly the Bantu-speakers. (Ref. 12, 13)

1 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [271] ANDERSON, ROBERT D., "Qasr Ibrim: Watchdog of the Nile", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 58-60, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

4 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

5 [48] DURANT, WILL, Ibid., Part III - Caesar and Christ. (1944).

6 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

9 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

10 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

11 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

12 [268] McINTOSH, SUSAN & RODERICK, "Finding West Africa's Oldest City", National Geographic 162: 396-417, Sept. 1982.

13 [154] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

Africa: A.D. 501 to 600

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

There were three separate Christian kingdoms in the region of Nubia in the middle Nile. At Ibrim an old temple, which was originally built probably during the Ethiopian Dynasty of Egypt in the 7th century B.C. and then modified later with typical Meriotic graffiti and votive inscriptions, was now made into the earliest of Ibrim Christian churches. A defensive wall around the church is now partially covered by Lake Nasser. (Ref. 1)

Early Abyssinians were active militarily, invading the Yemeni kingdoms on the Arabian Peninsula. In the middle of the century Axum was at the height of its power with a splendid court boasting royal elephants and gold. The capital city funneled materials from inner Africa to a maritime network reaching as far as Spain and even China. Axum covered an area of 75 hectares and contained many multistory stone buildings with 10,000 to 20,000 inhabitants and a fringe of suburban, elite villages. (Ref. 2) But the downfall of this country started when the Persians expelled the Axumites from south Arabia as a part of the Byzantine-Persian Wars. This was followed by raids by pagan Bela on the farmlands, so that gradually the people moved deeper into the highlands, merging with the pagan and Judaized people there and becoming the Abyssinians proper, the nucleus of later Ethiopia. (Ref. 3, 4)

Egypt continued to decay, politically and intellectually. Part of this was promoted by the decline in the incense trade which had previously come from the south, in part through Egypt. The country remained nominally under the control of the Byzantine Empire.

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

The Vandal kingdom of North Africa was reconquered for the Byzantine Empire by Justinian's General Belisarius in 533. Otherwise North Africa remained much as in the last century. (Ref. 5)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

In the tropical regions the availability of iron after A.D. 500 led to the development of kingdoms whose chief weapons were iron spears. A few Negroid Bantu-speakers filtered into the Bushman and Hottentot domains in South Africa. (Ref. 6, 7)

1 [271] ANDERSON, ROBERT D., "Qasr Ibrim: Watchdog of the Nile", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 58-60, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [82] GROVE, NOEL, "North Yemen", National Geographic 156: 244, Aug. 1979.

4 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

7 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

Africa: A.D. 601 to 700

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

The Ethopian upland soils had been largely destroyed, exposing underlying rocks. In the middle of the century, threatened by Muslim neighbors, Axum lost its Red Sea ports and had its gold supply cut off so its Christians retreated to the highlands, where they remained in isolation until the 15th century. Abandoned buildings deteriorated and contributed to the soil destruction. Land abandonment can be as destructive as over-use and there can be little doubt that all this exacerbated Axumite economic decline. (Ref. 1)

To the west in Nubia, Coptic Christians thrived. After an Egyptian attack in 651-652 relations between Christian Nubia and Moslem Egypt were formalized by treaty which included an agreement that Nubians would return all runaway slaves to Egypt. A cathedral was built about A.D. 700 in Qasr Ibrim and there were plans to make this a pilgrimage center. Nubia hereafter remained Christian for about 700 years. Just north of the present-day Aswan Dam, the survival of paganism into this 7th century on the island of Philae had been a notable scandal stimulating Byzantine missions into the area. (Ref. 2)

Egypt fell to the Persians temporarily in 616 but fell again to the Arabs later in the century, with Alexandria conquered by the latter in 660. The Monophysite Christians of Egypt actually helped the Moslems overthrow the existing administration. After the conquest, Amr ruled for the Arabs and did so well. (Ref. 3, 4)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

In the last third of the century the raiding Moslems easily took Tripolitania but on their original drive westward they were repulsed from Tunisia by Roman Empire troops. Subsequently, however, conversion of the indigenous Berbers1 to Islam in 696 gave Islam a new push and the Byzantine forces in Tunisia were then overrun and Carthage was destroyed again. Soon Morocco also fell to the Islamic onslaught. Shortly thereafter trade routes for slaves, ivory and gold opened up between Morocco-Algeria and the western Sudan. The Murabits (also Almoravids) of Morocco turned south, shattering the Negro Empire of Ghana.

The Berbers were of an entirely different race from the Arabs, having roundish heads contrasting with the Arabs' long heads. Even when some were initially converted to Islam, allowing the Moslem advance, most of the Berbers retreated to the naked mountains dividing Tunisia's coastal plains from the desert. Even so, the Muslims made a greater impact on these people than Rome or Christianity had previously done. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

From 500 to 1,200 ancient Ghana, in what is now Mali, monopolized the gold trade from west Africa to Europe. It sat at the southern end of the trans-Saharan caravan routes and thus acted as the hub. Kumbi Saleh was a city of 15,000 people. The excavated ruins of the ancient city of Jenne-Jeno had a formidable three meter-wide wall surrounding it which was constructed sometime between 400 and 800. Delicately constructed gold jewelry has been found under this city wall, indicating that this was a trade center over a long period of time. The nearest gold mines were 800 kilometers south of this developing city. (Ref. 10) The Moslem invasion of Ghana from the north caused some disruption in administration certainly, but did not destroy the fundamental culture or the developing cities.

In the far southeast of Africa the Leopard's Kopje people, a Bantu-speaking group, were in control of Great Zimbabwe from about A.D. 600 to 850. (Ref. 11) Elsewhere the great bulk of Africa remained as in previous centuries.

1 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [271] ANDERSON, ROBERT D., "Qasr Ibrim: Watchdog of the Nile", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 58-60, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

4 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

6 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

7 [58] EDWARDS, MIKE, "Tunisia: Sea, Sand, Success", National Geographic 157: 184, Feb. 1980.

8 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

9 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

10 [268] McINTOSH, SUSAN & RODERICK, "Finding West Africa's Oldest City", National Geographic 162: 396-417, Sept. 1982.

11 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

1.  "Berber" is an Arab word meaning "barbarian"

Africa: A.D. 701 to 800

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

In the last chapter we told of the collapse of Axum. Apparently as a last gasp. the Axumites made an unsuccessful attack on Mecca in A.D. 702 which was followed by Arab retaliation and Butzer (Ref. 1) says that it was at that time that the port of Adulis was destroyed and many Red Sea islands seized. At the same time the Christian monarchy had to withstand ravaging attacks by pagan Beja. (Ref. 2) After 765 Axum was almost completely abandoned.

The horn of Africa was not affected by the Bedouin Arabs, but the people there still retained close ties with Arabia. Of the three kingdoms of the middle Nile which had originated in the 6th century, the two northern ones now merged to form the Kingdom of Nubia, with a capital at Dongola, exerting its influence from the 1st to the 4th cataract of the Nile and west to Darfur. The country was Christian, prosperous and used a highly decorative pottery and developed a lucrative slave trade to Egypt. There was a gradual peaceful infiltration of Moslem Arabs into the area. Farther south at the confluence of the Nile was the Kingdom of Alwa, with its capital at Soba. It resisted the Moslem faith a little longer. (Ref. 3, 4)

Egypt was entirely under Moslem Arab control with supervision direct from the caliph in Damascus and later Baghdad.

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

This entire region was now under Moslem control, subject to the caliph in the Middle East. As mentioned in the last chapter, the Berbers of Tunisia and Morocco adopted Islam as they had previously adopted Christianity: with neither was it a total embracement and they, in addition, clung also to older tribal beliefs. Although called "Berbers" by the Arabs they called themselves "Imazighen", "Men of the Land", and their tongue, totally unlike the official Arabic, was Tamazight, still spoken today. (Ref. 5) The great Roman ports all over the Mediterranean were allowed to decline. Although they could sail the Indian Ocean, the Arabs ignored Mediterranean shipping routes and went overland with of central Tunisia, was the administrative center for the Arab Empire in the Maghrib. (Ref. 6)

Although the Omayyad Dynasty controlled the entire Moslem world in the first half of the century, as was intimated above, the Abbasids took over in A.D. 750 with Caliph Harun al Rashid establishing a capital at Baghdad. By A.D. 788 Morocco had declared its independence from Baghdad and Tunisia followed just after the turn of the new century. The new Moroccon Empire was to last over a millennium. (Ref. 7, 8)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

About A.D. 700 people from the upper Nile moved into Chad, just east of Nigeria, and established a string of cities. At about the same time traders were becoming ever more daring in crossing the Sahara to obtain gold and slaves. The increasing use of camels greatly facilitated this traffic and the traffic, in turn, seemed to monopolize the supply of gold and slaves and thus developed more systematic and larger operations. Ghana seems to have come under the control of a new dynasty in this century and this may have been the transfer of authority from Berber to Negro rulers.

Merchants of south Arabia, the Persian Gulf and northwestern India had long traded along the east African coast for palm oil, ivory, tortoise shell, rhinoceros horn and slaves. Finally some of the Asians settled in east Africa and they were soon joined by religious refugees from Oman and Shirax on the Persian Gulf . These Asians were responsible for the beginning of a chain of independent settlements all along the coast. They became city-states and because Arab shipping soon supplanted earlier traffic, all soon became Moslem. Excavations on the shore of Lake Kisale in northern Katanga (between Angola and the Great Lakes) indicate that in this 8th century there was a dense population using fine pottery and elaborate copper jewelry. This may be the original home of the Luba people (Ref. 9)

The population on Madagascar now included Indonesians, Arabs and Negroes, the later probably originally slaves or concubines. The Negroes multiplied more rapidly, probably because of greater resistance to malaria, but there was much intermarriage and soon a unique "Malagasy" people emerged. (Ref. 10)

The central rain forest of Africa and the semi-arid south remained untouched by civilized men, although the Bantu-speaking tribesmen continued to spread their settlements through the forest of the Congo basin and still farther south. The Leopard's Kopje people were still in control of Zimbabwe. (Ref. 11, 12)

1 270. BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

3 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

4 [271] ANDERSON, ROBERT D., "Qasr Ibrim: Watchdog of the Nile", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 58-60, Sept./Oct. 1982.

5 [104] HUNT, CARLA, "Berber Brides' Fair", National Geographic 157: 119, Jan. 1980.

6 83. HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

9 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

10 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

11 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

12 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

Africa: A.D. 801 to 900

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

The old Axum monarchy established a new residence deep in the interior of Ethiopia around Lake Hayq sometime before A.D. 870. This was actually a Christian monastery with some 300 clerics. The old Axumite area was given up entirely to invading sheep herders. (Ref. 1) Nubia remained essentially as in the last century.

Egypt was a Moslem state but independently ruled by the Tulunid Dynasty. These men were Turkish in origin, having been brought into Islam as professional soldiers. One of them, Ahmad ibn Tulun (869-884) conquered Syria to add to his realm. Egypt, as the ancient granary for southern Europe, no long robbed of its products by foreign masters, entered upon a minor renaissance, with new learning and art, palaces, public baths, a hospital and a great mosque honoring Tulun.

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

All of the original Moslem provinces in north Africa were now more or less independent with separate rulers. After 800 Tunisia was ruled by the Aghlabid Dynasty until the end of the century when they were overthrown by the Kotama, a Berber tribe from Kabylia. Morocco, under the Idrisids, had founded a Shi'ite caliphate in 789 which had carried on into this century. Still farther west, just on the Mediterranean side of the Straits of Gibralter, were the Rostemids. (Ref. 2, 3) (Please see map in connection with CENTRAL EUROPE, this chapter.)

There were three major trade routes across the Sahara at this time. One went from Fezzan to Kanem, running north of Lake Chad; a second went from Gao, on the Niger bend, to central Maghrib; and the third ran from the western Maghrib to Ghana. (Ref. 4)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

Commerce across the Sahara brought gold and slaves to the Mediterranean and stimulated the early Negro states of the sub-Saharan regions. Ghana had few natural resources of its own and its wealth was derived from levies imposed on this trade across the desert. We have seen in previous chapters how Jenne-jeno developed as a trade center on the Niger. By 800 it had perhaps 10,000 people and an extensive riverine trade with the Timbuktu region. (Ref. 5) To the Arabs, the ruler of Ghana was reputed to be the richest and most powerful monarch in all the Biladas-Sudan (Land of Blacks). Around

Lake Chad the empire of Kanem-Bornu developed about the beginning of this 9th century and survived for a millenium. This kingdom, founded by Zaghawa nomads, was originally only one of the seven Hausa city-states, each protected by strong city walls and excelling as manufacturers and long distance merchants. (Ref. 6, 7)

On the east coast of Africa a great wave of trading activity swept the countries bordering the Indian Ocean, resulting in a string of city-states along that coast, most of them founded by Muslims from the Persian Gulf and some from southern Arabia. Bantu-speaking Negroes soon joined them to produce a distinct culture and language (Swahili). Farther south in Zimbabwe, the Shona and particularly the Karangas sub-group, continued in this century to develop agriculture, stock raising, gold and copper trading and the building of large stone edifices. They probably originally came from iron-rich Katanga and had an advanced knowledge of iron mining and metallurgy. They soon became the overlords of the indigenous Gokomere and Leopard's Kopje people as the Rhodesian plateau became a beehive of gold, copper and iron production. The products went to the Arab merchants on the coast. The Shona civilization lasted until A.D. 1500. (Ref. 8, 9, 10)

1 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

5 [268] McINTOSH, SUSAN & RODERICK, "Finding West Africa's Oldest City", National Geographic 162: 396-417, Sept. 1982.

6 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

7 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

8 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

9 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

10 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

Africa: A.D. 901 to 1000

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

The off-shore islands of Ethiopia thrived on the export of Abyssinian slaves. Some apparently escaped to settle in Danakil and Somali, there to intermarry and become converted to Islam. Inland royal power was assumed in the mountain region of Lasta sometime after A.D. 940 by a non-Semitic Zagwe Dynasty. While these people became Christianized, Semitic farmers expanded southward along the forested spine of Ethiopia to modern Addis Ababa. At the same time Sidama tribesmen invaded from south and east. (Ref. 1, 2)

In 905 the Turkish Tulunid Dynasty of Egypt gave way to the Ikhshidids who, in turn, were again subject to the Abbasid caliphate of Damascus although this domination was short lived as the empire began to split. At the end of the century the Fatimids moved in from northwestern Africa to take control of Egypt. They were a branch of the Isma'ilites, claiming descent from Mohammed's daughter, Fatima. Sugar cane was now grown in Egypt, with the sugar produced by an advanced process. (Ref. 3, 4)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

We noted in the last chapter that the Aghlabid Dynasty had fallen to the Berbers. In this century these victors welcomed Ubaid Allah, a Shi'ite "Mahdi"1 from Syria, who used the Berber armies to establish a new north African, Fatimid Dynasty. They destroyed Tahert and dominated Fez, eventually establishing their capital in Cairo as they assumed control in Egypt. (Ref. 5) The Moroccan Idrisids resisted for some time, but with the Spanish Omayyids attacking also from the north, the Moroccans finally fell to the Fatimids. (Ref. 6) As the Berbers expanded northward in Morocco and the Arabs came westward along the coast, there was a shift in the balance between the sedentary cultivators and the nomadic pastoralists. Nevertheless, Morocco, Algiers and Tunisia had a renewed prosperity with the establishment of great trade routes across the Sahara and increased commerce with Spain. In the desert, itself, however, cruel famines were suffered by small towns and warfare contributed further to their demise. (Ref. 7, 8)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

By the end of this century most of Africa was out of the Stone Age. (Ref. 9) It was the time of the apogee of the Kingdom of Ghana with its capital at Kumbi and extending from near the Atlantic coast almost to Timbuktu. It was essentially Negro, consisting of a group of federated tribes with a fairly well developed culture. Writing of the wealth and wisdom of this African kingdom, the Moslem Ibn Hawqal said that Ghana boasted that its people had hoards of gold and "the wealthiest of all kings on the face of the earth"2. The recently excavated city of Jenne-jeno reached the height of its development and by the end of the century may have had close to 20,000 people. This and satellite communities had penetrated the marketplace of North Africa. Goods, produce and gold flowed north via river and caravan while Saharan salt and Mediterranean glass beads came south. (Ref. 10)

Pressure from the Berbers now forced the city-states of Chad to unite into a kingdom called Kanem-Bornu, or the Kanuri Empire, founded by a desert people and having the longest surviving dynasty in history, not being overthrown until the 19th century. A trans-Saharan slave trade running from west Africa east to the Arabs began in this century and lasted for hundreds of years. (Ref. 12, 13, 14) The Arabs began to colonize the east coast as far south as Zanzibar but never reached or knew of Madagascar, in this century. (Ref. 15) Ancestors of present day Kikuyu tribes migrated into Kenya from the south. They were Bantu-speakers who were in the process of spreading out from the Congo in the transition period from Stone Age hunting to the Iron Age and agriculture. (Ref. 16, 17) Zimbabwe continued to be occupied by the Shona people who traded in copper and gold.

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [8]. HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

6 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

9 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

10 [268.] McINTOSH, SUSAN & RODERICK, "Finding West Africa's Oldest City", National Geographic 162: 396-417, Sept. 1982.

11 [154] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

12 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

13 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

14 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

15 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

1.  "Mahdi" is a Moslem title of an expected spiritual and temporal ruler destined to reign righteously over the world

2.  Quotation from historical map of the National Geographic Society, (Ref. 11)

Africa: A.D. 1001 to 1100

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

In Ethiopia there was a revival of power under the Cushitic-speaking Zagwe Dynasty. Old documents link King Yimrha-Kristos to the Egyptian Coptic patriarchs Cyril II (1,077-1,092) and Michael (1,092-1102). Meanwhile the Semitic component of the country spread westward from Addis Ababa to include Lake Tana by 1,100. (Ref. 1) Nubia, in the region between the 1st and 4th cataracts of the Nile, continued to have two separate kingdoms, one the Kingdom of Nubia and the other, farther south, the Kingdom of Alwa. (Ref. 2)

Egypt remained an Arab, Moslem state under the Fatimid Dynasty throughout this century. As noted in the last chapter, these Shi'ite rulers had invaded from the west, having first had a base in Tunisia and an army of Berber tribesmen. They developed Cairo as their capital.

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWESTERN AFRICA

Morocco and Tunisia had a continuing change of emirates and the situation was complicated by the return of hordes of Spanish Moors, who were being run out of Spain. When the Berber Zirid Dynasty tried to become independent of Cairo, the Fatimids sent armies of Bedouin Arabs against them and they succeeded in devastating the region and its economy. At about that same time, on an island just off the Moroccan coast, Ibn Yasin, with some Sahara desert followers, formed a dedicated band and with thousands of camel men, launched a "jihad"1, driving eastward, overrunning all western, north Africa (the Mahgrib), some of Ghana and even part of Spain, establishing the Almoravid Dynasty2. A concept of Moroccan unity was born and Marakesh was developed as the capital of this new ruling group in 1062.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

The acme of the Ghana Empire may have occurred in the first half of this century. The inhabitants were the Negroid Soninke (Sarakole) branch of Mande-speakers. They dominated well over 100,000 square miles of territory with an efficient administration and an army of 200,000, including 40,000 bowmen. Their horses had gold trappings and their guard dogs had gold collars. Al Bakri, writing in 1067, said that the houses were of two stories, with warehouses on the ground floor and living quarters above. The Soninke had their own pagan religion, but they allowed Muslims in their territory. In the second half of the century drought, famine and pillage of the capital city by the Almoravids (1076) started the empire into decline. The invading Moslems were helped by non-Moslem Berbers who needed the salt mines of Ankar. It is probable that the city of Jennejeno, whose development we have followed in previous chapters, participated in this decline as it known that its population decreased, despite new commerce with North Africa. (Ref. 4) As Ghana fell, successor states included Diara, Soso, two Mossi states and Manding, or Mali, formed by the Malinke Mande. The ruler of the latter was a Moslem living in the rapidly growing city of Timbuktu. Subject to Mali was an adjacent empire in the middle Niger called Songhoy and at about this same time a people called the "Telem" took over the old abandoned granaries in the caves of the Bandiagara cliff in Mali and used this as a burial place for their dead. (See page 234, volume 1). One cave alone has been found to have 3,000 skeletons. (Ref. 5)

By this time most of the desert nomads had been converted to Islam, which had spread south from the Maghrib into the states of the Sudan with Muslim merchants as they crossed the Sahara. This dangerous trans-Sahara trade carried luxury goods, eventually fire-arms and salt, a vital element in the diet of tropical countries. On the reverse, north trek went gold, leather work and slaves. (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9) This was the era when the one-humped camel (dromedary) really became of greatest importance in the desert. These hot, dry-country animals could carry 700 to 800 "light pounds". A caravan of 6,000 camels could carry 2,400 to 3,000 tons or the load of 4 to 6 medium sized sailing ships of that period. (Ref. 10)

Farther east there was the country of Kanem, which had no gold but did a brisk business of exporting slaves. In this century Kanem accepted Islam and under Mai Dunama I, the borders of the state were extended northward across the desert to Fezzan and westward into Hausaland. Dunama is said to have had 30,000 horsemen, cultural and commercial links with the Middle East and to have maintained a rest house in Cairo for pilgrims going from Kanem to Mecca. (Ref. 11, 12)

In the dense rain forest of central Africa, Pygmoid and Bushmanoid hunters continued to be present and the Bantu-speaking Negroids had already been migrating down the rivers from the Sudanic belt to that area and were gradually spreading east and south. The Luba people may have been well established in the Lake Kisale region of northern Katanga for three centuries. The Kenya highlands and adjoining northern Tanzania were also already well populated. The original inhabitants, as previously noted, were Caucasoids called "Azanians" and by tradition were tall, bearded and red-skinned. Gradually through the centuries, however, these had been gradually absorbed by the Nilo-Hamites and the Bantu-speaking Negroids. The latter were also filtering into the south into the territory of the Bushmen. Some buildings were erected at Zimbabwe in this century, beginning the development of another great empire which would flower some centuries hence. (Ref. 13, 14)

1 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

3 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [268] McINTOSH, SUSAN & RODERICK, "Finding West Africa's Oldest City", National Geographic 162: 396-417, Sept. 1982.

5 [251] BEDAUX, ROGIER M.A., "Rediscoverring the Tellem of Mali", Archeology 35: No. 3, pp. 28-34, May/June 1982.

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

8 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

9 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

10 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

11 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

12 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

13 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

14 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

1.  This means a "holy war"

2.  In a newer terminology this is called the Murabit Dynasty. (Ref. 3)

Africa: A.D. 1101 to 1200

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

This was a period of building in the Lasta Kingdom of Ethiopia, with imported Egyptian artisans and materials for church construction. One of the greatest of the Lasta Zagwe kings was Lalibela, who came to power in 1195. Ethiopian records of this era were not kept indefinitely because later dominant dynasties considered the Zagwe an "usurping" one. (Ref. 1) The cathedral built about A.D. 700 in Qasr Ibrim, Nubia, was originally dedicated to the Virgin Mary, but after a raid in 1172-1173 by Shams ed-Dowla, brother of Saladin, it was converted into a mosque. Its ruins remain today as a small island in Lake Nasser. (Ref. 2)

The death throes of the Fatimid caliphate came about not by Christian Crusaders but by the expansion of Nureddin and his Zangid Sultanate from Syria. Nureddin continued to live at Mosul and let Egypt be ruled by a Kurdish general, Saladin, who then proceeded to set up his own Ayyubid Dynasty in 1174. Islam glorified in the integrity and justice of his rule and even Christendom acknowledged him as a gentleman and scholar, even though a foe. At his death in 1193 his realm again became divided. (Ref. 3, 4)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

The Norman, Roger of Sicily, annexed the Zirid Emirate of Tunisia about 1153, but as Saladin took over Egypt, a Shi'ite empire was created farther west by a Berber tribe led by another supposed "Mahdi" and this Almohade Dynasty1 replaced the Almoravids and gave Barbary its finest hour. They defeated the remaining Zirids and finally even ran the Normans from Tunisia. (Ref. 5, 6)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

The Tellem people continued to flourish in Mali. Men wore robes made of cotton strips sewn together, with waistbands or leather aprons and cotton caps. The women wore short fiber aprons, occasionally with the front pulled back between the legs to fasten to a waistband behind. They had leather sandals decorated with incised geometric designs, leather bags and knife sheaths. Personal ornamentation included beads, iron, wood or bronze pendants, iron and leather bracelets and cylindrical quartz plugs worn in noses or ears of both sexes.

Ife, a kingdom south of Nok (Nigeria), flourished from 1100 to 1500 and produced the greatest artistic creations of tropical Africa. Ife bronzes were cast by the "lost wax" process which is still in use for some purposes today. (Ref. 7) Timbuktu was a trade center of this century, servicing the empires of Manding and Songhoy. Great stone buildings were erected in Great Zimbabwe as the Shona people made it the capital of their powerful state. (Ref. 8, 9) (Please also see the 15th century C.E. where there is a summary of several centuries of activity in this part of Africa).

1 270. BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [271] ANDERSON, ROBERT D., "Qasr Ibrim: Watchdog of the Nile", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 58-60, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

5 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

6 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

7 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [35] COBB, CHARLES E.,JR., "After Rhodesia, a Nation named Zimbabwe", National Geographic 160: 616-651, Nov. 1981).

1.  In newer terminology this is the Muwahid Dynasty

Africa: A.D. 1201 to 1300

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

In the highlands of Ethiopia there were several Muslim sultanates. In Lasta, King Labibela, who gave his name to the capital city, is credited with 11 monumental rock-cut churches. Egyptian Coptic refugees were allegedly welcome here, as Labibela attempted to establish a "new Jerusalem". Juniper trees were planted (in place of cedars), a local stream was named the "Jordan River" and a grove of olives became the "Mount of Olives". (Ref. 1) Nearer the coast this rejuvenated dynasty line from the old Axumite kings gave way in 1270 to a new family claiming to be a restoration of the old Solomon line, calling themselves the Solomonid Dynasty. These Amharic-speaking people developed a true Ethiopian culture and came in conflict with the Muslim coastal states on the Horn of Africa, notably Adal. The Solomonid ruler became known as the "King of Kings" and had many vassal kings under him. Christianity in this area then began to absorb many Judaic and pagan practices from the mixed peoples living there. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

Nubia was invaded by Sultan Baibars of Egypt in the middle of the century and a puppet ruler was set up and tribute paid to the Mamluks.

The descendant of the Kurd, Saladin, ruled Egypt in the first third of this century and one of the greatest achievements of the time was the building of the Mansur Hospital in Cairo, a very large institution which had separate wards for different diseases such as fevers, eye problems, female disorders, etc. Ruling the country in about 1238, Sultan al-Salih, to augment his Turkoman army, purchased white slaves from the Mongols as they crossed southern Russia. These slaves were mixtures of Cumans, Circassians and Alans and they became the most powerful cavalry unit in the Egyptian army and were known as mamluks from the Arabic verb "to own". The practice of taking such men as royal bodyguards had been started by the caliphs of Baghdad, who could not trust even their own relatives. The last Egyptian sultan of the Kurd Ayyubin line died in 1249 and after a few murders, one of the white slave Mamluks named Aybak married Queen Shajar al-Durr, founded the Burji Dynasty and became the first Mamluk sultan of Egypt. After seven years Aybak made the mistake of trying to add a new wife, the daughter of the ruler of Mosul, Iraq. Queen Shajar al-Durr murdered him in his bath, but she, in turn, received the same type of death three days later from Aybak's loyal concubines. (Ref. 5, 6)

The Mamluk General Baibars (also Baybars) led an army through Palestine, thwarting the last of the Crusaders, and then went on to defeat his former captors in a great battle at Ain Jalut in 1260 and the Mongol advance was stopped. As a result of these victories Baibars was elevated to be sultan and he proceeded to be one of the most cruel, ambitious and yet able of the Mamluks. He traded ambassadors with the Mongol Berke in Russia and persuaded him to wage war against fellow Mongol Hulegu in the Middle East, thus pinching the latter's forces between them. He brought the last Abbasid caliph to Cairo from the destroyed Baghdad, set him up as a puppet and then proceeded to form a strong administration, reconstruct fortresses, roads, bridges and canals, although late in the century the old Necho canal from the Nile to Red Sea was filled in. He had a regular postal service between Egypt and his domains in Syria. At the height of his career, in 1277, he was poisoned. With the subsequent reign of Qalawun (1279-1290) the Bahri1 Mamluk Empire reached its height and the prosperity continued with his family successors until the middle of the next century. It was a period of a full treasury and resulting commissioning of great works of art, both secular and religious, including great palaces and mosques, manuscripts, glass vessels inlaid with gold and other treasures. (Ref. 7, 8)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

All of north Africa had changes of regimes during this century. When the Baghdad Caliphate was destroyed by the Mongols, the Hafsid Dynasty took the title of calph in Africa in A.D. 1259 and assumed control of Tunisia and some of Morocco. In the latter area the Almohades were in collapse because of their losses in Spain to the Christians, and they were displaced by the Marinid Sultan of Fez in 1269. Both Fez and Marraqesh were great Moroccon cities, exceeded in population by very few European cities of that time.

Algeria was taken over by still another dynasty, the Zujanids. All of these north African states contributed to trans-Saharan trade and the crossing of the great desert by these medieval Arab merchants was a tremendous undertaking. Caravans could cover 200 miles in a week but were subject to black-veiled Taureg pirates and if wells and oases failed, men and beasts alike could perish. (Ref. 10, 11, 12)

The area was not devoid of intellectual activity. Hasan published tables of sines for each degree and Nasir ud Din wrote a treatise on trigonometry. In addition the whole science of botany was revised by these Arab-Berbers.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

In western Africa in the great bend of the Niger River, several states vied for supremacy. At the beginning of the century, Sumanguru, greatest of the rulers of Soso, next to the Mossi states, plundered the old capital of Ghana, Kumbi, and in 1224 conquered and annexed Manding. This situation was reversed 11 years later, however, when the Mandingos defeated the ruler of Soso and re-established independence, in a decisive battle of Kirina. This cleared the way for the creation of Mali as a successor state to Ghana and it became the second great empire of the western Sudan, extending from the Lower Gambia and Senegal rivers to the Niger-Benue junction. In contrast to the Ghana homeland, which was in a semi-arid sahil, the Mali center was in a fertile agricultural land a little to the south and they even had better access to gold. Sundiata was the warrior hero of these conquering Malinke Mandingos. Exactly where the recently excavated city of Jennejeno fits into this new empire is not clear, but it is known that this ancient city was already starting to decline in this century. The Tellem territory near the Bandigara cliff at the bend of the Niger apparently was never governed politically by the Mali and evidently offered refuge.

In Ife, Nigeria, superb sculptured heads reached a peak production in this and the next century. It was the holy city of the Yoruba tribe and home of its priest-king, the Oni. Some of the sculptures are believed to represent former Onis. (Ref. 13, 14, 15, 16)

In the region of the southern Congo was the Lunda-Luba Empire. The trading states on the east coast were in a golden age with the Indian Ocean becoming a vast Muslim lake. From Somalia in the north to Mozambique in the south, dozens of coastal states flourished with between 30 and 40 medieval city-states, many on islands adjacent to the coast. Kilwa, on the coast of southern Tanzania, was the greatest medieval east African city, with caravans arriving there with ivory from around Lake Malawi and dhows coming up the coast from the south with gold, much of which came from Zimbabwe. From Kilwa great oceangoing ships took off for Arabia, India and China on the monsoon winds. (Ref. 17) Although the ruling dynasties of those eastern states were Muslim, the populations were mixed Arabs, Persians, and indigenous Bantu. This resulted, in time, in the distinctive east African Swahili Culture. The political control extended only a few miles inland and the interior peoples, themselves, brought the wealth of east and central Africa to the shores of the Indian Ocean. Slaves with tusks on their heads plodded for hundreds of miles to the coast and then were sold with the ivory. (Ref. 18)

Slightly inland and going from north to south, we should mention the rise of the Bantu kingdoms, especially Bunyoro, the largest at that time, in the area of present day Uganda. (Ref. 19) Farther south, in the Great Lakes area the cattle herding Cwezi kings held sway. (Please see also the summary after the section on AFRICA, in the 15th century chapter). Continuing south, the leading state of central Africa was governed by Mwana Mtapa and covered a 700 mile stretch of the Zambesi Valley.

Mtapa was also the heir to an even older Shona Dynasty which had built the fortress of Zimbabwe, the ruins of which still stand today. The Shonas formed loose federations to control gold mining regions and trade routes to the coast. There is some evidence, however, of a burning of the original Great Zimbabwe dwellings in this century. (Ref. 20, 21)

1 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [43] CUNLIFFE, BARRY, The Making of the English. (The Broadwater Press Ltd., Welwyn Garden City, Hertfordshire, England).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

5 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

6 [5] ATIL, ESIN, "As bodyguards or rulers, Mamluks made a golden age.", Smithsonian 12: No. 4, pp.108-1131, July, 1981.

7 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

8 [5] ATIL, ESIN, "As bodyguards or rulers, Mamluks made a golden age.", Smithsonian 12: No. 4, pp.108-1131, July, 1981.

9 [5] ATIL, ESIN, "As bodyguards or rulers, Mamluks made a golden age.", Smithsonian 12: No. 4, pp.108-1131, July, 1981.

10 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

11 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

12 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

13 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

14 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

15 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

16 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

17 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

18 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

19 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

20 [35] COBB, CHARLES E.,JR., "After Rhodesia, a Nation named Zimbabwe", National Geographic 160: 616-651, Nov. 1981).

21 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1.  "Bahri" means the "sea" and was the name given to the Mamluks who were stationed on the Island of Roda in the Nile by the last Kurd Sultan, Najm al-Din Ayyub. (Ref. 9)

Africa: A.D. 1301 to 1400

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

The Somali have been documented as being in the Horn of Africa in this 14th century but they may have actually arrived much earlier. Although commentary and archaeological material is meagre, it is probable that the homeland of these Somali, as well as the Galla, Danakil and Sidama lies in the Rift Valley of southern Ethiopia. They were all speakers of eastern Cushitic languages and for all life was hard, with frequent bloody feuds adding to their troubles. The Solomonids from Shoa continued their civilization in Ethiopia, with Emperor Amda Siyon (A.D. 1314-44) expanding toward the south and then defeating the Muslims of eastern Ethiopia in A.D. 1332. A reformed monastic movement evangelized frontier districts and churches were built on mountain tops. (Ref. 1, 2)

The real power in northeast Africa, of course, was Egypt, where the Mamluk Dynasty continued to reign with relative stability and with increased aggressiveness as they even conquered Armenia in 1375. Cairo was the greatest city and its minor art, enameled glass and pottery work was exceptionally fine. One of the greatest Bahri Mamluk patrons of the arts was Sultan Hasan (1347-51 and 1354-61), who is remembered for his school and mausoleum which was decorated with carved stone and stucco, marble revetments, inlaid metal doors and gilded glass lamps. His successor, Shaban II, commissioned fabulously illuminated Korans, some in blocks three feet high. Each Mamluk sultan was always surrounded by a group of Amirs, also former slave Mamluks, and these in turn, also always had a new group of slave Mamluk bodyguards. The latter could earn their freedom and when they did, they were sent as governors and commanders to various provinces and given land for themselves. (Ref. 3) Cannons were in use in Cairo and Alexandria in the latter half of the century. Ibn Batuta, travelling to Cairo, described 12,000 water carriers and thousands of camel drivers plying for hire1.

In this 14th century the majority of Egyptians, for the first time, were Arab-speaking Muslims and this must have resulted from many intermarriages with Bedouin Arabs. It is possible that the Black Death among the original native population may also have-been a factor in this ethnic shift, as about 1/3 of the inhabitants died in the first attack of that plague between 1347 and 1349. (Ref. 5)

In 1381 Malik al-Nasir Barquq, an amir of the Burji Mamluks, overthrew the east Bahri sultan and started a new dynasty, the Burji, dedicated to luxury and intrigue and violence, which soon led to social decay. This administration debased the coinage, taxed necessities and laid such heavy duty on India-European trade that Europe had to find a new route to India in the next century.

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

A creditable civilization remained in North Africa, although between the Marinids of Morocco and the Hafsids of Tunisia there was endless strife, particularly as to who should receive the homage of the intervening Ziyanids of Algeria. In 1360 the latter became independent and the Hafsid dominion divided into the Hafsid Emirate of Constantine and the plain Hafsid Caliphate, running to the east along the coast as far as Egypt. The Marinids of Morocco flourished as much from piracy as through commerce. (Ref. 6, 7)

At Timbuktu, far south across the great desert, there was a library of some 1,600 volumes, a famous university and beautiful mosques. The geographer Muhammad abu Abdullah ibn Batuta, after traveling about 75,000 miles, wrote a book about this area and Abd-er-Rahman of Tunis, perhaps the greatest historian of all time, wrote many treatises on the rise and fall of civilizations in general, anticipating and stimulating Arnold Toynbee in many respects. At the end of this 14th century repeated nomad conquerors from the fringes of the Sahara began raids into North Africa, starting a period of decadence.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

While Europe suffered the Black Death and the Hundred Years War, black kingdoms of the Sudan were flourishing with great wealth and brilliant artistic accomplishments. Competing with the one at Timbuktu, a university at Jenne attracted students from far and wide. (Ref. 8) The Muslims of Mali had "-a greater abhorrence of injustice than any other people", said Ibn Battuta2 The Mali emperor, Musa I, made a pilgrimage to Mecca, taking with him a great train of servants, courtiers, slaves and 3,800 kilograms of gold, sufficient to depress the price of that metal on the Cairo exchange. But about 1350, the expanding Empire of Songhai began to take over Mali territory, continuing to support their city of Timbuktu, but creating a new capital at nearby Gao. Between Songhai and Kanem-Bornu were the Hausa city-states. Of these, Kano and Katsina particularly were rich and industrious, with a specialty production of leather goods which was called "Moroccan" leather in England. If continued in the present region of Nigeria. On the Gulf of Guinea several kingdoms arose in the area now known as Ghana. The Yoruba people, who settled the tropical rain forest of the Niger Basin, built up powerful kingdoms of Benin and Oyo. (Ref. 9)

Many wealthy city-states appeared on the east coast of Africa in this and the next century. The city of Zimbabwe has been mentioned previously and this remained a very important religious, political and trading center of the Shona, a Bantu-speaking people among which building and pottery styles reached a peak in this and the 15th centuries. Stone walling was improved, the old burned out stone buildings were rebuilt and an attractive edifice 800 feet long and 32 feet high was constructed for some unknown purpose. (Ref. 10) The Shona are still today the majority people of that country.

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [5] ATIL, ESIN, "As bodyguards or rulers, Mamluks made a golden age.", Smithsonian 12: No. 4, pp.108-1131, July, 1981.

4 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

5 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

6 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

7 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

8 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

9 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

10 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

1.  As noted by Braudel (Ref. 4), page 481

2.  As quoted in Reference 154 by the National Geographic Society, Cartographic Division

Africa: A.D. 1401 to 1500

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

This part of the world experienced no great change from the previous century. The Solomonid Dynasty in Ethiopia was at the height of its power and Amhara colonists continued to invade southern Shoa, Gojam and the base of the Semien Mountains. The Moslems controlled all the Red Sea coast, however, and confined the Christians to the Ethiopian highlands. Even Nubia became Moslem. The Caucasoid Azanians in the northeastern interior felt the impact of migrating Bantu speakers and the arrival of Nilo Hamites with their Cushitic languages, such as Galla, influenced the region. These Nilo-Hamites appear to have been a mixture from three origins, - Nilotic Negroids of the upper Nile, Cushitic Sidama of Ethiopia and a third of origin unknown. (Ref. 1)

The Mamluk Dynasty continued in Egypt, but with declining power and influence.

It must be recalled that this ruling group were originally warriors from the Caucasus region and this communication with Black Sea ports allowed recurrent epidemic disasters in Egypt. Disease, helped probably by oppression and bad government, resulted in depopulation and impoverishment. The last great Mamluk sultan was Qaitbay (1468-96), an avid builder, who restored some of the greatness of the old Bahri period of the 13th century, but the decline of the empire was only temporarily halted. (Ref. 2, 3)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

The coast still had a high cultural level and now acted as a refuge for the Moors fleeing from the persecutions in Spain. With the decline of the Moroccan Marinids and after the Portuguese seized Ceuta, opposite from Gibralter in 1415, the Hafsids gained at least titular supremacy over all of western North Africa for while. By 1478 the Wattasid Sultanate developed in the far west and the Ziyanid Emir existed between the Wattasid and the slipping Hafsids. (Ref. 4, 5) By the end of the century, the Arabs had established sugar cane in the Moroccan Sousse and from there it soon spread on into the Atlantic to Madeira, the Canaries and the Azores.

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

Just southwest of the Sahara it was the heyday of the Songhai, who had great mosques at Timbuktu and Jenne and were famous for their piety and scholarship. Relationships of this particular empire with Morocco were not cordial because of competition for the trans-Saharan trade and the valuable salt mine of Taghaxa in the northern desert. This Songhai Empire came into its zenith about 1464, when a warrior king, the Sonni Ali, came to the throne of Gao in the middle Niger and by his death had extended his rule over the whole western Sudan. He had cavalry, levies of foot soldiers and flotillas of war canoes, which patrolled the 1,000 miles of the navigable Niger. It was he who ended the Mali Empire of Ghana. (Ref. 6)

In the forest area of west Africa were the Edo, who developed great bronze sculpture in the Kingdom of Benin, near the coast of Nigeria. Benin was a walled city, 25 miles around, with wide, straight streets and spacious houses of wood. In Ife, in southwest Nigeria, one of these bronze heads was definitely made by the lost wax technique. Seven Hausa city-states, including Kano, Zaria, Gobir and Katsina had become flourishing commercial centers in the Sudan. Agriculture was the basis of society, with trade routes through the Sahara. Guinea, existing out on the southwest corner of the bulge of west Africa, would, at first glance, appear to be a site early exploited by Europeans, but actually it remained isolated for a long time because European ships could not return from there directly up the west African coast. Because of the Atlantic currents and wind, they had to go straight out to the middle Atlantic before they could turn and go north again. The people of Guinea were modest farmers and fishermen, with some local trade involving salt and dried fish. Deeper inland, they had some contact with the Sudan. This small country has a rain forest, but it is not deep and is traversed by the magnificent waterway, the Niger. Near the end of the century the Portugese did arrive to establish a trading post. A little to the east, the foundations had been laid for the famous forest states of Oyo and Akan, as well as Benin, which we have described above. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10) The Sudan had gold mines, ruled by village chiefs and the workers approached the condition of slavery. (Ref. 11)

In central Africa gold was plentiful and the king of the Congo maintained such opulence in his capital that visiting Portuguese were amazed and made haste to make an alliance, not a conquest. About 1441 they brought Christianity to western, central Africa, going even 200 miles up the Congo to convert the Congo king. Incidentally, they brought back gold. (Ref. 12) Living in the great bend of the Congo, in the plateau north of Stanley Pool, were the Teke people in a number of chiefdoms collectively known as Mongo. (Ref. 13)

Farther east in the lake country between Tanzania and Zaire there appeared in this 15th century the Batutsi, a tall, warrior people, perhaps originally from Ethiopia. They invaded and subjugated the native Bahutu in Burundi. In Kenya, the nomadic Masai entered from the north, joining the Kikuyu already there and then some Luo entered from the west. The Kikuyu were Bantu-speakers and related groups established themselves in parts of the Transvaal and Natal as well as the lower Congo and Zambezi by about A.D. 1500. Kitari was an Hamitic kingdom north of Lake Victoria. (Ref. 14, 15)

In the meantime Muslim Swahili1 city-states had been established all down the eastern coast of Africa and there was special interest in the gold of the Zimbabwe (Rhodesia) region. The Bantu-speakers had migrated southward along the spine of east Africa with a new war-like ethos and a pastoral life, dominating other tribes and reaching the Zambesi River by the end of the century. Arab trade inland actually declined, because these Bantu were less amenable to exploitation than their predecessors, chiefly Bushmen. By 1440 King Mutota of the Rozur clan in the Katanga nation assembled an army which completely dominated the Rhodesian plateau within 10 years. This period has been described by Charles Colt, Jr. (Ref. 16) as a splitting of the Shona state into two rival kingdoms. At any rate, as ruler of an empire, Mutota than took the title of Mwene Mutapa2. The Portuguese wrote this as Monomotapa, which soon became the name of the empire, itself. The stone birds, which have been found in the ruins of old Zimbabwe, were probably important in the religious ritual of that theocratic empire. The realm was soon subject to revolution and succession wars and this resulted in many "ups and downs" in its history and in its buildings. From the beginning in 1440 on for 400 years, however, there was a progressive evolution of artistic and technical skills in that society. The Monomatapa ruler was considered divine and his subjects would hear him but not look at him and had to approach him on their stomachs. He lived amid great pomp, but when he became seriously ill or very old he was obliged to take poison. At the end of the 15th century the entire nation moved hundreds of miles north, apparently because the local salt supplies of Great Zimbabwe had been exhausted. Their extensive stone buildings, which still exist, were abandoned at that time. (Ref. 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22)

Explorer Diogo Cao claimed Angola for Portugal in 1483 and the slave trade was opened up in earnest. In the next four centuries, some 3,000,000 slaves were sent to Brazil by the Portuguese. At the very tip of South Africa the people seen when the Europeans first explored the area were the Bushmen, who were hunters and gatherers, and the Hottentots (Khoikhoi), who herded sheep and cattle along the coastal regions. As noted previously, these were not Bantu-speaking people. (Ref. 25)

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

3 [5] ATIL, ESIN, "As bodyguards or rulers, Mamluks made a golden age.", Smithsonian 12: No. 4, pp.108-1131, July, 1981.

4 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

6 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

7 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

8 [17] BREFFNY, BRIAN DE, (Editor), The Irish World, (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. N.Y., 1977).

9 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

12 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

13 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

14 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

15 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

16 [35] COBB, CHARLES E.,JR., "After Rhodesia, a Nation named Zimbabwe", National Geographic 160: 616-651, Nov. 1981).

17 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

18 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

19 [35] COBB, CHARLES E.,JR., "After Rhodesia, a Nation named Zimbabwe", National Geographic 160: 616-651, Nov. 1981).

20 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

21 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

22 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

23 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

24 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

25 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

1.  "Swahili" implies "Arab and Negro". (Ref. 23)

2.  In the Shona language, "Mwene Mutapa" means "Master Pillager". (Ref. 24)

Africa: A.D. 1501 to 1600

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

The horn of Africa now became the site of bitter conflict, originally a trading rivalry, but soon a long religious and political fight between Christians of Ethiopia and the Muslim coastal states. The sultan of Adal (now between Somalia and Ethiopia), Ahmad Gran, attacked into the heartland of Ethiopia in the 1520s with the help of Danakill and Somali nomads. The Christian Amhara nation dominated the Ethiopian plateau at that time and sustained a flourishing ecclesiastical art. (Ref. 1, 2) The pope sent Portuguese soldiers, led by Christopher da Gama (Vasco's son), to help against this Muslim conquest in a 20 year long war. As a result of that help by Portuguese, Ethiopia came under Catholic influence for the first time, as their own Coptic Church had been declared heretical some 1,100 years previously. The Jesuits with the Portuguese tried to convert the Ethiopians, apparently without too much success, as all Catholic missions were expelled by the next century. But the old Christian empire was so exhausted by the warfare that the pagan Galla, from the south and east then invaded and settled in the country, with general anarchy resulting. (Ref. 3, 4, 5)1

1 The southern farmlands of Ethiopia, in the region of Bale, was occupied by Oromos, most of whom were Moslems

In what is now the country of Sudan, the Funj people appeared early in this century, defeated the Arabs and established a powerful kingdom around the capital Sennar, on the Blue Nile. The people, known as the "Black Sultans" of eastern Sudan eventually adopted Islam. (Ref. 6)

In Egypt the last Mamluk sultan was Qansuh al-Ghuri, a scholarly man coming to the throne late in life. Decadence, rivalry and corruption continued in his regime. To add to the Mamluk troubles, their trading ports were now by-passed by the Portuguese trade- routes around the Cape of Good Hope and the Egyptian treasury was soon empty. The stage was set for the advance of the Ottoman Turk, Selim I, who defeated the Mamluk army in Syria and advanced to rule Egypt and Hejaz (Saudi Arabia). (Ref. 7)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Estimates of the population of North Africa in this century vary from 2,000,000 to 3,500,000. (Ref. 8) After da Gama's voyage around Africa at the end of the preceding century, the economic ascendancy of North Africa ended. Science and philosophy lost out to both Christianity and Islam and the area began to decline to the status we know today. In the early century, both Spain and Portugal gained control of some Moroccan ports, but in a great battle of Alcazarquivir in 1578, King Sebastian of Portugal was killed and the Moroccans preserved their independence for another half century, usually ruled by factions of the Sharifian Dynasty. (Ref. 9) That country, alone of the north African states, remained independent of the Ottomans. At the height of its power, in about 1590, Morocco invaded the Songhai Empire and set up a client state in the sudan, disrupting the economy of that entire region. (Ref. 10) Throughout the century local fairs were set up in connection with local saints and pilgrimages. One of the largest was among the Gouzzoula, south of the Anti-Atlas, looking out over the desert. It survived for hundreds of years. (Ref. 11)

East of Morocco in the Oran-Algiers-Tripoli area a band of pirates roved until captured by Spanish forces using artillery in 1509 and 1510. Then in 1,516 a colorful buccaneer entered the picture - one Khair ed-Kin Khizr, called "Barbarossa" because of his red hair. Actually he was a Greek, who had joined the pirates, conquering Tripoli, Tunisia and Algeria and he then offered the Ottoman, Selim I, sovereignty over the area in return for the use of a Turkish army. With the latter he became the hero of western Islam, by ferrying 70,000 Moors from Spain to Africa, raiding Sicily and Italy, landing at Naples and then, with the French fleet, taking Nice and Villefranche from the Holy Roman Emperor. After all this, he died in bed at age 80 years. The Algiers and Oran area continued to be the haunt of the Barbary pirates until the end of the 18th century. (Ref. 12, 13)

In the meantime, however, Charles I of Spain (later Emperor Charles V) had re-captured Tunis as part of his war with Turkey, and had installed a puppet ruler. But the Ottomans, with Barbarossa's help, continued to creep across north Africa and gradually once again took over the entire area, with the exception of a few Spanish ports and the Sultanates of Fez and Morocco. In 1,571 the Turkish sea power was broken in a great sea battle off Lepanto, by a combined Spanish-Venetian navy. (Ref. 14)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

Horses have never been used much in Africa. For one thing the animals do not thrive in the tropics and secondly, they remained exceptionally expensive. In this 16th century horses cost three times as much as slaves in central Africa, although in the sudan the great Moroccan horses were sometimes worth 12 slaves each. (Ref. 15) The huge Songhai Empire, which had been built up by Sunni Ali in the last century, was led early in this century by an even greater man, Askia Muhammad, the Great (1493-1528). There were a number of large commercial cities, such as the old Mali capital of Timbuktu, a town of 6,000 houses with a splendid royal court. The city was multi-racial, with Songhai, Taureg, Moor, Malenki and Fulani, a fact which led to hostility and succession problems in the empire. The predominantly Negro inhabitants were described as superior in wit, civility and industry. Other cities were Jenne and Gao, the latter full of rich merchants. But each century the Sahara was becoming more and more desiccated and life a little harder. To further complicate matters, in 1590 the Sultan of Morocco sent an army of 3,000 men, including Spanish and Portuguese renegades straight south across the desert to wipe out Songhai. Their cannons and muskets won the towns quickly, but in the south where the terrain did not favor open warfare, they could not win, although the war went on for a decade, devastating the country-side and bringing down the empire. Learning, culture and prosperity all disappeared from the region. (Ref. 16, 17, 18, 19) Apparently isolated from the rest of Mali, a people called "Dogon” arrived in the Bondagara cliff region to gradually replace the Tellem, who had lived in the area since the 11th century. The latter had been decreasing in nu mber since the 13th century, however, perhaps because of pressure from the Mali and later the Songhai empires. The Dogon lived in this isolated region, more or less unknown to the western world until about 1907. (Ref. 20)

Farther south in Nigeria, the Bini tribe of Benin made magnificent bronzes, using the "lost wax" method and did beautiful ivory carvings for the royal palaces. Ife remained, related to Benin. About Lake Chad it was the apogee of the Empire of Kanem, or Bornu, under Idres III. In the Great Lakes region, Lwo invaders from the north overthrew the Cwezi kings and established the states of Bunyoro and Buganda.. In Uganda the Kingdom of Buchwezi continued. The Watutsi, probably originating in Ethiopia, migrated in the late 16th century to the Lake Kiva region, establishing the Rwanda and Burundi kingdoms. The Kikuya reached Kenya from the south, cut down the forest and started to cultivate the land. (Ref. 21) Farther south, in what later was to become Rhodesia and is now again Zimbabwe, the king of Monomatapa left the original Zimbabwe region to establish a new capital on the northern edge of the Rhodesian plateau. A new dynasty, the Rosvis, soon revived the original area and some of the largest Zimbabwe buildings were then constructed. (Ref. 22, 23, 24) As the Bantu speakers pushed southward, four main linguistic groups developed. The Nguni group took on many "clicks" of the Khoisan tongue of the Bushmen, as the latter were pushed westward and toward the cape. (Ref. 25)

The Portuguese were the first European power to make some inroad into Subsaharan Africa. After having taken Sofala and Kil-wa and founding Mozambique between 1505 and 1507 they ascended the Zambesi River in 1513. And they were not hesitant about taking slaves from the Atlantic side of the continent. In the Congo in about 1526 the Christian King Affonso deplored the depopulation of his country by slavers who were chiefly Portuguese. Inadvertently, these Europeans did Africa another great disfavor by bringing maize from America. That maize grew so rapidly that it led to a great population increase in some areas, so that slave ships never sailed empty. A terrible side effect, however, was the appearance of the nutritional disease, pellagra, which resulted from the exclusive diet of maize, when not supplemented with other foods or prepared with lime water. In the Central and South American homelands of that vegetable, people not only converted the corn to hominy with lime water, but ate tomatoes, capsicum, peppers and fish, which supplied the vitamins necessary to prevent pellagra. (Ref. 26, 27)

Sir John Hawkins initiated the British slave trade and the Dutch established their first colony on the Guinea coast in 1595. To evaluate the early effect of the slave trade one must realize that in the early years African monarchs profited from the trade, obtaining weapons, cloth, metal and spirits, which increased their wealth. The loss of population of about 40,000 a year was generally economically acceptable and in this respect only, the less populous Angola and East Africa suffered. The larger kingdoms of Ashanti and Dahomey might owe their rise to power to the fire-arms acquired in the slave trade. (Ref. 28)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

3 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

6 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

7 [5] ATIL, ESIN, "As bodyguards or rulers, Mamluks made a golden age.", Smithsonian 12: No. 4, pp.108-1131, July, 1981.

8 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

9 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

12 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

13 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

14 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

15 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

16 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

17 [154] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

18 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

19 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

20 [251] BEDAUX, ROGIER M.A., "Rediscoverring the Tellem of Mali", Archeology 35: No. 3, pp. 28-34, May/June 1982.

21 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

22 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

23 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

24 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

25 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

26 [154] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

27 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

28 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

Africa: A.D. 1601 to 1700

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

In the early century, Ethiopian emperors began to reconsolidate their power among the plains and lush hillsides of Begemder and developed a permanent royal residence at Gondar, after 1636. Emperor Fasilida expelled all Jesuits by 1633, put down the Moslems of Adal, and closed the country to foreigners. Later local wars against both the neighboring Muslims and the Galla, farming people of central and south Ethiopia, resumed and was to last almost two centuries. Galla groups continued to move in Somali, some intermarrying with Arabs and developing a passionate devotion to Islam. Cubes of salt served as both money and food for these people. In Egypt, Turkish control continued. (Ref. 1, 2)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

This area continued to decline economically and intellectually, Ali Bey made himself hereditary Bey of Tunis, while Algiers and Tripoli became virtually independent states. Politics was violent, with riots, plots, counter-plots, and massacres. 30,000 of Algiers’ 130,000 people were Christian slaves of the dominant Moslems. The Barbary pirates continued to work the Algiers and Oran areas throughout this century, using renegade Europeans from Calabria or Sicily, as captains. (Ref. 3)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

In the western bulge of Africa the state of Ashanti was formed and rapidly expanded to absorb some 30 independent neighboring kingdoms in the area that is now part of western Ghana. It was the Ashanti who teamed up with the European slavers for the greatest exports of men. Between the Ashanti and the Niger delta the states of Dahomey and Oyo were also established in this century and the entire region was sometimes called “the slave coast”. Later some of it was called “the gold coast”. The Portuguese had refused to sell firearms to any of these people, but in the middle of the century the Dutch did. On the upper Niger, the black Bambara Kingdom defeated and replaced the old Manding empire about 1670. Brought from America, maize gradually came to be the primary food plant north of the Congo in Benin and among the Yoruba. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

Bornu continued as the most powerful state of the central Sudan, but interstate wars continued in this and the next century. Kuba was a group of chiefdoms at the south edge of the rain forest which developed a relatively high standard of living and rapid population increase as they received new American crops and techniques, both brought by the Portuguese. The Buchwezi Kingdom in Uganda was succeeded by the Buganda and this had become the most powerful of the Bantu-speaking kingdoms by 1700. Those people carved wooden sculptures and had very artistic palaces, shrines, and houses. Large drums, some 12 feet across, were used as ritual objects, supposedly to communicate with ancestors. (Ref. 7)

Portuguese domination of Swahili cities of the east coast was eliminated by the Arabs of Oman, who had considerable maritime power at that time. A 1690 revolt in Mozambique, led by Changamire, to protest against harsh Portuguese treatment, resulted in the elimination of Europeans there, but they still bought slaves through other ports. (Ref. 8)

In parts of southern Africa, Bushmen still made rock-paintings and engravings of polychrome animals which could compare favorably with any stone-age art of the Sahara or even of western Europe. The best paintings of this and the next two centuries are in the Drakenburg Mountains. (Ref. 9) In 1652 the Dutch East India Company established a rest station near the cape at the tip of Africa, en route to the Spice Islands (Indonesia). Soon slaves were imported for local labor and the local Hottentots supplied beef. Several hundred French Huguenots arrived as settlers also by 1700 so that by the time there was a mixture of about 1000 Dutchmen with some French and the native Hottentots and Bushmen. Neither of the latter are correctly considered to be truly of the Negro race and the Bantu-speaking, true Negroes were still in the process of migrating slowly down the eastern coast of the continent, although the Nguni were beginning to settle over most of Natal. (Ref. 10)

Although the Europeans were establishing trading posts along the coast of Africa, the mainland of the continent remained self-contained and there were no true European colonies until the end of the next century. Probably the chief reason for the slow penetration up the rivers by Caucasians is that most of tropical Africa’s rivers are blocked by huge waterfalls only a short distance from the rivers’ mouths. There was some traveling up the Senegal and the Gambiae. As the sugar, cotton, and tobacco plantations developed in the New World, the slave trade from Africa reached substantial proportions. Initially handled by the Portuguese, the trade was progressively taken over by British, Dutch, and French. In 4 ½ centuries some 10 million slaves were brought to the Americas and this slave trade inhibited political, economic, and social development and culled out the sound and healthy population already debilitated by endemic disease. (ref. 11) Early on the Portuguese had a trading station in Angola, but for a while the Dutch took this away, depriving the Portuguese for slaves for the Brazilian plantations. By 1640, then independent of Spain, Portugal recovered Angola and some 14 years later even drove the Dutch out of Brazil as well. The French started some settlements on Madagascar in 1626 and intermarried with various primitive tribes and the Hovas, who had arrived from across the Indian Ocean about 1000 A.D. They were the most advanced of several peoples of Malay and Melanesian stocks, all speaking one language, but with many dialects.

1 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

2 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

3 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

4 [58] EDWARDS, MIKE, "Tunisia: Sea, Sand, Success", National Geographic 157: 184, Feb. 1980.

5 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

6 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

7 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

8 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

9 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

10 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

11 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

Africa: A.D. 1701 to 1800

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Local war continued in Ethiopia. James Bruce, exploring that country as he traveled from Massawa to Gondar and thence to the Blue Nile, reported that the Ethiopian Empire was in decline, restricted to the area north of the Blue Nile and was wracked by rebellion. Galla tribesmen had penetrated the countryside and looted at will. (Ref. 1) Egypt was simply a part of the Ottoman Empire until the very end of the century, when Napoleon penetrated it as a gateway to the east (1798). The population had shrunk from about 8,000,000 in the 1st century C.E. to 2,000,000 at this time. (Ref. 2)1

1 The Oromos in the south, which were the largest group in the country, were subjugated in late century by Menelik II and the land was divided up among the royal family, the church, soldiers of the conquering army and other friends of the crown. The farmers became mere landless tenants

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

Hussein ibn Ali founded the Husseinite Dynasty in Tunis and threw off Turkish authority in 1705 and shortly thereafter Ahmed Bey made himself ruler of Tripoli, founding the Karamanil Dynasty, which was to last more than a century. The Spaniards were expelled from Oran for awhile, but they resumed control in 1732. From 1757 to 1789 Morocco was ruled by Sidi Mohammed, who established a regime of law and order and abolished Christian slavery. By 1800 those north African areas still subject to Ottoman Sultans were the most powerful communities controlled by outsiders on the continent. (Ref. 3, 4)

Copper bracelets, gold dust and horses were all used as currency in that part of Africa. Magnificient horses of the Moors were sold for 15 slaves each. In more southern areas a sheet of paper would obtain a fat, tender chicken. (Ref. 5)

SUBSAHARAN AFRICA

In western Africa, local wars in Ghana finally allowed that state to be taken over by Ashanti warriors, whose king and major chief s wore regalia made of local gold and imported silver. This forest Akan Empire became supreme in the interior of that part of Africa, trading gold for European fire-arms. They used minature brass sculptures to measure their gold dust. (Ref. 6, 7) The west coast of Africa was also the source of slaves for the British slave trade to the Spanish colonies in America. Britain had obtained this right as part of the treaty ending the Spanish War of Succession. The Ibo, in Guinea, supplied a greater number of slaves than any other e-thnic group, but their internal state was very little disturbed. Late in the century (1787) Sierra Leone, on the west coast, was acquired by the British for the settlement of freed slaves and it was made a separate colony in 1799, the same year as the founding of the British Church Missionary Society. Also late in this period, at about 1776, there was a rise of the Tukulor power in west Africa on the upper Niger, pushing the French out of their Senegal possessions on the river of the same name. The French recovered these in 1778.

Farther east the Hausa continued as a power about Lake Chad. Oyo, south of the Hausa states, got horses from the latter and built up a large cavalry. They may have had as many as 6,000 towns and villages, with almost all of the population speaking the Yoruba tongue. Still farther east, about the Great Lakes, the lake kingdoms of Uganda and Buganda made contact with the outside world, particularly through the Arab and Swahili merchants on the east coast. The Arabs had settled the coastal area of Kenya and came under control of the Sultan of Zanzibar from 1740 on. (Ref. 8, 9)

In the equatorial area, 600 miles northeast of the Kuba Kingdom, were several states of warrior Zande stock and east of them were the Mangbetu who, although cannibals, had advanced metal work displayed in lavish treasure chambers. The origin of these people is unknown. On the southern savannahs the Bakuba of Zaire commemorated their king with many fine portrait statues and in the more isolated regions, the Bushmen continued rock paintings. In the Cape Colony, the Dutch gradually pushed inland as cattle raiders and farmers, reaching the Orange River in 1760 and the Great Fish River in 1776. In 1795 the British fleet, acting under mandate from the exiled Prince of Orange, captured the Dutch garrison, primarily to prevent the Cape Colony from falling into the hands of the French. We should note, in passing, that the end of the century marked the birth of Shaka, a great Bantu-speaking king who would eventually fuse the Zulu nations into a great war machine. The Bushmen of the Cape were essentially destroyed by the European impact. (Ref. 10, 11, 12)

1 [270] BUTZER, KARL W., "Empires, Capitals and Landscapes of Ancient Ethiopia", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 30-37, Sept./Oct. 1982.

2 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

3 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

4 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

5 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

6 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

7 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

8 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

9 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

10 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

11 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

12 [154] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

Africa: A.D. 1801 to 1900

AFRICA

NORTHEAST AFRICA

Ethiopia, a land of priests and monasteries, was the only Christian state in this area. It had an emperor without power as the country was - rent by rivalries among the provincial warlords and was subjected to repeated attacks by Galla nomads from the south. Actually, the latter, along with Amhara warlords, wielded the real power. In 1855 an ex-bandit, Ras Kassa, seized power making himself Emperor Theodorus and soon became a tyrant. In 1864 he imprisoned three members of a British mission and they were rescued only three years later by a British military expedition coming in from the Red Sea. Theodorus killed himself and civil war followed. A powerful, local leader, Menelik, supported by Italy finally won out, becoming Menelik II. He soon broke with Italy, however, and captured some 3,000 Italians in a battle at Aduwa in 1896. He did build railways and schools and a new capital at Addis Ababa. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

The horn of Africa came under the control of the Sultan of Oman and Zanzibar in the 1820s. Throughout most of the century the Sudan was controlled by British-Egyptian administrations, but there were many changes from decade to decade. Some of these are discussed in the paragraphs about Egypt, to follow. In 1885 Major General Charles George "Chinese" Gordon was killed in Khartoum by Mahdi followers, ending Egyptian suzerainty. The religious leader Mahdi then established the f irst Sudanese government in Omdurman. Some 13 years later, however, Lord Kitchener defeated the Sudanese forces (1898) and started the era of the Anglo-Egyptian Condominium, which ruled Sudan for over 50 years. Just at the end of the century a highly developed Zandes military empire of the Congo basin swept up into the Sudan, under King Gbudwe, but were repulsed. (Ref. 4)

Napoleon Bonaparte had penetrated Egypt in 1798, but the British navy helped the Turks to drive the French out in 1801, allowing Muhammad (also Mehemet) Ali, an Albanian Turk with Albanian soldiers, to invade. In 1803 the Ottoman Sultan appointed him Pasha (viceroy) of Egypt. There was still a Mamluk garrison present, but in 1811 Muhammad massacred every man in it and emerged as absolute ruler of the country. He then Europeanized the army, reformed the administration and built up the commercial economy, employing many Europeans, especially Frenchmen. The cultivation of cotton helped to awaken the somewhat somnolent Islam and Ali was able to extend his control to Sennar, Arabia, Sudan, Crete and Greece (1825-28) Europeans were considerably upset about all this and a combined British, French and Russian naval force took Greece away from Ali, ensuring the success of a Greek revolution, which had been in progress. Later the Europeans made Ali relinquish a portion of Syria that he had annexed and forced him to settle for hereditary rule over Egypt and the Sudan, only. As a side light of this Near Eastern crisis of 1839-41, a British squadron compelled the French Navy to withdraw support from Ali and this stimulated the French admiralty to find new technological means to challenge the British at sea. In turn, this resulted in the development of steam-powered ships of war. (Ref. 5)

Egypt was independent in all but name. Some gold was found in the southern part and the ivory trade enjoyed a boom. Some 20,000 slaves were imported each year. When Mohammed Ali died in 1849 he left his successors the strongest government, most efficient army and most prosperous economy in Africa. At that time no part of northeast Africa was under any European sovereignty. (Ref. 6) Muhammad Ali's grandson, Ismail, educated in France, ascended to power with the title of king, while still paying tribute to Constantinople. 30,000 Egyptian soldiers kept northern Sudan under Turco-Egyptian rule, although there were still tribal chiefs. In south Sudan there was a Shilluk Kingdom of Nilotic people, although under Turkish suzerainty and a large independent tribal group called "Nuers". (Ref. 7)

A cholera epidemic of 1831 caused the death of 13% of the population of Cairo.

The first Egyptian railway was constructed in 1854 and others in the Near East followed soon after. By 1875 Egypt was the only African country with more than 1,000 miles of railroad track, but wheeled vehicles were otherwise nowhere of use. Long staple cotton had been discovered and put into production in the 1820s and 30s, with new land under cultivation. Cash crops for export from Egypt included that cotton and tobacco and it should be noted that during the American Civil War the demand for Egyptian cotton in- creased greatly so that it became worth ten times as much money as previously. Its worth almost trebled again in the next 45 years. (Ref. 8, 9)

French interests constructed the Suez Canal in 1869, but the English gained a share of it by purchase from Egypt in 1875 because the canal saved 41% of the mileage from London to Bombay and 29% of that to Singapore. After the French and English had established a joint control over Egypt in 1880, a native revolt against the British was led by Arabi Pasha in 1881-82, but the British countered with a military expedition two years later which resulted in actual British control of the country, although theoretically it was still under Turkish jurisdiction. The French had withdrawn. In the south the British were repeatedly under attack in the 1880s and 1890s by Muslims led by the Mahdi and his successor, the Khalifa. (Ref. 10, 11, 12, 13)

At the end of the century the British and French again came to blows over the eastern Sudan. The French backed down and, as mentioned earlier, the Sudan became an Anglo- Egyptian condominium in 1898. Indian immigrants to British East Africa eventually surpassed whites in number, however, and currently the migration of a great many of these dark, British citizens to England is giving the administration much trouble. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

NORTH CENTRAL AND NORTHWEST AFRICA

This was a period when the North African coast was divided among the imperialistic European powers, chiefly France and England. As the latter took over Egypt, France became interested in the more western areas, in spite of some Spanish footholds. Starting about 1830 hundreds of thousands of southern Europeans settled in North Africa, controlling practically all trade, industry and finance, but they did not fuse with the natives racially and they remained a distant and distinct group, arousing increasing local animosity. In the mountains the Berber Montagnards governed themselves in cantons or village republics and often some of these grouped loosely together for mutual protection. In the vast area of the central Sahara the Tauregs, of Berber stock, were arranged in 5 groups or confederations of tribes, named from the massifs that made up the core of their respective territories. Raiding was the profession of the nobles and most had large numbers of Negro slaves. (Ref. 17)

The bay of Algeria was constantly bickering with the French government over coral fishing concessions and finally in 1830 the French intervened with 37,000 soldiers in 103 ships and launched the largest and most destructive military campaign in the story of European imperialism in Africa. They had pushed the Ottoman Turks out completely by 1841, but they made the mistake of using Jews, who were despised by the Muslims, for support.

Abd al-Kadir, at the head of a religious group in western Algeria, set up a Muslim theocratic state, which was only subdued in 1847 by 108,000 French troops. (Ref. 18) By that time there were 100,000 European settlers in Algeria, with the French in control. Further insult to that country occurred in 1867-68 with the worst drought of its history, along with locusts and cholera. Some 300,000 people died out of a population of 2 1/2 million. The French also occupied Tunis in 1881, provoking a large scale Islamic uprising, followed by sporadic warfare in the south, in the next century. Phosphates from Tunis were used as fertilizer in France. (Ref. 19, 20, 21) Morocco kept foreigners pretty much at bay until 1850, when the French waged a victorious war to become, in essence, the owner of that country. (Ref. 22)

In the meantime, the Ottoman Turks had obtained a firm hold on Tripoli, the Fezzan and Cyrenica by 1835. In the oasis of Jaghbut in the latter country, the Muslim teacher, Sayyid Muhammad al-Sanusi (Grad Sanusi) established a religious center, which was continued after his death in 1859 by his son, Muhammed al-Mahdi. Missionaries were sent from the center out along the caravan routes. (Ref. 23)

We must not leave this section on North Africa without mentioning its troubles with the new United States of America at the beginning of this century. Throughout the Napoleonic Wars the United States had attempted to remain neutral in foreign struggles and had paid almost $2,000,000 or 1/5 of its national income to the Moslem states of Morocco, Algiers, Tunis and Tripoli for ransom or tolls. When President Jefferson cut out some of the tolls in 1801 the bashaw of Tripoli declared war on the new nation. In 1804 Commodore Preble attacked Tripoli with the U.S.S. Constitution and the f rigate Philadelphia, was taken prisoner, but then rescued by the night-time heroics of Lt. Stephen Decature, in the captured schooner Intrepid. This, coupled with a heroic desert march by William Eaton across Libya, resulted in a final favorable treaty with Tripoli, which was later repudiated.

SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA

At the beginning of the century the interior of Af rica was almost wholly isolated from the rest of the world. The only resident Europeans lived precariously along the coasts where the slave forts and trading posts existed. Most of Africa lagged 100 years behind in economic development, a feature which led to many of the African problems of the 20th century. It will be convenient to discuss the history of Sub-Saharan Africa in the first half of the century separately from that of the second half, and in each instance five main areas will be listed. For the first half of the 19th century, then:

SUDANIC STATES (Immediately sub-saharan and western forest belt)

In the west there were the theocracies of Futa Toro and Futa Jellon, formed after fierce holy wars conducted by Al-hajj Umar. At the southwest corner of the great western bulge of Africa some 2,500 former United States slaves formed the country of Liberia in 1820, introducing American democratic institutions. (Ref. 24) In the Niger River bend the great empires of medieval times had given way to numerous states, chief of which were Segu, Ka'arta and Masina. Farther east the whole of Hausaland, including the Kingdom of Bornu about Lake Chad, was overrun and destroyed by the Fulani, under a Tukulor chief, Usman (or Uthman) dan Fodio, in a " jihad" or holy war. The Fulani, of mixed Negro and Berber origin, had a formidable army of horsemen and from Hausaland they struck east and southwest, forming a Muslim Empire of Sokoto under the Kanemi Dynasty. By 1850 this was the most extensive political structure in Africa, comprising 20 provinces in an area of 150,000 square miles between the Sahara and the forest belt. It was through this empire that Islam penetrated into the southern forest states. Between Lake Chad and the Nile were the sultanates of Wadai and Darf ut and on the Nile was the Funj Sultan ate of Sennar. All of these communities had extensive trade across the Sahara, bartering slaves, leather, kola nuts, etc., in exchange for weapons, horses and holy books. All of the Sudanic states except Segu and Ka'arta had Muslim rulers. (Ref. 25, 26, 27, 28)

Ashanti (modern Ghana), Dahomey, Oyo and Benin (modern Nigeria) all had active, relatively progressive kingdoms, as in the last century. Italian made coins in the form of milled, coral cylinders, perforated in the center and called "olivette" remained in common usage throughout the 19th century and even to the present day in Nigeria, Sierra Leone and Liberia. The Africans carry them on a string on their belts. (Ref. 29)

(Continue on page 1055) Continue to Sudanic States

EQUATORIAL AFRICA

This portion of Africa was still an unexplored area and the course of the Congo was unknown to Europeans. Slave trade to Cuba and Brazil flourished up until 1840, when it was officially banned. The people of the interior Congo basin were now chiefly of Negroid stock, speaking Bantu languages, having replaced most of the original pygmoid1 and bushmanoid hunters. (Ref. 30) (Continue on page 1056)

EAST AFRICA AND THE GREAT LAKES AREA

In this part of Africa there were a cluster of strong kingdoms - Bunyoroo, Buganda, Ankole, Karagwe, Rwanda and Burundi. To the east the hostile Masai terrorized central Kenya and Tanzania as they repeatedly raided for cattle. Arabs on the east coast grew rich from the sale of ivory from elephant tusks and in the slave trade, which they continued well past the half century mark. The eastern Bantu-speaking Negroes have lighter skin than others, perhaps from considerable intermarriage with people of Caucasoid stock. (Ref. 32) (Continue on page 1056)

SAVANNAH SOUTH OF THE CONGO BASIN

Luba-Lunda was ruled by Mwata Yamvo and Mwata Kazemk. The ancient kingdom of Mwene Mtapa in the region of modern Zimbabwe was rivalled by the Rozwi state of the Changamires. The last people to inhabit the city of Zimbabwe, which was already somewhat decadent, were apparently driven out about 1830 during the Zulu wars, which will be discussed in the next paragraph. Into the vacuum so created, the Ndebeles tribe swept in from the original Zulu area in the south. On the west side of the continent the Portuguese had coastal settlements in what is now Angola, but after the abolition of the slave trade in 1840, the colonies collapsed and the number of white men there dropped from 3,000 to less than 1000 by A.D. 1850. (Ref. 33, 34, 35, 36, 37) (Continue on page 1057)

THE CAPE AREA

An expedition along the Orange River in 1801 revealed a city of 10,000 people in the territory now called Botswana, which is surrounded by desert. Although millet and some legumes were used, the people relied chiefly on cattle, using the milk in a curdled state.

Both Dutch and British had started settlements near the Cape at the end of the 18th century and in the early years of the 19th they came in contact with a great southward migration of the Bantu-speaking blacks from central Africa. These included multiple tribes such as Swazi, Zulu, Pondo, Tembu, Xhosa, Sotho and Tswana. There was cattle raiding along the line of the Fish River and fighting between the Dutch and the natives had broken out in 1779 to last over a hundred years. After the British officially came into power at Cape Colony by treaty with the Batavian Republic in 1814, they decided to secure the line of the Fish River by colonization. Between 1820 and 1821 some 5,000 people were brought there from Great Britain. English began to replace Dutch as the official language, the judicial system was remodel ed on the English pattern and Dutch currency was replaced by English. But Anglicisation was not completely successful as the Dutch clung tenaciously to their own culture and institutions so that the only result of the new policy was to harden those differences of opinion, especially on the native question.

When the English missionaries got slavery abolished in 1833, the settlers were indignant.

The first crisis came in 1834 when hordes of blacks swept over the Fish River frontier, laying waste the country and destroying the farms. The governor, Sir Benjamin D'Urban, drove them back and annexed the territory to try to prevent future trouble, but the missionaries forced abandonment of that plan and prevented any compensation for the damaged farms. Thus was provoked the Great Trek, in which about 5,000 Boers (Dutch), with women, children and cattle, set out into the unknown, some going as far as 1,000 miles inland, to get away from the British. Many were attacked by Matabele and the Zulus and all endured thirst and famine.

At about that same time, the empire of the Zulus, under Chaka and his successor Dingaan, began a war of blacks against blacks, crushing all other tribes in the area and leaving a trail of devastation, rotting corpses and burned villages. Most of modern Transvaal, Orange Free State and Natal were denuded of population. The massacres of thousands of natives thus gave the Boers room to move, although in great peril. They, themselves, finally crushed the Zulus in a great battle at Blood River in 1838 and then established the Republic of Natal in the region east of the Drakenburg range, with Andries Pretorius as its first president

They then discovered that there was already a garrison of British troops at Port Natal (later Deurbar) and by 1843 the area was made into a British colony. Most of the Dutch then went back over the range to the region of the Orange and Vaal rivers to establish the independent Boer state of the South African Republic (Transvaal) and two years later the Orange Free State. (Ref. 38, 39, 40) (Continue on page 1057)

The last half of the 19th century showed some great changes in those portions of Africa under European control, but even as late as 1875 those areas were primarily Algeria, Senegal and South Africa, although the pressure was gradually increasing overall. Although the European slave trade was supposedly banned early in the century, by 1850 some 25,000,000 blacks, supplied by local Africans, had been sent away from the continent by European, American, and Arab slavers. But Christian missionary activity increased and the hinterlands began to be explored with gun-boats behind them. As the Europeans gradually increased their coastal influence, the Age of Imperialism in Africa was initiated. This was about 1860 and we shall now re-examine the five sections of sub-saharan Africa as they received the impact of the 2nd half of the 19th century:

SUDANIC STATES

The Ashanti Kingdom comprised most of what is modern Ghana and in 1850 had 3,000,000 to 5,000,000 people in its 125,000 square miles. There was great opulence in the royal court at the capital, Kumasi. In an unusual arrangement, a new ruler was chosen by the Queen Mother, assisted by senior chiefs. Trade was active in gold, slaves, livestock and food-stuffs. In neighboring Dahomey there was a royal core of women warriors consisting of some 5,000 women backed up by 7,000 men. It was their custom to have an annual killing of several score criminals and war captives.

The French began to penetrate along the Senegal River to obtain a profitable gum trade and the British began to occupy Sierra Leone and to take over the Niger basin.

A crown colony was established at Lago in Nigeria in 1861 and by the 1870s there were 14 British steamers on the Niger River. On the upper Niger, however, the Tukolors, under their leader al-Haji Umar, were active and expanded to come up against the French on the Senegal.

EQUATORIAL AFRICA

White explorers penetrated central Africa in this time period, going chiefly from east to west. Prominent among those was Sir Henry Morton Stanley2 who explored the Congo for King Leopold of Belgium and then sold the southern bank area to Belgium. France signed treaties with the Bateke Kingdom for the north bank of the Congo, through the explorer Savorgnan de Brazza. All of this European penetration would have been impossible without quinine for control of the endemic malaria. The Dutch had originally obtained that drug from Java.

The scramble for land in Africa by European powers became so intense that in November, 1884 Otto von Bismarck and the French premier called a Berlin Conference in which 14 nations took part. In addition to agreeing to work for the further suppression of slavery, the nations agreed to complete liberty of commerce in the Congo basin and adjacent coasts and the Congo and Niger rivers were to have free navigation.

Deep in the rain forest, however, pygmies and negroids still ruled unmolested by whites. In Katanga, Msiri, with Yeke followers, established himself as chief and initiated a reign of terror. Fortress grounds were littered with skulls of people he had tortured and murdered. That empire disappeared by the 1880s. (Ref. 42, 43, 44)

EAST AFRICA AND GREAT LAKE AREA

In 1850, through the genius of Sultan Sayyid Said of Oman, Zanzibar was made into an influential center, with a small army and navy. By 1860, however, it was under some British influence and by 1873 the British navy had stopped the sultan from trading in slaves. (Ref. 45) Buganda, now a province of modern Uganda, launched great raids under Mutesa I between 1854 and 1883 to obtain slaves, cattle and ivory. For this purpose Mutesa had a large army and a navy of canoes for use on Lake Victoria. That country also fell under British protection in the 1890s.

In Kenya the basic Kikuyu people had no chiefs and were ruled by a senior elders' council. They were repeatedly terrorized by- the Masai, who dominated an area of 80,000 square miles and who had two passions in life - war and cattle. Because of these warriors, when white explorers such as Burton, Speke, Grant, and Stanley went in to central Africa they went from the south over dry bush country infested with many tropical diseases.

Even the Masai, themselves, were decimated in the 1880s, but that was from small-pox. The great days of the Masai ended in the 1890s as the British occupied the Kenya highlands. Many of the large game animals were already becoming limited and a few, such as the quagga3, were already extinct.

SAVANNAH SOUTH OF THE CONGO BASIN

It has been noted previously that Portugal had an early lead in Angola and then she took Mozambique. Actually there were very few whites in those two areas, including only about a dozen priests. The white men did intermarry with the natives and kept some measure of control in that way. Germany, not to be outdone, wedged into areas on the Indian Ocean coast north of Mozambique and Cameroun and in Togo (German Southwest Africa) in the west. In the second phase of European partition of Africa, after 1895, there was increasing bitter, local African resistance. The colonial governments had turned to raising money by direct local taxation and corvee, or forced labor systems, had become widespread. This, along with the expropriation of land, led to more destructive, bitter and longer wars, with the superior weaponry of the invading Europeans winning in all areas4. (Ref. 46, 47)

THE CAPE AREA

One region where war occurred with white against white, rather than against black, was in South Africa. By 1856 the Cape population was roughly 267,000, including 119,000 Europeans with a Dutch majority. Natal had about 6,500 people, chiefly English; the Orange Free State had 12,000 Europeans and the Transvaal some 18,000. Both of those were soon free of English control. By 1857 there were 8 separate governments in South Africa - 5 Boer republics and 3 British colonies. Intermittent fighting continued and when the Boers of Transvaal attacked blacks led by Khama the Great, in Boswana, the British protected the latter.

Map taken from Reference 97

Two great mineral discoveries began to effect tremendous changes in the area. First, diamonds were discovered in an old volcano chimney along the Vaal River and at the site of present day Kimberly, bordering English and Boer states. Within 10 years $100,000,000 worth of diamonds had been mined. The British, who negotiated themselves into annexing this Kimberly region into the Cape Colony about 1870 and two Englishmen, Cecil John Rhodes and Barney Barnato, gained most from the diamonds. Secondly, gold was discovered on the Witwatersrand in 1886 and by 1900 some 100,000 men were employed in the gold fields. The gold rush made the original mining camp into the city of Johannesburg, which then had 237,000 people by 1911 and more than 1,000,000 at this writing. The gold was deep in the earth, requiring costly machinery and capital to recover it. Rhodes, with a dream to make all Africa British, got involved only politically in the gold industry as the British attempted to take this over. Conflicts inevitably followed with eventually a full-scale war. Many British at home were actually pro-Boer, including Lloyd George, but most of the people were staunchly imperialist. Paul Kruger, who had taken part in the Great Trek, headed the recalcitrant Dutch, who were unwilling to make common cause with the British. They opposed any advance of industry, although ready to feed on its profits.

In spite of long drawn out negotiation, actual war started October 9, 1899 when Boer groups moved over the border. The latter started with 35,000 men and artillery derived from German sources. Almost all were mounted. The German presence in the region was actually the main factor which had activated Britain to move north again. Suddenly in 1883 the Germans had run up their flag in Luederitz Bay on the Atlantic and proclaimed the whole of southwest Africa as a protectorate and began to survey a route for a railroad to the east, linking up with Paul Kruger in the Transvaal and then on to the east coast. The danger to Britain's holdings was obvious and so they moved, annexing Pondoland, Zululand and Tongaland, cutting off the only possible outlet of the Transvaal to the sea and then they took part of Bechuanaland. The countryside and world opinion was with the Dutch, but the British poured in men and arms and by autumn of 1900 both Boer capitals had been occupied and it seemed that the war was over. But the rebels fought on and were only finally subdued sufficiently to sue for peace in March 1902 after thousands of men, women and children had been swept into concentration camps. The total cost in money to the United Kingdom of the Boer War was reckoned at over 220,000,000 pounds. The British lost five times as many men from disease as from battle and left a legacy of mistrust and bitterness. (Ref. 48, 49, 50, 51, 52)

1 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

2 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

3 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

4 [254] CAPUTO, ROBERT, "Sudan: Arab-African Giant", National Geographic 161: 346-379, Mar. 1982.

5 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

6 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

7 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

8 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

9 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

10 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

13 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

14 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

15 [154] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

16 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

17 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

18 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

19 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

20 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

21 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

22 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

23 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

24 [217] De TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

25 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

26 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

27 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

28 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

29 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

30 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

31 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

32 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

33 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

34 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

35 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

36 [35] COBB, CHARLES E.,JR., "After Rhodesia, a Nation named Zimbabwe", National Geographic 160: 616-651, Nov. 1981).

37 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

38 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

39 [154] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Africa: Its Political Development", Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C., Feb. 1980.

40 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

41 [53] DURANT, WILL and ARIEL, Ibid., Part VIII - The Age of Louis XIV. (1963).

42 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

43 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

44 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

45 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

46 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

47 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

48 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

49 [160] OXENSTIERNA, ERIC, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

50 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

51 [322] FOSDICK, HARRY EMERSON, Riverside Sermons. (Harper & Bros., New York, 1958).

52 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

1.  As late as 1890, however, Stanley reported that he had found Mbuti pygmies living in symbiosis with neighboring Negroes in the Ituri forest. (Ref. 31)

2.  Stanley, born in Wales as John Rowlands, took the name of his adoptive father in New Orleans, fought on both sides of the American Civil War, found David Livingston on Lake Tanganyika in 1817 on commission by the New York Herald and finally sold his services for African exploration to Belgium. (Ref. 41)

3.  Similar to a zebra

4.  Except, as we have seen, in Ethiopia, where the Italians met defeat

America: Beginning to 8000 B.C.

NORTH AMERICA

At sometime between 40,000 and 10,000 B.C. human hunting groups occupied all the main land masses of earth except Antarctica. Men reached America about 20,000 B.C. (perhaps earlier) from Asia over a land bridge between Asia and Alaska, varying from three hundred to one thousand miles wide and apparently including the Aleutian Islands where blades and burins, perhaps dating back to 10,000 B.C. have been found. Otherwise the earliest known cultures of the American far north have not been well dated1. The so-called British Mountain Culture near the Yukon Arctic coast is probably the oldest, with artifacts of eastern Siberia, including crude instruments and shaping tools. There, in the Old Crow Basin, the first known occupation site in the New World has been tentatively carbon-dated to 25,000 B.C. The inhabitants were skilled users of bone, using mammoth and horse bone, the latter animals ranging in size from ponies to Percherons. Jaws of domesticated dogs appear to be 30,000 years old. At any rate, the people who came over the land bridge apparently simply followed their prey animals and were of a basic, general Mongoloid stock with skulls not much different from Caucasians and their descendants became the American Indians. The tools and skills spread from Asia to America with them and included the stone adze, spoons, combs of bone or horn, the toggle harpoon and eventually the bow and arrow. Marshack (Ref. 1) says the American Indians came in waves from Asia over a period of perhaps 20,000 years with some as late as 2,000 B.C. The latter figure is not further explained. We know that the land bridge was present off and on over several millennia, but never as late as 2,000 B.C. It is interesting that as late as 1962 this theory of the Asiatic origin of the American aborigines was not universally accepted. Greeman (Ref. 2) was committed to diffusion across the north Atlantic in skin-covered boats in the Upper Paleolithic times. He felt that Sandia Culture material in America was the same as the Solutrean of the Montaut site in southwest France. Blood typing studies beginning with Boyd (Ref. 3) in 1963 probably laid this theory to rest.

The great bulk of the people coming over the Bering land bridge may not have been able to migrate down into the region of the United States and farther south until about 12,000 years ago when the ice that had previously almost covered Canada finally melted enough to open a corridor east of the Rockies, at which time the Mongoloid hunters poured through to the gamelands of the American plains. Dr. Knut Fladmark (as quoted by Canby [Ref. 22]) of British Columbia argues that some men could have come south when the corridor was closed by leapfrogging down the coast where there were many ice-free pockets, by boat. Furthermore, recent work shows positively that much of the coast line and island archipelago off the coast of southern Alaska was never covered by glaciers at any time. (Ref. 5)

A slightly different view is given by Swanson et al (Ref. 6) who states that the first crossing of the Bering Strait occurred from 26,000 to 28,000 years ago and that these people became the American Indians with blood types chiefly O, with some A and no B. Then a second migration took place between 10,000 and 20,000 years ago which perhaps included the Eskimos who have AB and 0 blood types. They may have come by kayak from one shore to another as Eskimos today still live on both sides of the Bering Strait. By 10,000 B.C. prehistoric hunters were in all parts of the New World, even at Tierra del Fuego. Some fishing and gathering populations were very large. The highest average population density north of Mexico was in California where there were the acorn gatherers, a group which was so successful that they were not apt to experiment with new techniques. The most recent glaciation period in North America reached its maximum between 18,000 and 22,000 years ago and extended down to New York State and central Ohio, covering Minnesota, Wisconsin, Iowa, Illinois and parts of Kansas and Missouri. After 12,000 B.C. this retreated rapidly, sometimes several miles in a single year.

At 9,000 B.C. the American plains still teemed with giant bison, camels, stagmoose, musk-oxen, large cats, mastodons and three kinds of mammoths. Most of these were gone within 1,000 years of man's arrival. The dating of the flint spearheads of the Sandia Culture which have been found in Oregon, Ontario and New Mexico have been variously dated from 23,000 to 6,000 B.C. At any rate it was along the retreating ice edge, where the spruce forest and pines migrated north and west from the Appalachians and the oak moved north from the Gulf, that the increased parkland and grass allowed the human population, now with a radical new stone technology, to greatly increase. This was the time of the Great Hunting Culture, associated with the Clovis points of the Sandia Culture mentioned above. These Clovis points (so named because first identified near Clovis, New Mexico) were large, heavy flint points designed for hunting large animals, and butchered elephants have been excavated dating to the period 9,500 to 9,000 B.C. In some areas this culture, also sometimes called Llano, has been dated from 11,000 to 15,000 years ago. The Folsom spear points which developed from the Clovis were smaller and more delicately made, for effective use by the bison hunters.

As temperatures rose and the cloud cover diminished, there was an increased evaporation rate, the plant cover thinned and the great herds declined rapidly. Some feel that prior to the temperature rise the north-south corridor opened up in the glaciers allowing arctic winds to descend on the plains, and the sudden drop in temperature was a factor in the dying off of the giant bison and mastodons. The Desert Tradition of western North America, dating from about 9,000 B.C. was centered in the Great Basin of Nevada between the two great mountain chains and occupying portions of six present states - Nevada, Wyoming, Idaho, Oregon and California. Baskets and milling stones were made and the subsistence base included small seeds, berries, bulrush rhizomes and nuts.

In eastern United States, some forty miles south of Pittsburg is the Meadowcroft rock shelter where remains of Ice Age man includes a bifacial projectile point which may be ancestral to the Clovis point. The carbon-14 dating of the hearth is 14,000 B.C. but some doubt if this date is correct. (Ref. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15)

Concerning blood types, most North American Indians are exclusively type O but a few, such as the Sioux, Chippewa and Pueblo have 10 to 15% Group A while the rest are O. These may represent separate and later migration groups over the Bering land bridge, or, as shall be discussed later, possibly mixtures with Europeans or later Asiatics. (Ref. 16, 17)1

1 Texas radio-carbon dated to 10,000 years ago. Artifacts buried with them indicate trade, with sea shell pendants, red flints from the Texas Panhandle, projectile points from the plains and some tools. Some burial objects indicate a death ritual, perhaps related to a religion. Bones of cooked rabbits, turtles, raccoons and snakes were present. (Ref. 18)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

The National Geographic Society (Ref. 19) says that artefacts suggest man's presence at Puebla, Mexico by 20,000 B.C. although such early dates are not universally accepted. The rock shelters near Tehuacan have been continuously occupied since 10,000 B.C. In Central America gourd and squash date to prehistory along with various wild forms of beans, lentils and chickpeas. (Ref. 20)

SOUTH AMERICA

The tools of Pleistocene men who hunted camelids, sloths and perhaps horses have been unearthed at the bottom of a rock shelter on the western slope of the Andes cordillera. The presence of humans has been attested 13,000 years ago in Venezuela, Argentina and Peru. During the last phase of the Ice Age (the Wisconsin in North America) the Andean glaciers were as low as 11,000 feet and their melting later may account for the rarity of human sites during that chaotic period of terrific gorge flooding. After that, however, the Andes were certainly inhabited by numerous bands corresponding to the archaic societies of North America. In central Peru, at Chilca, where at 12,000 to 13,000 feet altitude only eight inches of rain fall in a year, caves with as many as fourteen archeological strata have been excavated. Perfectly preserved corpses of several people have been found indicating a stout but tall physique, varying from 65.2 to 69.2 inches in height according to sex, with long heads, protuberant jaws and strong bones. They had clothes made of cactus plant fibers or of reeds. Some had cloaks of vicuna skin, painted and sewn with the help of cactus spines. Weapons were slings and spear throwers with javelin points made from obsidian, basalt or quartz. Hand axes and scrapers were very similar to the European Mousterians', although separated in time by some 20,000 years. At about 13,000 B.C. the waters of the Pacific were some three hundred feet below present level, and at times since then they have been sixteen feet above the present level and have oscillated through the ages. This may have greatly disturbed the lives of the early dwellers by virtue of changes in the fresh water levels of the beaches of arid, western Peru.

Human living sites along with bones of sloths, horses, camelids and mastodons have also been found in the sierra region (the Atlantic Andes) of Columbia and Venezuela. Men may have reached the extreme tip of South America at Falls' Cave by 9,000 B.C. or shortly thereafter, but there may be some disagreement as to their origin. In this area Patagonian caves were inhabited during the high Holocene and immigrants from Australia or Southeast Asia may have entered the continent via Antarctica and the island of Tierra del Fuego. Still later other settlers came from the eastern Andes. On Tierra del Fuego the chief people were Onas - big, handsome men dressed in vicuna skins. They had domesticated dogs and poison arrows and removed their body hair with shells used as pincers.

The Lagoa Santa caves in Brazil show charcoal dating to between 18,000 and 20,000 B.C. and tools along with mastodon bones dating to 9,400 B.C. have been found in central Chile. El Ingo is a pre-ceramic site at an altitude of 9,100 feet in Ecuador, dating back to about 10,000 B.C. showing an obsidian workshop and hunting camp site. The tools show similarity to Folsom and Clovis points of North America. (Ref. 21, 22, 23)2

2C. and at the tip of South America dating to 10,000 B.C. (Ref. 24)

It has been the belief of authorities in the past that all Central and South American Indians had the blood type 0 exclusively. Very recent ABO blood-group antigen and HL-A white cell studies indicate that this was not true of Peruvian and Chilean coastal peoples even at 3,000 B.C. Both A and B were found in mummies of Paracas, Huari and Ica while AB was found in these areas plus those of the Huacho and Nazca. Only the Inca mummies were 100% 0 and only five of these were studied. Of only four Chile Atacamenas mummies typed, all were type A. We do not know what this means, but it is possible that these studies are compatible with ideas of pre-Columbian diffusion from Europe or Asia, a feature we shall discuss later. (Ref. 25) Professor Frederic Andre Engel (Ref. 26) who has spent most of his adult life as an archeologist in South America re-emphasizes that although one must accept an Asiatic foundation, evidences of strong foreign influences appear almost everywhere in the Americas, even in pre-Columbian times.

1 [130] MARSHACK, ALEXANDER, The Roots of Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1972).

2 [78] GREEMAN, E.F. Discussion of paper of Ronal J. Mason, Current Anthropology, Vol. 3, No. 3, pp. 252-254, 1962.

3 [17] BREFFNY, BRIAN DE, (Editor), The Irish World, (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. N.Y., 1977).

4 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [239] WORLEY, IAN A., "Ancient Environments & Age of Non-glaciated Terrain in Southeastern Alaska", National Geographic Research Reports, Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 731-732. (Publ. National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

6 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

7 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

8 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

9 [210] TAMARIN, ALFREDAND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [22] CANBY, Thomas Y., "The Search for the First Americans", National Geographic Vol.155 No. 3, page 330, Sept. 1979.

12 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

13 [224] VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

14 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

15 [21] BRONOWSKI, J., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

16 [21] BRONOWSKI, J., The Ascent of Man. (Little, Brown & Co. Boston, Toronto, 1973).

17 [155] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

18 [298] HANNERS, DAVID, "Archaeological find alters conceptions of early Indian life", Dallas Morning News, Feb. 20, 1983, pp. 1 & 2 AA.

19 [155] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

20 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

21 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

22 [22] CANBY, Thomas Y., "The Search for the First Americans", National Geographic Vol.155 No. 3, page 330, Sept. 1979.

23 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

24 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

25 [3] ALLISON, MARVIN J., "Studies of Pre-Columbian American Diseases 1971-1976, National Geographic Research Reports. Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 1-11 (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

26 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1 Trager (Ref. 4) even states that racemization tests on bone suggest that Neanderthal man may have been on the west coast of the western hemisphere at 50,000 B.C., but we have not seen confirmation from any other author and Trager does not reveal his source material.

America: 8000 to 5000 B.C.

NORTH AMERICA

The land bridge from Siberia to Alaska became inundated about 8,000 B.C. and, as mentioned previously, the later arriving Eskimos and Aleuts came by boat and represented the later, classical Mongolian race, as contrasted to the earlier original Mongolian stock who came over about 20,000 B.C. Possibly still later came the Athapascans, who slowly moved inland where many still live today in central, northern Canada. Some of these Athapascans eventually migrated down to the southwest United States where they became the Apaches and Navajos.1

1C. Mummies on neighboring islands are wrapped in furs and woven grasses. (Ref. 1)

In the United States area big game hunting continued throughout this period but with a gradual decrease in the number of animals available. By 8,000 B.C. North American Indian culture was already divided into three great patterns:

Eastern Woodlands, which will later be called "Archaic"
Desert, possibly related to Eastern Woodland
Western Paleo-Indian

Although the Eastern Woodlands actually existed from 8,000 B.C. to about 1,000 B.C., during this 8,000 to 5,000 B.C. period under discussion it was called "Early Archaic" and was characterized by big game hunting with fishing and shell and plant gathering. Burial mounds were being built in eastern Canada by 5,000 B.C. (Ref. 2) In the mid-west there was a related sub-culture called "Modoc", with evidence of mano and metate (stone mortar and pestle) existing about 7,200 B.C. Another variation existed in the Ozarks, Oklahoma and Mississippi.2

2C. (Ref. 3)

The Western Paleo-Indian Culture was originally a big game hunting tradition congregated in the Great Basin lying between the Cascade Mountains of southern Oregon and the Rockies of Idaho and running south through Nevada, western Utah and the eastern part of California. The "Old Cordilleran Tradition" is a name given to the culture of Indians in the Oregon and Washington areas dating from 7,800 to 5,700 B.C. who used characteristic flaked stone points known as "Cascade points". Around 7,000 B.C. some of the hunters from the Great Basin area migrated south into the mountains and tablelands of the southwest- i.e. southern Colorado and Utah, along with Arizona, New Mexico and the Mexican states of Sonoro and Chihuahua. This migration was probably precipitated by weather changes which were making semi-arid deserts of the previous great savannahs of the Basin, and the consequent disappearance of the game. One large branch of these ancient immigrants to the southwest has been given the name recently of "Cochise" (from a county in Arizona). The so-called Sulfur Springs Phase of this culture ran from 7,000 to 5,000 B.C. and was a society dependent on hunting ancient horses, mammoths, antelope and bison with flaked projectile points. The Lake Mojave area of southern California has yielded kite-shaped points, choppers, drills and scrapers, some of which have been dated back to 9,000 B.C. At 6,000 B.C. the climate changed with a marked rise in temperature associated with drought. The great herds died out including the mastodons and camels. Many areas were denuded and there was a shifting of Indian population and a change in their living patterns. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

By 7,000 B.C. in the Tehuacan Valley of Mexico there were people living in rock shelters and using stone cooking pots which were left in the center of the hearth. Maize was used in the same valley between 6,000 and 5,000 B.C. and at some point the turkey was domesticated. Before the development of pottery some peoples may have used animal stomachs as liquid containers to hang over fires. In the same valley there is evidence of the use of six food resources--the maguey plant, cactus fruits (prickly pear), tree legumes like the mesquite, wild grasses, deer and rabbits. Cultivated plants probably made up only 5% of the diet, as opposed to 54% from hunting and 41% from collecting wild plants. The common bean and maize were introduced into the valley about 5,000 B.C. Maize apparently went under considerable genetic change with cultivation, but since it lacks an important amino acid, it was fortunate for the Indians that it was eaten in connection with beans, which supplied the deficit. (See also Africa in the 16th century C.E.). There was squash in the Mexican highlands before 5,000 B.C. (Ref. 7, 8)

SOUTH AMERICA

As early as 8,000 B.C. the need for artistic expression apparently existed in the high Andes. We mentioned in the last chapter that prehistoric people had painted clothing, but now we can add necklaces, bracelets, carved pendants and geometrically marked bones, painted green. These people ate prickly pear cactus, alder seeds, tomatoes and plants with rhizomes and tubers such as jiquimas, potatoes, ullucu and possibly manioc and sweet potatoes. There is also refuse of many land mammals such as bucks and roe deer, vixcahas, camelids and rodents, as well as the remains of fish. Although the caves were sixty miles from the ocean, marine mollusks have been found, suggesting that these men migrated at times to the seashore, probably living in the condensed fog oases called lomas, as the beach land otherwise is completely arid. By 7,000 B.C. there were all sorts of projectile points in Venezuela, Chile, Bolivia and Peru. Long-headed human skeletons along with both extinct and modern animals have been found in Brazil dated to the same time.

Natives of both Americas are of extremely varied types. In South America there are people with Caucasian appearance but dark brown skin, along with Mongolian types with African faces, but of pale or sallow complexion. Big, straight non-aquiline noses are seen frequently near Cuzco in the high Andes, where non-Mongolian characteristics mix with true Asiatic ones. Many scholars such as Julian Steward, Paul Rivet, Miguel Covarrubias and Heine Gildern, as well as Heyerdahl and Fell, who will be mentioned often in this manuscript, are all coming to the conclusion that transoceanic voyages from southern Asia, Polynesia, even Australia or Africa, have helped people the New World since the Bering Strait migration. The early men of 8,000 to 4,000 B.C. unearthed in the excavations of Professor Engel (Ref. 9) were all dolichocephals, prognathous, big-boned and tall, whereas the 16th century people found by the Spaniards were of only mediocre height, meso or brachycephalic with short limbs and slender frames.

By 6,000 B.C. some Andean populations were already advanced to the stage of comparable groups in the Near East, not yet true farmers or herders, but living a sedentary type of life, occupying well defined territories. On a south Peruvian plain between mountain spurs, inland from the coast at about the 16th parallel, there were hundreds of inhabitants using water from now dry wadis. Seashore villages of the same millennium have also been found and because of the complete surface dessication, humans have been uncovered by simply brushing off the sand. They still have their clothes, skin and eyes after 7,000 to 9,000 years. Milling stones have been found in every hut and in graves, particularly in the Santa Valley of Peru and the eastern Andes. It is possible that llamas and alpacas began to be domesticated on the eastern slopes at about 6,000 B.C.

In the Columbia and Venezuela areas between 7,000 and 3,000 B.C. Meso-Indians lived, eating seafood, berries, seeds, roots and tubers. Remnant now can be identified by the large mounds of shells, ashes and food debris. These northern South Americans were also navigators, for traces of the same people are found on all adjacent islands. Documentation regarding humid Chile and Argentina is lacking in this early period, although groups of pre-agriculturalists certainly occupied the western slope of the Chilean Andes at times about 8,000 B.C. although perhaps not continuously. It is possible that some fifty valleys in central Peru and arid Chile were inhabited by groups of up to 2,000 people before agriculture appeared on the coast. (Ref. 10, 11, 12)

1 [310] MORGAN LAEL, "Alaska's Far Out Islands: The Aleutians", National Geographic 164, No. 3: 336-363, Sept. 1983.

2 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

3 [298] HANNERS, DAVID, "Archaeological find alters conceptions of early Indian life", Dallas Morning News, Feb. 20, 1983, pp. 1 & 2 AA.

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

6 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

7 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

8 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

9 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

10 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

11 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

12 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

America: 5000 to 3000 B.C.

NORTH AMERICA

1. FAR NORTH AND CANADA

In the far north there was a micro-blade tradition called "Little Arm" with evidence of caribou and elk hunting dated from 5,500 to 4,000 B.C. In Canada by 4,000 B.C. the Maritime Provinces were settled by hunters, fishers, and gatherers. The Columbia plateau folks, previously mentioned, were hunting elk and deer in the forests of Douglas fir and western yellow pine, and fishing for salmon in the Columbia by 9,000 B.C. (Ref. 1, 2)

2. THE UNITED STATES

Between 5,000 and 3,800 B.C. the temperature lowered again and precipitation increased so that some game returned as the climate approached what it is today. Even so the hunting cultures gradually gave way to a type in which the people were not specialized in a single skill but were versatile enough to attempt other things.

In the Eastern Woodlands there was now a "Middle Period" with great variation from area to area. Some used antlers and bones for fish-hooks, spears and harpoons, some learned to use copper for tools and ornaments. In the latter respect, a distinctive culture of the Great Lakes and upper Mississippi Valley, beginning about 4,500 B.C., was the "Old Copper Culture" in which the metal was worked either in the cold or hot state, but it was never melted or cast. Knives, barbed harpoon points and atlatl weights (throwing sticks) were made in this way. There was no big game present and most of the inhabitants of the eastern societies used steatite vessels. The earliest of the Archaic Cultures is sometimes called the southern "Indian Knoll Society", with a later northern Lauretain Culture about the Great Lakes and on eastward where along the Labrador coast it eventually came face to face with Eskimos. (Ref. 3, 4, 5)

The western Desert Culture was oriented toward plants, collecting of small seeds and roots for food. Plant fibers were used for baskets, footwear and nets for snares.

In the southwest, the Chircahua Phase of the Cochise Culture made its appearance about 5,000 B.C. and was to last about 3,000 years. It was there that maize first appeared in the United States, sometime between 3,000 and 2,000 B.C., apparently brought up from Mexico where it had been cultivated long before. The Cochise could grow the corn because they had the soil, the right growing season and the necessary skills and tools. They could already weave baskets in which to store it and had long used grinding tools to pulverize seeds and nuts. This early desert society later gave way to the Pueblo and Mexican empires. In California the San Diego County Archeological Society recently brought suit against a land development firm, alleging that it intentionally marred a site thought to have been occupied by La Jolla Indians 3,000 to 7,000 years ago1 . Excavations on Catalina Island just off the California coast, show that man gorged himself on abalone in the 4th millennium B.C., almost wiping out the colonies (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN

Santa Luisa, in the Veracruz area was occupied before 4,000 B.C. and became major trade center with an extensive irrigation system . The people were successful hunters and gatherers as well as early farmers. By 3,500 Mexican cave inhabitants relied heavily on agriculture. One third of their food came from domesticated plants, including maize, beans and others. Maize was destined to play the same role here that wheat and barley did in the Near East. In the Tamaulipas Mountains they had begun to domesticate summer squash and chili pepper, and the bottle gourd (as a water container). Early man also ate grasshoppers, ants and termites.

We speculated at the beginning of this chapter that the time of about 3,100 B.C. might have been a milestone in history when some fantastic upheaval occurred in the Atlantic, with far-reaching secondary effects in the development of early civilizations in Egypt and the Near East. It is amazing then, to find the zero date in the incredibly accurate Maya Calendar, which will be described later, to be "4 Ahau Cumhu", which converts to our calendar as August 12, 3,113 B.C.! No satisfactory explanation of that date has ever been given, but Maya written and oral texts and those of their descendant civilizations claim descent from a civilized people who sailed in from the east! (Ref. 11, 12, 13)

SOUTH AMERICA

Dating to probably about 5,000 B.C., in those last centuries before real agriculture, is the partially excavated village on a loma at Paloma on the dry Peruvian coast. The village extends over 1,900 feet in length at an altitude of 660 to 825 feet. Engle (Ref. 14) excavated only 2 trenches, removing 35,000 cubic feet of ruble, using only trowels and brushes. Some 90 graves and 45 huts were thus exposed and from that he estimated, by extrapolation, that complete uncovering of the entire village areas would involve 7,000,000 cubic feet of debris to be removed to reveal 9,000 graves in and around some 4,000 to 5,000 houses. Obviously this was not done.

Radio-carbon datings indicate that cotton and beans were present in the upper inter-Andean valleys about 6,000 B.C. but in the coastal villages they were not present until 5,000 B.C. or shortly thereafter. At Chilca, about 45 miles south of Lima, portions of another village have been excavated, showing multiple archeological layers, indicating multiple re-occupations. Carbon 14 dating indicates the earliest habitation at 3,500 B.C. Large mollusks were present but are no longer to be found, so the shore line may then have been much farther east and the retreat of the ocean-line and consequently the mollusks, may have led to the abandonment of the site. Only a few sites have been uncovered, since a cubic yard of kitchen midden weighs about 2,600 pounds and so sifting a village of 7 1/2 acres that forms a mound 1 yard thick means the "---sifting some 36,000 tons of debris, the equivalent of a train 1,000 cars long"2.

Maize was brought down from Mexico, but potatoes and manioc were developed from local plants. The earliest dated pottery in the New World is from Colombia, from 3,090 B.C., sand-tempered with wide-lined incising. Cotton has been used for at least 4,000 to 6,000 years in the Andes, replacing other plants that could be used for spinning and making cloth.

We have written something of Patagonia and Tierra del Fuego in the last chapter. The islands of the western archipelago off the tip of South America were still blocked by ice until about 5,000 B.C. and the Alacaluf arrived after that time. They were a little people with the men ranging from 61 to 62.5 inches and the women 56.9 to 57.7 inches, with a truly Asiatic appearance, including thick black hair, Mongoloid spots and very little body hair. They lived entirely from the ocean, diving off boats made of boards sewed together. Later these people were sold as slaves by the Chonos to the north. (Ref. 16, 17)

1 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

6 [106] JONES, ROBERT A., "State's Past Being Sacrificed in Rush to Future", Los Angeles Times, Oct. 1975.

7 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

8 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

9 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

10 [106] JONES, ROBERT A., "State's Past Being Sacrificed in Rush to Future", Los Angeles Times, Oct. 1975.

11 [236] WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

12 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

13 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

14 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

15 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

16 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

17 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1. Complaints have been made that other construction projects have destroyed hundreds of prehistoric Indian sites in California. Estimates give more than 600 Yokuts villages, campsites and burial grounds in Merced and Stanislaus counties. Logging operations in the Sierra Nevada range have churned up innumerable similar sites. Along the south coast there were Chumash, Gabrielinos, Fernandenos and some others, depending upon a fishing and food gathering existence. These people were apparently free of intertribal wars and did not have the cyclical famines suffered by groups dependent upon farm crops. They lived in large villages, used plank canoes and traded with villages on the Channel Islands, often bartering the coastal basketry for effigies carved from the steatite rock of Catalina (Ref. 10).

2. From Engel (Ref. 15), page 98.

America: 3000 to 1500 B.C.

FAR NORTH AND CANADA

There were always more people on the Aleutian Islands than on the mainland, because of a milder climate. Nevertheless, from 4,000 to 1,000 B.C. an Arctic Small Tool tradition existed in Alaska, spreading across the arctic part of Canada to Greenland, given its name from the miniature blades lashed to handles of bone or walrus ivory used for cutting and scraping skins. The blades were chipped from a core of chert, a rock of micro-crystalline quartz. These Asiatic people even migrated to Ellesmere Island in northeastern Canada, less than 800 miles from the North Pole, about 2,300 B.C., crossing over the mountains in a great notch, today known as Sverdrup Pass, to the upper end of Baffin Bay, which usually has open water at least in the summer. Canadian archeologists have excavated some of these pre-historic sites, where the earliest are now thirty to thirty-five meters above the present sea level, although they were originally on the beach. As in other northern areas of the globe, the earth's crust has risen slowly over the centuries after the lifting of the great weight of the glacial ice. From Ellesmere Island progress into northern Greenland over winter ice was no problem. By about 1,500 B.C. in British Columbia (and Washington state) people were settled in villages and fished for salmon, although they did not practice cultivation. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

This is the era of the so-called Red Paint Culture, with native Amerindian Stone Age traditions derived from old northeastern Asia. The Red Paint or Moorehead Culture originally described from prehistoric graveyards in Maine - the graves containing red ochre has now been identified as part of a larger maritime Archaic tradition extending from northern Labrador at the 60th parallel to southern Maine between about 2,000 and 1,500 B.C. This area was deglaciated about 7,000 B.C. with tundra then present until about 3,000 when spruce forests finally appeared. The settlement pattern and life styles of these Red Paint people seems to have been different from both the Eskimos and the Montagnais-Naskopi Indians of inland Labrador and Quebec. Hunting, fishing, trading tools and raw materials and burying their dead were definable activities. The roots of this culture may have extended back several thousand years to the Paleo-Indian hunters of the now submerged continental shelf. (Ref. 4)

THE UNITED STATES

The reader is advised to review the preceding two paragraphs concerning Maine and Washington State. In the east the eastern Archaic Culture was changing about 2,000 B.C. in that there was the manufacture of some crude pottery and there was an increased attention to burial observances. Some call this the beginning of the Woodland Culture and others call it simply the Late Period of the Archaic of the Eastern Woodland. At the same time, in the southwestern states, specialized desert cultures continued to develop from the Archaic. As recorded in the last chapter, the Cochise began cultivating corn sometime from 3,000 to 2,000 B.C., providing them extra nourishment for their uncertain diet. Squash now was also brought up from Mexico and tiny gardens of both have been found all over the Cochise wandering area. Santa Catalina Island, twenty miles off the California coast, as previously noted, was inhabited and some forty Indian town sites have been identified. It is obvious that coastal Indians had facilities for ocean travel. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN

The "Pre-Classic Age" of Middle America traditionally began about 2,000 B.C. with Mayan ancestors being simple village farmers, although the earliest Maya carbon dating on the Caribbean side of Yucatan goes back to between 2,750 and 2,450 B.C. It is entirely possible the Maya beginnings may go back to Ecuador at 3,000 B.C. while the Olmec civilization began separately on the Gulf coast much later. In 1977 Norman Hammond (Ref. 9) published results of archeological excavations in Belize (formerly British Honduras) which seem to confirm the origins of the Maya back at about 2,600-2,500 B.C. He describes a lowland pottery called "Swash", found in burial sites with human skeletons. The adults among the latter showed advanced tooth wear, suggesting abrasives in their diet. The Maya steeped corn in slaked lime before boiling, to soften it (and incidentally it released certain amino-acids not otherwise absorbable) and this lime, along with grit derived in the grinding process probably accounted for the tooth wear. These individuals also constructed raised earth platforms in swamps by digging out drainage channels and throwing the mud up to make platforms on which various crops were grown. The presence of jade, not naturally present within 350 kilometers, indicates a trade network. Their Swasey ceramics - colorful, decorative and mature - are different from that of Mexico and the southern United States of 2,500 B.C., but are similar to Ecuadorian pottery of this period. Throughout Central America maize-farming had become the basis of life by 1,500 B.C. and the farmers lived in permanent villages. By the same date in the Tehuacan Valley of Mexico, there was complex village life, pottery, elaborated religious rituals and intricate social organization. Corn and pottery have been dated to 2,000 B.C. in Panama. (Ref. 10, 11, 12, 13, 14)

SOUTH AMERICA

Valdiva, as a coastal society in Ecuador, like Panama, had corn and pottery by about 2,000 B.C.1. Evans and Meggers, of the Smithsonian Museum, are impressed with the similarities between Valdivian pottery and the Jomon pottery of Japan, believing Ecuador may have been the landing place of a Japanese immigration, thus bringing one more possibility of Asian diffusion to the Americas. We shall examine other ideas in other chapters. Potatoes were cultivated in the Andes by 3,000 B.C., manioc was grown on the tropical lowlands and there were domesticated animals in South America shortly after 2,000 B.C. Ceremonial centers found along the desert coast of Peru date to about the same time as did evidence of metal working. The Ancon Yacht site on the coast of Peru, dated 2,500 to 2,000 B.C. showed chipped leaf points, string, turned cloth and baskets, wooden tools, shell fishhooks and cultivated plants which included gourds, cotton and chili peppers.

The Peruvians used the potato by 3,000 and soon domesticated the guinea pig for food. Coastal Peruvians gathered protein-rich shell fish off the beaches by 2,800 and by 2,500 B.C., when the villages were large, far out ocean fishing for larger fish was common. (Ref. 16, 17, 18, 19, 20)

Early farmers were probably well established on the Ecuadorian sea coast and river plains by 3,000 B.C. Contact with Mesoamerica was certainly possible by water, but otherwise there was a 2,000 mile jungle stretch between them. What Engel (Ref. 21) calls the "bean planters society" came into being in the lower central Andes, along with cotton clothes and underwear at about 2,000 B.C. The bones of sea-lions are mixed with those of these early agriculturalists. Excavations in Venezuela, like adjacent areas, show evidence of manioc and sweet potato cultivation from between 3,000 and 2,700 B.C. Both of these are root crops, but manioc required special preparation to be made palatable. (Ref. 22, 23, 24)

1 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

4 [69] GARRETT, W.E., "China's Beauty Spot", National Geographic 156: 536, Oct. 1979.

5 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

6 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

7 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

8 [187] SANTA CATALINA ISLAND, Pamphlet by Santa Catalina Island Co., Avalon, Calif.

9 [85] HAMMOND, NORMAN, "The Earliest Maya", Scientific American 236: 116-133, Mar. 1977.

10 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

11 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

12 [85] HAMMOND, NORMAN, "The Earliest Maya", Scientific American 236: 116-133, Mar. 1977.

13 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

14 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

15 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

16 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

17 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

18 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

19 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

20 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

21 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

22 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

23 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

24 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

1. Thomas (Ref. 15) says the Ecuadorians had pottery even earlier, at 3,200 B.C.

America: 1500 to 1000 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

The Arctic Small Tool tradition continued across northern Canada to Greenland and the Pacific coast Indians continued their salmon fishing, without attempting cultivation. By 1,000 B.C. they were building villages along the Snake, Columbia and Fraser rivers south of the Snake, there were large oval dwellings with floors and a timber frame, usually about twenty-five by thirty feet. (Ref. 1)

THE UNITED STATES

The Indians of North America originally had lived by hunting game and gathering wild foods, but about 3,000 years ago they began making clay vessels, an innovation that accompanied the appearance of agriculture in many areas. The pottery found in various excavation sites in the United States has a distinctive gritty temper and is often decorated with fabric or cord impressions. One village, called the Baumer site, in southern Illinois, covered more than ten acres and was made up of houses about sixteen feet square. The use of local strains of corn, beans and squash after 1,500 B.C. gave people the surplus of food and time needed to engage in some communal activities. The first signs of mound building appeared in the middle west about 1,000 B.C. as some villages began to bury their dead under low earth mounds. In the southwest the Cochise continued their gradual transition from hunter-gatherers to true farmers. (Ref. 2, 3)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN

Village life in Mexico continued to show more advanced societies. In the Oaxaca Valley there were villages with agriculture dominant by 1,300 B.C. Each village contained ten to twenty houses which were single family units made of wattle and daub, all opening into a common plaza. By 1,200 in San Jose Mogote in the same valley, the people began to build large platforms with limed walls and floors. (Ref. 4, 5) Recent excavations at Dzibilchaltun in northern Yucatan indicate that this site, which contained one of the largest of the Mayan cities of the late post-classic period of A.D.600 or later, had been continuously occupied since 1,500 B.C., so that in all probability pre-Mayan or Mayan people lived there with an ever increasing level of civilization for over 2,000 years.

The big story of this period, however, is that of the Olmecs who had developed a civilization in the humid, low-lying, forest region of southern Veracruz and western Tabasco by 1,200 B.C. Most authorities agree (with a few dissenters) that this remarkable society appeared suddenly, without known antecedents. They were the first Meso-Americans to handle large masses of stone in monumental sculptures and they may have been responsible for extending the growth of maize in that area, chiefly by example or leadership, as they were not the basic inhabitants of the region. The latter were ethnically Huastec while the Olmecs were apparently an hereditary ruling class who promoted efficient farming techniques, long distance trade net-works, large temples and public buildings, fine art, an official state religion and social stratification. The question of pre-Columbian contacts with America has been brought up time and again, particularly regarding this advanced, suddenly appearing Olmec civilization, but the nature and method of such contact and whether or not it occurred at all, continues to be debated.

Like the Egyptians, the Olmecs (and later Mayas) wrote in hieroglyphs, developed a calendar and predicted the movements of planets. These Central Americans built flat-topped pyramids similar to the ziggurats of Mesopotamia and decorated those with bas-reliefs showing priests with Semitic facies and long beards. There is even some botanical evidence of European contact in that the Olmec successors wore garments from a strain of cotton that seemed to be a cross between a local, wild type and the long-staple Egyptian cotton. The latter has thirteen large chromosomes and the native central and South American cotton, which was short stapled, had thirteen small chromosomes per cell, but the cotton used for cloth later in Central America was a hybrid of the two above and contained twenty-six chromosomes, thirteen small and thirteen large. One has to wonder if it is just coincidence that these Olmecs developed writing, calendar systems, pyramids etc. directly at the terminus of the strong Atlantic Canary Current, flowing from the bulge of Africa through the Canary Islands to the Gulf of Mexico at the base of the Yucatan peninsula. The swampy, unfavorable jungle coast in which this civilization developed would suggest that it must have arrived almost in full bloom, from the sea. The Egyptians and Phoenicians knew more about astronomy, the key to ocean navigation, than the later European contemporaries of Columbus and Pizarro, and it is definitely known that the Phoenicians had settlements all the way down the Atlantic coast of Morocco by 1,000 B.C. (Ref. 6, 7, 8)

There is also the possibility of still other peoples being the source of early foreign diffusion to the New World. Heyerdahl (Ref. 9) lists fifty-two examples of common characteristics seen in the early civilizations of Asia Minor (Hittite), Cyprus and Crete and the early societies of Central America and Peru. These include priest-king dynasties in sun-worshipping administrations, brother-sister royal marriages, fully developed script writing1, paper manufacture from vegetable fibers, stone masonry of amazing accuracy without the use of mortar and with methods of long range transportation of gigantic stone blocks, colossal stone statues, repetitive representations of a bearded man (all true Amerindians of Siberian origin should be beardless) fighting a giant snake standing on its tail, a bird-man standing on a plumed serpent (See Hittites, this chapter), construction of ziggurat types of pyramids, mummification of deceased royalty, trepanning of skulls, circumcision as a religious ritual, cities of adobe houses separated by streets and with water and sewer systems, large scale terrace agriculture with irrigation and fertilizers, similar cotton looms and garments, identical leather and rope sandals (although the latter were useless in the tropical swamps), feather crowns used by nobles, similar organization of standing armies and weaponry, similar tools and utensils, use of red dyes from mollusks, identical stages of metallurgy with outstanding gold work, ceramic, polychrome funeral ware, clay models of daily life, as well as a universal female goddess, stamped seals, curved wooden figurines, understanding of the "zero" concept, belief in their own origin in the first century of the 3rd millennium B.C., remarkably high standard of calendar system and finally the same ocean-going reed ships with canvas sail hoisted on a double-legged mast. We should also note that the date of the blooming of the Olmec civilization at 1,200 (+200) B.C. is the same time often given for the Thera upheaval in the Mediterranean, with the subsequent possible displacement of the Sea People who roved the Mediterranean and possibly the Atlantic! Self portraits of the Olmecs on colossal monoliths have shown two contrasting types - one with Negroid physiognomy and the other with typical Semitic features with long flowing beard - all this in the swampland exactly at the end of the Canary Current. (Ref. 10)

It is difficult to be certain of the exact physical type of the original Central and South American Indians, since the populations that came back to life after the territories became independent of Spain, are now so cross-bred with Europeans, Chinese and Africans that identification is impossible. The Chinese factor brings up still another diffusion theory that has been advanced as late as 1975 by Betty Meggers (Ref. 11) of the Smithsonian Institute, who believes that the invaders were Chinese from the Shang Dynasty! As others have, she points out that in Meso-America2 as late as 2,000 B.C. there was only one village per kilometer in the estuary systems along the Chiapas-Guatemala coast, but about 1,200 B.C. something unusual occurred - the sudden appearance of the Olmec civilization in full flower - and she relates that this event was felt almost simultaneously over almost all of Mesoamerica. This corresponds in time to the end of the Shang Dynasty, in China. Meggers feels that one of the most striking aspects of this new society was the extent of traffic in raw materials such as obsidian, basalt, magnetite, ilmenite, himatite, serpentine and jadeite, along with the transportation of the heavy, basalt boulders over long distances. She points out a great number of shared cultural features of the Shang and the Olmec societies including:

writing, stating that a few, often repeated Olmec symbols resemble Shang characters, and later Maya glyphs were read top to bottom in Shang fashion (characters of Minoan Linear A of Crete were read similarly)
jade, a primary commodity of long distance trade in both societies
batons as a symbol of rank, some with bifurcated tops
feline deity, the Shang tiger and the Olmec jaguar both associated with the earth god and both often drawn lacking a lower jaw
worship of mountains
cranial deformation, apparently artificially produced in the center of the head of rulers
large groups of scattered villages with central service Centers
the construction of rectangular platforms with a north-south orientation.

When asked why the Mesoamericans did not use the wheel, which was certainly used by the Shang, she replied, as others have, that the Americans had no use for the wheel in the absence of roads and draft animals, the ruggedness of the terrain and the ability of a man to carry more than his weight in fragile cargo.

As might be expected, refutations of Meggers' theory soon appeared. David Grove (Ref. 12) of the University of Illinois says that the society which we have mentioned as being in the Oaxaca Valley between 1,500 and 1,400 B.C. was a complex culture and perhaps preceded those of the Gulf coast, and would more apt to be the Olmec ancestor than the Shang. Furthermore, he says that the jade carving may not even have been Olmec and that the feline deity idea came up from South America. He also makes the point that excavations by Coe at San Lorenze on the Gulf coast since 1970 have revealed significant Olmec cultural levels which predate those at La Venta, but also pre-Olmec levels, suggesting that the Olmec culture appeared gradually rather than suddenly. Meggers immediately replied to this in a publication in 1976 (Ref. 13) stating that twenty-three of the references she had consulted for her previous publication had been written between 1970 and 1974 and that she was still convinced that Shang refugees were involved in Central America. The concept of the sudden appearance of the Olmec society seems to be given another boost by the 1977 publication, The Encyclopedia of Archeology (Ref. 14) which discusses recent investigations at San Lorenzo by Yale University, describing that center as having the longest stratigraphic history of any known Olmec center and that it was constructed on an artificially raised mass of land, built by the Olmecs to support a number of earthern pyramid constructions, plazas and mounds, all laid out along a north-south axis. The writer indicated that the Olmec Culture was emerging at this site just in 1,250 B.C. and that most of the pure Olmec monuments and structures actually date from 1,150 B.C. onwards.

Whether or not the Olmec civilization was imported or local in origin, there is no doubt but what this was the mother of all later true civilizations in Central America, including the Mayan. Probable extensions of the Olmec into more central Mexico are indicated by recent excavations at Chalcatzingo in the state of Morelos, about 85 miles southeast of Mexico City. Radio-carbon datings are from 1,170 B.C. on, and the findings include bas-relief carvings, platform complexes, etc., all typical of the Olmec style. It has been postulated that it was a center for controlling the trade of highland raw materials (obsidian, jade, iron ore and possibly cotton) and channeling these on to the Gulf coast centers. Contacts with nearby Oaxaca seem to have stimulated cultural growth there, as well (or was it vice-versa, as suggested by Grove?). At any rate, within a few centuries, Oaxaca, with its vastly greater resources and richer agricultural possibilities, with irrigation, actually began to be the dominant partner. (Ref. 15, 16)

Still another, separate culture is suggested by fairly recent excavations at La Victoria, Guatemala, where Micheal Coe (Ref. 17) has uncovered iridescent ceramic pottery as a unique technological feature dating from 1,500 to 800 B.C. This same unusual pottery has been found also in Peru, and it seems possible that the technology may have gone from Guatemala to Peru where the earliest dating by radio-carbon is 714 B.C. (+ 200 years). If this diffusion did occur, it was probably by boat for that is only a 1,300 mile sea trip and has been shown possible by Heyerdahl's raft voyage and the presence of ancient sherds on Galapagos Islands, which lie 650 miles off the Ecuador coast. Other pottery of Middle America was highly developed but had no local ancestry and Coe suggests that it possibly migrated down from the Woodland Culture of North America.

SOUTH AMERICA

Several of the immediately preceding paragraphs, particularly those concerning the possible cultural derivations from pre-Columbian European migration were applicable to parts of South America as well. We should now make some observations peculiar to the latter, however. For one thing, the South Americans did not have writing and why this did not arrive with other Mid-American cultural features, if there was indeed early contact, remains an enigma. As far as the illiteracy is concerned, however, we shall discover later in this text that illiteracy did not hamper the Scandinavian Vikings or the Mongol Khans. The most spectacular excavation, abandoned between 1,500 and 1,400 B.C. according to carbon-dating, is El Paraiso, near Lima, just three miles east of the ocean on the Chillon River valley. This consists of seven architectural units, of which one has been pretty well restored. The units were enormous buildings made of two rows of heavy quarried and roughly-shaped stone blocks cemented with unfired clay and the gaps filled with rubble. The buildings were of various sizes and shapes, some a thousand feet long; some almost square 165 by 132 feet. There were wide stair cases and various halls and rooms, some of which must have been for storage while others were for festivities and still others living quarters. A single building would reach thirty feet high. A similar building complex has also been found higher up in the valley, thirty-six miles from Lima. Trepanation and deliberate deformation of skulls (see also Mexico, Central America and the Caribbean) was practiced frequently in this period. In the last chapter we discussed the "bean planters" of Peru. Archeology indicates that El Paraiso and all the bean planters' villages were abandoned at about the same time, apparently around 1,500 to 1,400 B.C.. No explanation has been found for this rather sudden and complete disappearance of this society, and furthermore it appears that the Peruvian coast probably remained deserted for one to three centuries thereafter. Skeletons supplied to physical anthropologists by Frederic Engel from the vicinity of the last of these pre-ceramic, bean eaters show the presence of a different ethnic group with cross-breeding, as evidenced by the presence of brachycephalic and mesocephalic skulls in addition to the older dolichocephalic. One can image that foreign ethnic groups may have brought a plague that killed the bean planters, but one cannot rule out severe climatic change as the cause.

Corn growing had appeared in the central Andes, both in the cordillera and on the coast by 1,500 B.C. Although previously used on the Caribbean coast, pottery does not seem to have been introduced in western Peru until about 1,300 B.C. Engle (Ref. 18) had found some in the central Peruvian lower Andes carbon-dated in the 3,300 to 3,500 B.C. range, so perhaps both corn and pottery were brought over from the eastern slopes of the mountains. Near Lake Titicaca and in the Cordillera de la Viuda, northeast of Lima, early types of pottery have been found dating between 1,500 and 1,300 B.C. and this pottery has subsequently been found everywhere in caves and rock shelters in the upper Andes. The corn raisers and pottery makers were apparently a new, migrating people, and did not represent merely a change in culture of the bean planters. Basically by 1,320 B.C. Americans ate corn as the Europeans ate wheat and the Asians rice. Seafood, especially shellfish, however, always played an important part of the Andes peoples' diets, supplying protein that they lacked in the absence of meat. A deep refuse midden on the coast of Peru has revealed a cultivated gourd, used for various artifacts in a fishing culture. These were only later found in Polynesia. By 1,000 B.C. Peruvians had hallucinogens and alcohol and were smoking cigars, although the leaf was not tobacco. (Ref. 19, 20)

1 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

2 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

3 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

6 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

7 [209] SWANSON, EARL H; BRAY, WARWICK; FARRINGTON, IAN, The New World. (E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, 1975).

8 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

9 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

10 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

11 [141] MEGGERS, BETTY J., "The Transpacific Origin of Meso American Civilization: A Preliminary Review of the Evidence and its theoretical Implications", American Anthropologist 77: 1-271, 1975.

12 [80] GROVE, DAVID C., "Olmec Origins and Transpacific Diffusion: Reply to Meggers", American Anthropology 78: 634-637, 1976.

13 [142] MEGGERS, BETTY J., "Yes if by Land, No if by Sea: The Double Standard in Interpreting Cultural Similarities", American Anthropologist 78: 637, 1976.

14 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

15 [81] GROVE, DAVID C., "Archeological Investigations at Chalcatzingo, 1972, 1973." National Geographic Reports Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 287-304, (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980.

16 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

17 [36] COE, MICHAEL D. "Archeological Linkage with North & South America at La Victoria, Guatemala", American Anthropologist 62: 363-393, 1960.

18 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

19 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

20 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

1.  Not in South America.

2.  Strictly speaking the term "Mesoamerica" includes Guatemala, Belize, Western Honduras, El Salvador and only southern Mexico, including Yucatan.

America: 1000 to 700 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

The Arctic Small Tool tradition continued in the far north. Centered at the Fraser River delta about 1,000 B.C. and extending from southern Alaska down to northern California, was the Northwest Coast Tradition. Eskimo and Old Cordilleran traditions may have contributed to this society which included hunting and gathering of multiple river and marine foods - mollusks, salmon, halibut, whale, seal and sea otter. Out of wood the people made canoes, plank houses, carved household items and wooden slat armor that may have been derived directly from Asia. (Ref. 1)

THE UNITED STATES

In the United States area, the Burial Mound I period of the Woodland tradition was typified by the Adena Culture of Ohio, Indiana, Kentucky, Pennsylvania and West Virginia. Similar areas could be found, however, from Canada through Minnesota and down to the Louisiana-Texas border. The characteristic traits were woodland pottery, burial mounds, some as high as 66 feet, and the beginnings of agriculture. Indians lived in small, scattered villages with round houses, using wattle for walls and thatch for roofs. (Ref. 2, 3) In southeast United States an Archaic type of culture extended throughout the period under review. Studies of remains have been made in the St. John River of Florida and the Savannah River culture of the river valley by the same name. The major weapon was a short heavy spear propelled by a throwing stick while bone fish-hooks, stone net weights and stone axes have been found. Fiber tempered pottery had been in use in this area for a long time. (Ref. 4)

And now we must mention the recent and very controversial work of one Barry Fell. Professor Fell is a teacher of marine biology at Harvard University, but he also claims an extensive education in ancient Celtic languages at Edinburgh University and thus professes to be one of the few who can read ancient scripts in Celtic and other ancient tongues, including Egyptian, Phoenician and Libyan. It is his assertion that in various parts of the United States he has found stone inscriptions in those ancient tongues, seeming to prove that those people visited or even colonized parts of America in this early period. Of special note, in the time bracket of this chapter, is his claim of Phoenician inscriptions, written in the Celtic alphabet, at a site called Mystery Hill, New Hampshire, dated to 800 to 600 B.C. He feels that Goedelic Celts from Spain and Portugal explored and settled multiple areas in New England during the first millennium B.C. and that the Punic phase just mentioned undoubtedly followed an original Celtic occupation. In addition, he has allegedly translated the so-called Pontotoc stele of Oklahoma as an extract from the "Hymn to Aton", a chant of the pharaoh Akhnaton, dating from the 13th century B.C., although Fell says the Oklahoma version can scarcely be older than about 800 B.C., believing it was the work of an early Iberian colonist writing in the script from the Cachao-da-Rapa region of northern Portugal. Similarly he writes that the Davenport stele of Iowa has three separate scripts,- Egyptian hieroglyphics alongside Iberian and Libyan scripts. Previously these stelae had been considered as fakes. Fell's interesting hypotheses have not yet been generally accepted and seem to have been more or less ignored by the professional archeologists. (Ref. 5)

In the Cochise area of southwest United States a new and more vigorous strain of corn was imported from Mexico about 1,000 B.C. A new plant, the red kidney bean, also appeared as the Cochise began to build simple pit-houses and group themselves together in small villages. As agricultural activities made easier living, they had time to develop early pottery forms and soon figurines of people and animals. Findings in the refuse of the Ventana Cave, some 100 miles from Tucson, have revealed these gradual changes from hunter to farmer. (Ref. 6)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

In previous chapters we have mentioned the early cultures in both Oaxaca and Tehuacan which are adjacent areas in southern Mexico. At Tehuacan the Ajalpan cultural phase ran from 1,500 to 850 B.C. and excavations have revealed that about 40% of their diet came from agricultural products, 31% from wild plants and 29% from meat. Various settlements were scattered along the waterways, with caves for summer occupation to escape the heat. Population increased rapidly, as agriculture was improved. The next phase, beginning in 850 B.C., was the Santa Maria, which saw the rise of templed villages, a figurine cult, and some irrigation. (Ref. 7) The Zapotecs of Monte Alban (Oaxaca) developed true civilizations with populations in the tens of thousands, a hierarchy of social classes, a civil service, priesthoods and specialists in commerce, administration and government.

The Olmecs at the base of the Yucatan peninsula had similar progress and a distinctive culture dominated by a powerful religion with sky or rain deities in the form of jaguar people with drooping or snarling feline mouths and deformed heads. They originated the bar and dot calendar which traditionally has been credited to the later Mayas and they had fine jade carvings. As their population increased they continued to live in villages scattered throughout the forest, but at intervals they built impressive centers for ceremonial, civic and perhaps commercial use. Each center was the focal point for the life and culture of some 10,000 people.

Four types of exotic maize found in Guatemala were entirely confined to the western coast area and all are of South American origin, giving further suggestion of maritime contact between Ecuador-Peru and Guatemala. Coe (Ref. 8) has shown that boats, even without the special Peruvian guaras (a system of center-boards acting as adjustable keels) could sail along the South American - Middle American coasts, going one direction at certain times of the year and reversing direction at other seasons, similar to the monsoon wind system of the Indian Ocean. (Ref. 9, 10, 11, 12)1

1C. This was later to become a great tool production center because of adjacent deposits of chert nodules, as described in the Additional Notes of the 1st century C.E. (Ref. 13)

SOUTH AMERICA

About 800 B.C. one of the Peruvian states, the Chavin, underwent an expansion much like the Olmecs did in Central America. This civilization, with social classes, bureaucracies, and priests, soon spread throughout the northern half of Peru. Heyerdahl (Ref. 14) writes that this civilization appears to be a direct extension down the coast from the Olmec be- cause there were multiple closely related jungle civilizations in a narrow coastal line, apparently in contact one with the other by sea, while outside this narrow civilized strip there was nothing but barbarian jungle tribes of Amerindians throughout Venezuela, Guiana and all of Brazil. And yet there were many differences between the Chavin and the Olmec' Mesoamerica had writing, South America did not; Peru had metallurgy by 300 B.C., Mexico not until about A.D. 1000. Engel (Ref. 15) does not relate the South American culture to the Olmecs, but does agree that it apparently developed rapidly, perhaps in a single generation and occupied most of the area of present day Peru. Beneath the Chavin layer (archaeological speaking), occasionally complete "pre-ceramic" villages can be found. The Chavin traits included low-relief ornaments made on hammered gold leaf, cigars (but not from tobacco), carved and polished stone vessels and tools including notched axes and cylindrical maces - some of the stone pieces so perfect that they seem to be replicas of objects previously made in metal. The Chavins also used anthracite mirrors and constructed very large architectural units, some several hundred yards long. The decorative themes almost all derived from five basic subjects, as follows:

African style mouth with thick lips. (See Heyerdahl's ideas under Central America)
Snake-like bodies protruding from demoniacal or human figures.Some are reminiscent of a crocodile snout, considered sacred in Africa
Fangs, shaped like curved swords
Crenellations, staircases or geometric forms recalling models of buildings or fortresses
Vessels representing human or demonic heads, animals and plants

The center of the Chavin society was the village of Chavin de Huantar, probably a temple at 10,000 feet altitude consisting of a massive building 500 feet long in an inter- Andean valley on the west bank of the Mosna River. Engel thinks that Chavin art may well be the product of foreign immigration, but from where? Some have said South Asia, some China and Meggers (Ref. 16) says the Jomon Culture of Japan. Engel is impressed with the resemblance to Oaxaca and Vera Cruz. Las Haldas became another great Chavin complex, measuring 1,220 feet long by 260 feet wide and covering 7 1/2 acres, with a platform overhanging the sea at a height of 130 feet. Chavin influence reached as far south as the Mantaro basin in central Peru, as indicated by pottery found there. (Ref. 17)

Some would date the beginning of the Tiahuanaco Society to 800 B.C. (Ref. 18) but since this date remains very debatable and since the full development of this society was reached only later, we shall defer discussion of it until the 5th century B.C.

In the 2nd millennium and this part of the 1st millennium B.C. a drier climate reduced the Amazonian forests to scattered refuges and during this period migration of various tribes may have been relatively easy. The resulting spread may help to explain the multiplicity of languages spoken there since then. (Ref. 19)

1 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [258] SEARS, W.H., "Food Production & Village Life in Prehistoric Southeastern United States", Archaeology 24: 322-329, Oct. 1971.

5 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

6 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

7 [259] MAC NEISH, RICHARD STOCKTON, "Food Production & Village Life Developed in the Tehuacan Valley, Mexico", Archaeology 24: 307-315, Oct. 1971.

8 [36] COE, MICHAEL D. "Archeological Linkage with North & South America at La Victoria, Guatemala", American Anthropologist 62: 363-393, 1960.

9 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

10 [155] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

11 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

12 [36] COE, MICHAEL D. "Archeological Linkage with North & South America at La Victoria, Guatemala", American Anthropologist 62: 363-393, 1960.

13 [304] HESTER, THOMAS R.; SHAFER, HARRY J., ET AL, "Colhas's Stone Tool Industry", Archaeology 36, No.6: 46-52, Nov./Dec. 1983.

14 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

15 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

16 [141] MEGGERS, BETTY J., "The Transpacific Origin of Meso American Civilization: A Preliminary Review of the Evidence and its theoretical Implications", American Anthropologist 77: 1-271, 1975.

17 [255] ARCHEOLOGYOF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

18 [255] ARCHEOLOGY OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

19 [256] INDIANS OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

America: 700 to 601 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

The Arctic Small tradition continued in the far north as previously described.

Indian life throughout Canada was essentially as recorded in the last chapter.

THE UNITED STATES

Here again, as in the last chapter, we run into the controversial theories of Barry Fell (Ref. 1). Various rock inscriptions of New England, some originally found years ago1 and others just recently, as at Union, New Hampshire, and on Monhegan Island off the coast of Maine, have now been interpreted by Fell as being Tartessian Punic, recording arrivals of Phoenician ships from Spain. It is his hypothesis that these voyagers, dated from 700 to 600 B.C. were probably not explorers but merchants, trading with already settled New England Celts'

In the midwest, the Burial Mound I period of the Adena variation of the Woodland tradition continued. Here again Barry Fell introduces new controversy when he states that excavation of some of the mounds have revealed copper and bronze tablets, pottery, figurines, etc. showing unmistakable similarities to ancient Phoenician constructions. He says these are located in West Virginia, lowa and Ohio, along major rivers. Other students of the Adena Culture mention only stone ornaments and engraved slabs in these mounds, although the later Hopewell mounds (see 3rd century B.C.) certainly had various metals, but of local origin. In the southwest United States the San Pedro phase of the Cochise Culture continued as a desert society, with increasing population and improvements in farming and other skills. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

The Olmec civilization, now some 600 years old, reached the height of its development with a center at La Venta, Mexico. Every village was linked in an elaborate network of trade up and down the valleys and between the highlands and the coasts. Salt, maize, obsidian, oyster shells, stingray spines, sharks' teeth, conch and turtle shells were all traded widely. The Olmecs were not only great sculptors but also carvers of jade, from which they made statuettes, jewellery and axes. To judge from their art, the Olmecs had two contrasting ethnic types, one remarkably Negroid, with thick lips, broad noses and round faces and the other strikingly Semitic with sharp profiles, hooked noses, narrow faces and lips and pronounced beards, usually shown as either square or pointed goatees. Neither of these types would seem to have come across the Bering Strait. (Please also see pages 124 to 127 and the chart which follows the next section in this chapter). The Mayan calendar indicates activity in Central America by 613 B.C. but little actual knowledge of those people is available for another century or two. (Ref. 5)

SOUTH AMERICA

The Chavin civilization continued in northern Peru and perhaps the Tiahuanaco existed in the highlands on the Bolivian border, but we shall omit discussion of this group until the 5th century B.C. As in Central America, there are many equivocal findings suggesting the possibility of multiple origins of South American peoples, rather than a single ancestral strain from Bering Strait migrants. Some of the features which contribute to this confusion are now listed.

NOTE: Insert SPECIAL SECTION, UNEXPLAINED FEATURES OF NATIVE AMERICANS

1 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

2 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

1.  One such inscription was described and recorded from Mount Hope Bay, Bristol, Rhode Island, in 1,780 by Ezra Stiles, later president of Yale College

America: 600 to 501 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

There was no real change in the human condition in North America at this time. The Arctic Small Tool tradition is usually divided into two stages with what has been called the Dorset Stage emerging at about 600 B.C. This was an harpoon based hunting culture extending all across the far north.

THE UNITED STATES

The Adena Woodlland Culture thrived in the east and the middle west of the United States and the influence of the Adena burial customs, religion and art can be identified over a large area, including Chesapeake Bay and New York state. In the 1880s Professor Cyrus Thomas surveyed over 2,000 mound sites and collected over 4,000 specimens of this and the later Hopewell Culture. The San Pedro phase of the Cochise Culture continued in the southwest. (Ref. 1, 2)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

In the Olmec center at La Venta a clay pyramid 103 feet high was erected and surrounded by four colossal stone heads. At Monte Alban, Mexico, one can still see rows of carvings with Olmec features. At Tikal, Quatemala, pottery has been found dating to 600 B.C. similar to south American pottery of the same date, suggesting that trade existed between the two areas. About 500 B.C., however, the Olmec people seem to have collapsed and disappeared, perhaps passing on their knowledge to the Mayas who began to occupy some of the same territory. Archeological finds establish a human presence in Vera Cruz as early as 5,600 B.C. and this may have been from ancient times a thorough-fare for migration of Huastec and Olmecs along the coastal plain. (Ref. 3, 4, 5)

The zero point of the Mayan calendar corresponds to our 3,113 B.C. and brings up the interesting questions as to the ultimate origin of those peoples and how they were able to triumph over the jungle to establish a type of civilization. The most likely hypothesis is that they were agriculturalists originally and that they moved in from adjacent river-estuarine lowlands. The bulk of archaeological data points to an original incursion of the lowlands during the first half of this 1st millennium B.C., but the earliest ceramics from Tikal and UJaxactun date to about 600 B.C. There may have been two stages in the development of the Maya society, with the first stage characterized by the dissemination of riverine settlements from the tropical Lowlands of the Pacific and Gulf Coasts in the general area of the Isthmus of Tehuantepec and the second stage occurring when Pre-classic groups abandoned the rivers and moved into the interior. This later stage appears to be linked to the beginnings of Mayan civilization. The change to the interior habitat involved many problems not the least of which was the obtaining of drinking water. The solution to this problem was apparently found in the construction of artificial reservoirs in impermeable clays. Fed by artificially constructed drainage systems they allowed for the storage of millions of gallons of water. For carbohydrates, the relatively small crops of maize that could be raised with the slash and burn method, was supplemented by the ramon, a tree of the fig family which produces dense carbohydrate seeds in tremendously large quantities. Storage places for these seeds have also been found. Now shut off from river proteins, deer hunting was of importance, a fact confirmed from the examination of hidden contents from Tikal. As the Pulestons (Ref. 6) have pointed out, the necessity of organizing labor to construct the large public reservoirs may well have been a catalyst for the development of social stratification and the developing concept of a state; and the utilization of the ramon would have allowed stable settlements with the release of much male labor for use in various other channels.

SOUTH AMERICA

The Chavin civilization continued in Peru throughout this century but then about 500 B.C. their cities were rather suddenly abandoned1. Some writers say that Paracas developed its own individual type of pottery in the south at this time, but Engel (Ref. 7) does not date Paracas I until another 300 years. Marvin Allison (Ref. 8) has found multiple mummies from various Peruvian and Chilean coastal burials, some dating to 600 B.C., with tuberculosis, especially of the bones and joints and he believes this must have been a common disease of the western coast. The first known densely populated centers on the north coast of South America date from 600 B.C. to 150 B.C. and have been called the "Salinar phase" by archaeologists. (Ref. 9)

In the light of Barry Fells 's hypotheses concerning possible European and Middle East voyagers to the new world in ancient times, it is of interest that a stone inscription in Phoenician script was allegedly discovered in Parahyba Province, Brazil, in 1886 and a translation published in 1939 indicated that it had been written by Canaanites of Sidon who had left the Red Sea area in 536 B.C. (the 19th year of the reign of Hiram) with ten ships, sailing along the coast of Africa for two years, under the orders of Necho, pharoah of Egypt. The writers note that they became separated from their flagship and were carried far away and landed on this unknown (Brazilian) coast. When first put forth this finding and translation was declared a forgery, but more recently it has been accepted as genuine by many authorities. (Ref. 11) The south Atlantic ocean currents coming from the African Cape could easily result in this drift. Ornate ceramics decorated with animal and bird figures were characteristic of the Brazilian Barrancoid tradition of this and many adjacent centuries (Ref. 12)

1 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

2 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

3 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

4 [155] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

5 [236] WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

6 [261] PULESTON, DENNIS E. AND PULESTON, OLGA STAVRAKIS, "An Ecological Approach to the Origins of Maya Civilizations", Archaeology 24: 330-3371, Oct. 1971.

7 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

8 [3] ALLISON, MARVIN J., "Studies of Pre-Columbian American Diseases 1971-1976, National Geographic Research Reports. Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 1-11 (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

9 [255] ARCHEOLOGY OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

10 [255] ARCHEOLOGY OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

11 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

12 [255] ARCHEOLOGY OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

1.  The National Geographic Society (Ref. 10) reported in 1982 that this society lasted until 300 B.C.

America: 500 to 401 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

The far northern Eskimo Culture, the midwestern Woodland Adena Cultures and the southwestern Cochise traditions continued as before. In southern Utah's Barrier Canyon (now Horseshoe Canyon) on the Colorado River just before it goes into Arizona, rock paintings and figurines dating back at least to 500 B.C. have been found. They may date much earlier. Barry Fell (Ref. 1) has further astounding hypotheses dating to this century.

For example, he has identified a stone temple at South Woodstock, Vermont, to be of Celtic construction, dated after 433 B.C. and like others, oriented with its long axis at compass bearing 123 degrees, which is the horizon azimuth of the rising sun on the December 22 winter solstice, important in the Celtic religion. He says that many monoliths characteristic of any Celtic landscape are found in New England. And still more - Fell states that the Zuni tongue in Arizona is basically Libyan, taken from the limited, racy and colloquial vocabulary of Libyan navy men sailing in this century from ships of Tarshish or Carthage. He insists that the basic Zuni language of today is similar to Coptic, with borrowed elements from Spanish and English. One of the problems involved in accepting this is that most authorities do not think the Zuni existed as a definite people at this early time, and that they developed from the Mogollon Culture much later. (Ref. 2, 3)

MEXICO AND CENTRAL AMERICA

The middle America "ball-game", a curious, violent cross between soccer, volley-ball and pelota seemed to have some religious significance and appears to have been developed by the Olmecs, although it became popular all over middle America by 400 B.C.1 As noted in the previous chapter the Maya probably started their differentiation from other primitive peoples in the scrub-covered lowlands of northern Yucatan and Guatemala's Peten about 2,500 B.C.2, slowly struggling against the invading forest. Clearing land was difficult and was done chiefly by burning. Their staple food was maize, of ten with several varieties grown in the same field. Although their land was relatively infertile, except along the river flood plains, it was rich in building materials - limestone rock, sandstone and volcanic rock as well as hard stones. Up until 300 B.C. is known as the formative period of Mayan history, and there is no doubt but what much of their advanced culture was transferred from the preceding Olmec Society. (Ref. 4, 5)

Costa Rica, on the narrow isthmus leading to Panama and South America has a long prehistory, but available artifacts date chiefly from 500 B.C. onwards. In a new chronology for Central America proposed by a seminar in 1980, the time from 1,000 B.C. to A.D. 500 in the Costa Rican story would be Period IV. At about 500 B.C. the Guanacaste-Nicoya and some of the Central Highlands-Watershed region were influenced by Mesoamerican culture, with production of the same red-on-buff pottery and a tendency for all settlements to prefer level, fertile land suitable for agriculture. (Ref. 7)

SOUTH AMERICA

The complete disappearance of the Chavin society of Peru in this century was so sudden that a cataclysm is suggested. It may have resulted from a climatic crisis in that it is known that the sea level oscillated as much as 23 feet in this time period. Engel (Ref. 8) states that in the north central part of Peru there were two new societies after about 500 B.C., the Mochica and the Gallinazo, both in an area no more than about 240 miles long. South of there from the Huarmey Valley to the Lurin, south of Lima, with an area of almost 1,200 square miles there appears an archeological gap of about 1,000 years.

Still farther south the Paracas Society appeared at the end of the Chavin time or after a short gap and the very far south has not really been studied.

The exact time of origin of the Mochican society is disputed and even radio-carbon dates are somewhat confusing. Engel feels that it existed from this 5th century B.C. until at least A.D. 100 and was contemporary with the Gallinazos with whom the Mochicans fought. The chief phenonemon of Mochica is a classical pottery, handsome, of various shapes, decorated and some of it pink-fired. On some pottery the paintings show circumcised prisoners shackled together, but none of the Mochicas are shown nude. Since circumcision was essentially unknown in early South America, from whence did the prisoners come?

Ceramic portrait paintings of many classes of men are found, including warriors, farmers, priests, etc.. The warriors may have arrived later, representing a new, conquering group. Some of the Mochican sites contained metal objects but the sites had been looted long before any professional archeologists arrived. (Please also see South America in the 2nd century B.C. for Barry Fell's thoughts).

In nearby Viru Valley lived the Gallinazo, named after a vulture, with a great building society superimposed on an age old strata of previous peoples. One ziggurat, 82 feet high, obviously had religious significance. Most sites have been looted centuries ago, as they contained gold objects, and finally the valley seems to have been conquered anyway by the Mochicans.

On a treeless, barren plain 12,500 feet above sea level in central Peru, there existed perhaps at this time, the Tiahuanaco civilization3, similar in every way to the Olmec except in the drastic differences in climate and geology. The similarities of this society at Lake Titicaca and the Olmecs with the Old World cultures are many, including a domesticated, small dog, with no wild progenitor in America, the use of hybrid long staple cotton and many other botanical features. Building materials were treated differently than in any other part of the Andes, with monolithic blocks weighing a hundred tons cut with geometric precision. The blocks show mortised joints and recesses in which metal hinges could have been placed to swing monumental doors. Multiple temples were built and at least one building 500 feet in length was included.

1 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

2 [195] SMITH, GARY AND LONG, MICHAEL E., "Utah's Rock Art: Wilderness Louvre", National Geographic 157: 971, Jan. 1980.

3 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

4 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

5 [263] HAMMOND, NORMAN, "Unearthing the Oldest Known Maya", National Geographic 162: 126- 140, July 1982.

6 [263] HAMMOND, NORMAN, "Unearthing the Oldest Known Maya", National Geographic 162: 126- 140, July 1982.

7 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

8 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

9 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1.  See this same section in the 10th century C.E.

2.  Recent excavations indicate a Maya presence at Cuello, Belize at 2,400 B.C. (Ref. 6)

3.  It has been very difficult for archeologists to accurately date the Tiahuanaco Society for many reasons. Most of the great areas have been looted extensively over the centuries and at present all excavation is restricted by the Bolivian government. Engel (Ref. 9) has obtained a carbon-dating of the deepest strata of the city proper of about 2,000 years ago, but pottery fragments at that level already were decorated in high classical Tiahuanaco style, suggesting that this was late in the history of the people. We are empirically starting the discussion of Tiahuanaco in this century although it may have originated either earlier or later by several hundred years.

America: 400 to 301 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

The Dorset Arctic, the Adena variety of the Woodlands and the southwest Cochise traditions continued as described in the preceding two chapters.

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

In the Central American tropical forests of Guatemala and Honduras the Mayan Culture continued to develop with an increasing complexity indicated by the construction of mound platforms for temples and palaces. Recent excavations at Cuello, a ceremonial center of northern Belize which may have had its origins as far back as 2,400 B.C., have revealed evidence of what was probably a barbaric religious ritual of about 400 B.C. Twenty skeletons were found, some complete but others with detached skulls lying beside lopped-off limbs. These were lying in the center of a massive, raised platform some 200 feet square and standing 12 feet high. (Ref. 1) Another city on the Mayan trade route along the eastern coast of the Yucatan peninsula in modern Belize was Cerros. This community has been remarkable well preserved although it was abandoned many centuries ago. For three hundred years, beginning in about 350 B.C. it existed as a modest fishing and trading village. In the beginning the inhabitants lived on or close to the current ground level or on low clay platforms. In later centuries marked changes occurred in the manner of living and we shall refer to these in subsequent chapters. (Ref. 2) The mound platforms of the early Central American people initiated the building of pyramids which was a virtual obsession for the next 2,000 years. Mexico alone may have some 100,000 as not uncovered. (Ref. 3, 4)

SOUTH AMERICA

The people of northern Peru were melting gold and copper by 300 B.C. Since the melting point of these metals is a little more than 2,200 degrees Fahrenheit, one wonders how they reached such temperatures. The later chroniclers of the Spanish say the Indians blew on the fire and installed their hearths on hilltops where they had the help of the wind.

Fine Columbian metallurgy (using the lost wax method) was to later far surpass in quality that of either Peru or Mexico. (Ref. 5)

The highlight of the Paracas Culture in southern Peru was embroidery. "As in the earlier Chavin Culture, the stylized feline animal played an important part in the decoration of their pottery as well as their textiles.”1Hybrid birds, beasts, fish, snakes and men also moved up and down the fabrics in rows, as cotton and alpaca wool were fabricated into mantles and other fabrics, with as many as 190 different shades of colors. Many of their ceramic vessels were characteristic Chavin steep-mouthed jars. Mummies from major necropolises on the Paracas peninsula, carbon-14 dated to about 300 B.C., have been found near large quantities of hardwood guara, a type of centerboard used in the navigation of sail-carrying rafts, attesting to extensive maritime activity. The physical attributes of mummy bodies differed markedly from those of known South American Indians; the mummies being for one thing much taller and having different skull shapes.

All studies of Tiahuanaco skulls have also shown a mixture of skull shapes, with the cranial indices varying from 71.97 to 93.79 and hair color and shape varying also. Interesting features of the tremendous Tiahuanaco statues are the deep-set eyes and straight noses, quite different from the round Chavin eyes and the deer-shaped ones at Mochica. Most statues call to mind the ones on Easter Island in the south Pacific. (Ref. 6, 7) At one point Tiahuanaco reproduced an art theme typical of the old Chavin style with serpent-like animals protruding from the bodies of armed figures with animal heads, sometimes feline and sometimes that of an eagle. A hot-land item, the feathered shield, has also been found in the Jojo Province of the eastern shore of Lake Titicaca and the greatest number of Tiahuanaco stones has also been found in this area. Some archeologists have described three phases of pottery decoration in that society. (Ref. 8, 9, 10)

Regarding the eastern side of the South American continent, we might mention that Barry Fell (Ref. 11) writes that he has translated rock inscriptions written in the ancient Ogam Celtic alphabet in caves near the upper reaches of the Paraguay River, these dating probably between 500 and 500 B.C. The writing allegedly describes a visit by mariners from Cadiz, Spain and the language supposedly was a variant of Phoenician called "Iberian". Others have described a stone found on a Brazilian plantation with alleged Phoenician writing2.

1 [263] HAMMOND, NORMAN, "Unearthing the Oldest Known Maya", National Geographic 162: 126- 140, July 1982.

2 [264] FREIDEL, DAVID; ROBERTSON, ROBIN; AND CLIFF, MAYNARD B., "The Maya City of Cerros", Archaeology Vol. 355, No. 4: 12-211, July/Aug. 1982.

3 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

4 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

5 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

6 [3] ALLISON, MARVIN J., "Studies of Pre-Columbian American Diseases 1971-1976, National Geographic Research Reports. Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 1-11 (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

7 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

8 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

9 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

10 [10] BELCHER, TAYLOR AND EDIE, "Great Golden Art of the Ancient Peruvian Artisans", Smithsonian 8:841, Dec. 1977.

11 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

1.  Quotation from Taylor and Belcher, Ref. 10, page 85.

2.  This interpretation has been backed by Ladislau Netto, Director of the National Museum in Rio as well as by Cyrus Gordon of Brandeis University in Massachusetts, but is scoffed at by European scholars.

America: 300 to 201 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

In the far north the Dorset phase of the Arctic Small Tool tradition continued. This Dorset Society was to last overall, some sixteen centuries. (Ref. 1)

By this century, for reasons unknown, the Adena Culture had faded and almost disappeared, but a new North American Indian culture made its appearance in Illinois and soon spread to Ohio. Named the "Hopewell" after an Illinois mound group, this eventually spread widely over a huge portion of the eastern United States, stretching from the Mississippi River to Florida. Although the people probably cultivated corn and other crops, hunting and gathering were still of critical importance. They built elaborate earthworks, some for defensive purposes and some as burial mounds. They worked in copper, mica, obsidian, soap-stone and wood as well as clay. Copper and mica cutouts in various designs were seen in effigy pipes and occasional pottery. Rock carvings of satyr masks almost identical with some of Carthaginian occupied Sardinia and Carthaginian coins of the 4th and 3rd centuries B.C. have allegedly been found along the Arkansas River both above and below Wichita, Kansas, according to Barry Fell, and he feels positive that the Carthaginians traded on the Atlantic side of America for lumber, gold and furs. (Ref. 2, 3)

In the southwest, in southern New Mexico and eastern Arizona, Coshise Indians continued their agricultural, hunting and gathering society, but with still more improvement in the type of corn, squash and beans, so that a true farming community had materialized.

MEXICO AND CENTRAL AMERICA

As the Mayan Society began to flourish we must not fail to remember that the Olmecs left a heritage of religious beliefs, artistic symbolism and other cultural traditions to all subsequent Mexican people. Recent excavations near Coba, Mexico, on the Yucatan peninsula have been called the Late Pre-classic Maya period by Mexican archeologists, with a dating going back to 300 B.C. and with a peak at A.D. 200. The Mayas excelled in astronomy and developed a very complex system of chronology (perhaps originating with the Olmecs) which was remarkably exact in its calculation. For example, they calculated that 405 full moons occurred in a period of 11,900 days, while today astronomers make it 11,959,888 days, thus differing by 1 day every 292 years or less than five minutes a year! They recorded their language in a complex hieroglyphic script composed partly of ideograms representing whole words or ideas and partly of phonetic symbols for sounds, much as did ancient Egyptian and modern Japanese. Scholars are still working on decoding this language, which is still spoken by some two million people. (Ref. 4)

In Costa Rica this Middle to Late Period IV can be viewed as a time of contact with more developed Mesoamerican cultures. Superb human and zoomorphic ceramic effigies were produced at this time. In the Central Highlands-Atlantic Watershed, household remains also resemble Mesoamerican patterns; small, rectangular houses are sometimes accompanied by bell-shaped storage pits. The pottery was adorned with any number of tropical reptiles with the color chiefly red on buff. (Ref. 5) The archeological record of western Panama begins at about 300 B.C. and includes ceramics found in the Rio Chiriqui rockshelters. They were similar to those described in Costa Rica. We shall note in later chapters that this was an area where big chiefdoms developed. (Ref. 6)

SOUTH AMERICA

There were apparently any number of small, localized although prosperous societies in various parts of the Ecuador, Peru, Bolivia complex in this century. About this time a numerous tribe arrived in the Chilca Basin just south of present day Lima, building clusters of dwelling houses made of conical, hand molded clay blocks, a temple and store-house-fortress. Their temple resembled a Polynesian "marae", and large and impressive adobe pyramids were constructed. There were perhaps 2,500 people to a village, living on corn, sea-food and potatoes of cultivated species, the first in Peru. Seven Lapa Lapa1 systems with some 10,000 structures made of heavy stone have been mapped out. They had some traits in common with the Nazcas who lived farther south and were their contemporaries - such things as pipes with ten holes, triangular obsidian projectile points and certain types of dishes. (Ref. 7, 8)

The Paracas ceremonial center on the south coast of Peru faded at about 200 B.C. although there appears some confusion about dates in regard to the Paracas-Nazca time periods. Fell (Ref. 10) reports carbon dating of the Paracas in the middle south Peru area back about the 5th century B.C., while Engel (Ref. 11) makes it much later, although he agrees that what he calls "Paracas I" was gone before 200 B.C.2 This territory was originally part of the Chavin society area and some Chavin decorations were continued. There now appeared a recently identified Vicus Culture which existed at the bend of the Maranon River almost on the present Ecuador-Peru border. This appears to have begun about 220 B.C. and lasted for approximately five hundred years. From the artistic standpoint these people are identified by intricate sheet- gold figures. Nose and ear ornaments employing both gold and silver were developed there and carried on even into much later Inca days. (Ref. 12, 13)

The high culture Tiahuanaco made small micriolithic projectile points of obsidian, quartz or flint, and bolas used for catching camelids were typical of the area. Some Tiahuanacoid pottery of the era shows an eye on figures that became Nazcoid or almond shaped, suggesting a hybridization of these two cultures. The jewels of Tiahuanaco were very fine and when faces were carved the noses were aquiline rather than straight, as shown on the winged god of the famed Gateway of the Sun, and as found on the gods of Easter Island. (Ref. 15)

At Chiripa, on the shores of Lake Titicaca there are interesting excavated architectural styles dating to about 300 B.C., where the walls were built with unfired clay bricks painted red, green and white, resting on a pebble base. All walls were double with the space between apparently used for storage bins and some as stables for guinea pigs . The roofs must have been of straw. The attached graves showed malachite beads and hammered, thin sheets of gold. The pottery had a stylized decoration using Greek-like step patterns and other geometric forms.

1 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

4 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

5 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

6 [266] de SAPIR, OLGA LINARES AND RANERE, ANTHONY J., "Human Adaptation to the Tropical Forests of Western Panama", Archaeology 24: 346-355, Oct. 1971.

7 [255] ARCHEOLOGY OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

8 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

9 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

10 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

11 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

12 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

13 [124]  LOW, D.M. (Editor). Abridgement of The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire, by EDWARD GIBBON. (Harcourt, Brace & Co., New York 1960).

14 [255] ARCHEOLOGY OF SOUTH AMERICA, Cartographic Division, National Geographic Society, March 1982.

15 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1.  A term Engel (Ref. 9) uses for the Chilca Basin dwellers.

2.  In 1982 the National Geographic Society (Ref. 14) dated the Paracas Period as 550 to 200 B.C.

America: 200 to 101 B.C.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

There was no interruption of the Dorset Society previously described in the Arctic north. In southeastern Canada, particularly in the region of Nova Scotia, the Micmac Indians eventually had script writing. Although usually credited to work of later French priests, Fell (Ref. 1, 2) gives some evidence indicating an east Libyan origin from near the Egyptian border where Herodotus said that an Adrymachid tribe had adopted Egyptian manners. He dates the contact of Libyan sailors with the Micmacs to this century but only further investigation can really settle this one way or another.

We have recorded previously that some authorities feel that Asian migrations to North America via a Pacific northern route continued by boat down to about 2,000 B.C. If true, then over the vast expanse of some 20,000 to 30,000 years a great variety of people could have made this trek. We know for certain that the Aleuts and the Eskimos are separate from true Amerindians and that the Athabascans of central, north Canada were relatively late comers, different in culture and language from most other Indians. Now we shall describe still another group of people, occupying the far western shore and the off-shore islands of Canada, who appear to be different from all other early North American inhabitants in many ways and who developed in an isolated situation along the Canadian waterways, shut off from inland Canada by precipices and wild mountains. These are the Haida of the Queen Charlotte Islands and the Kwakiutl of northwestern Vancouver Island, both ranking among the tallest people in the world. They appear to be related to the Salish or Flathead Indians who later inhabited northern Montana, apparently coming down gradually from Bella Coola and British Columbia. These people are dolichocephalic while most American Indians are brachycephalic; their complexions are fair and their hair of ten soft and brown, rather than Mongolian coarse and black. The earliest European visitors to the western Canadian islands - Cook, Dixon and Vancouver - all emphasized those features. In addition those northwest coast people of ten had strong mustaches and beards, in contrast to the usually totally beardless Amerindians. Thus they have many Caucasian features and are physically identical to true Polynesians. Their homesites in the Canadian islands probably represent way-stations on the trip these people made from some place in Asia in ancient times to the eventual destination of some of them, in Polynesia. If they are related to Malaysians it is a very distant relationship and the two physically dissimilar peoples must have separated from an original stem in very ancient days, before the Malayasians even migrated down into the peninsula now bearing their name. The theme of the unity of the northwest American Indians and the Polynesians will be further developed in subsequent chapters.

THE UNITED STATES

The expanding Hopewell sphere extended from the Alleghenies to the western border of the Mississippi alley, north to the Great Lakes, south to Florida and the Gulf States. Their craftsmen obtained obsidian for knives and arrowheads from the Yellowstone area of Wyoming as well as other rocks from Montana and North Dakota. We have not emphasized it previously but the Woodland Culture with its burial mounds, pipes, stone and copper gorgets, wooden carvings, pottery effigies and earrings existed in the south as early as 1,000 B.C. onto this 2nd century B.C. and beyond. Burial mounds up to forty feet in height are scattered throughout the south. (Ref. 3)

We do not like to belabor a controversial point but is perhaps worth mentioning that Fell (Ref. 4) insists that Celt-Iberians were scattered throughout the eastern United States by this period and that coins found in quantity in Ohio were local copies of ancient bronze coins of Evia, an old Portuguese city. This entire question of European and/or North African visitors in America at a much earlier time than heretofore ever mentioned in classical histories is an interesting one. Although Fell and Thor Heyerdahl1, both of whom have written extensively on this subject independently, have not obtained any significant agreement from others in the field, this does not necessarily mean that they are in error. We must remember that in the latter part of the 19th century the initial reports on the extensive and now famous prehistoric cave paintings and engravings from parts of Spain and Les Eyzies region of France were met with complete skepticism by the International Congress of Prehistoric Archeology and Anthropology. (Ref. 5, 6, 7)

In the southwestern United States where the corners of Arizona, New Mexico, Utah and Colorado join, the so-called Basket-maker I period of the Anasazi Indian Culture was in progress but few details are available from this century. Farther south the San Pedro Culture, apparently a modification of the Cochise, continued to be viable. (Ref. 8)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

In Mexico the Teotihuacan city-state continued to grow. The late Pre-Classic period of Central America continued with progressive population growth. The Maya in the Peten area subsisted on corn, beans and squash, as they cleared land by a slash and burn system. There were no large ceremonial centers as yet.

SOUTH AMERICA

The Vicus Culture flourished in northern Peru. At Lake Titicaca, on the border of present day Peru and Bolivia, on a bleak 13,000 feet plateau in the middle of the previously described Tiahuanaco Culture area there now was built abut 200 B.C. the definitive city of Tiahuanaco. Its remaining stones give evidence of a colossal style of building, with formidable mathematically ordered walls and imposing massive stone steps. A giant stone idol, 24 feet high, was excavated in 1932 by an American archeological team under W.C. Bennett. Another idol, only 8 feet tall but of a completely different style, although also of red sandstone, was found beside it. Shrunken human heads have been found, suggesting the bloody cult of head-hunting and/or human sacrifices. A Bolivian scholar, Ponce Sangines, believes this culture lasted from 200 B.C. to A.D. 1,200 with perhaps five buried cities, one often overlapping another in the archeological strata. Lake Titicaca is the highest navigable lake in the world and its largest island, the Island of the Sun, has hills with ancient crop-growing terraces and beneath its waters are high walls and paved paths. The lake, covering 3,200 square miles now is thought to have once reached the walls of the ancient city of Tiahuanaco, the runs of which now lie 25 miles away in Bolivia. The city may have been basically a religious or meeting center, as the large public buildings could hold thousands of people. There seems to have also been suburbs were craftsmen, weavers, smiths and farmers lived in mud-brick houses. Potatoes and corn were grown as they are even today. The stones which made up the large public buildings and walls appear to have been brought from quarries between 60 and 200 miles away and the method of transport brings up the same questions and possible answers that have been issued about the great stones of Stonehenge, the European megaliths and the statues of Easter Island. Some American prehistorians have suggested that the Tiahuanaco people simply fused together all the upper Andes societies that had been fragmented since the end of the Chavin Culture.

Heyerdahl (Ref. 9) quotes many of the very earliest Spanish chroniclers as they have recorded the natives' legends of the great pre-Inca past. In these there is the recurring theme suggesting immigrants from across the ocean. Lake Titicaca is given as a possible beginning point for Inga Viracocha or the composite Con-Tici-Viracocha, a bearded deity who "brought his people fro the sea." Legends among the Chimu have this same deity arriving by sea long the coast much farther north. One of the statues unearthed by W.C. Bennett in 1932 was that of Con-Tica-Viracocha in Tiahuanaco, complete with beard and long girdled robe, decorated with an horned serpent and two pumas, symbols of the Supreme God in both Mexico and Peru.

At about this same time of 200 B.C.2 and running to about A.D. 900 there appeared in the north of Peru the mysterious Mochica Culture complete with pottery and clay figurines and musical instruments and clothing resembling that of classical times in the Mediterranean. The Moche have sometimes been called "the Greeks of South America." Fell believes that they derived from a Libyan colony which was originally in the southwest Unites States because of similarity of some dragon-ship art work and other features found in ancient Nevada and California desert sites. He believes extensions of Maui's voyages (Please see The Pacific: 300 to 201 B.C.) included the southwestern Unites States and that visitors from there to northern Peru account for the civilization of the Moche.

Meanwhile on the middle south coast the society which Engel (Ref. 11) calls Paracas II developed as a coastal society with limited architecture, some use of copper and gold and a very advanced state of weaving. All skulls were deformed to a pear-shape and many were trepanned. Some elements suggest that they came up the coast from Chile and their many identified weapons indicate terrific battles. The Nazcas were direct successors of the Paracas and they too remained a coastal tribe, although with a far different social system. The transition was apparently somewhat gradual and although the Nazca Society may have taken shape in this century, it did not blossom until long after. (Ref. 12, 13, 14, 15)

1 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

2 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

3 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

4 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

5 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

6 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

7 [130] MARSHACK, ALEXANDER, The Roots of Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1972).

8 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

9 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

10 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

11 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

12 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

13 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

14 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

15 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1.  Heyerdahl's theories apply only to Central and South America, not the United States.

2.  Engel (Ref. 10) dates this earlier, between 500 and 400 B.C.

America: 100 B.C. to 0

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

All across northern Canada as far north as Ellesmere Island and northern Greenland and down to the northern shores of Hudson Bay and the east side of the Ungava Peninsula, the Dorset people continued to thrive. They carved figures of animals from walrus's tusks and bone, decorating them with peculiar outer marks which Schledermann (Ref. 189) has called an outline of animals' skeletons. In the pictures he shows, however, it hard to identify true skeletal structures and the marks are more reminiscent to this writer of the lunar notations of ancient Europeans described previously by Marchack. (Ref. 139) The northwest American Indians of the Canadian waterways continued in active existence at this time.

THE UNITED STATES

According to Barry Fell's original hypothesis North American trade from southern Europe ceased after the conquest of Brittany (55 B.C.) and the Battle of Actium (31 B.C.) because the Romans had no navy and needed none and the memory of America was lost1. In his latest book of 1980, however, Fell (Ref. 66) revises this markedly, having allegedly recently been deluged with finding of European (Roman) coins and rock inscriptions in a great variety of places in North America. Rock engravings which he believes to be copies of multiple coins minted locally in Spain about 20 B.C. in imitation of Roman coins of the same era and bearing portraits of Caesar Augustus, have been found at Castle Gardens, Wyoming. Fell is convinced that this Wyoming site was actually an early bank and center of trade with customers using Celtiberian Gaedelic as their main language. He hypothesizes that people of Wyoming traded with Celtiberians and their Indian wives, after the latter had migrated across the continent from New England to British Columbia and then to northwest United States. West Arkansas and Oklahoma have also yielded coins which seem to fit into this same category. Lacking further confirmation, the reader may make his own interpretation.

In the central and eastern United States there was continued Hopewell expansion with a distinctive ritual and artistic tradition, probably indicating a loosely knit group of societies with common religious and artistic conventions. The Gulf states, too, were heavily inhabited probably as far back as this era. In southern Colorado the Anasazi people entered into what we have already labeled the Basket-maker period. Excavations at Durango show both cave and open village sites, with evidence of maize growing as well as hunting activities. Baskets were made of plant fibers loosely plaited, coiled or stitched and decorated in red and black. (Ref. 215, 45, 210)

The Mogollon Culture in southern New Mexico and eastern Arizona apparently developed from the Cochise Culture and was manifested by a sedentary life style utilizing a plain pottery and existing on maize along with the fruits of some gathering and hunting. The name "Mogollon" is one lately applied2, and first given to a range of mountains running almost east-west across central Arizona and New Mexico, marking the southern edge of the northern high plateau country. South of this Mogollon ridge the terrain drops several thousand feet into the southern basin with meager rainfall and hot desert valleys with desert grasses, mesquite and cactus. In the middle of that basin there are north-south running mountain ranges going from New Mexico well down into Old Mexico. About 100 B.C. the Mogollon Indians have been identified as inhabiting this region. They continued to live in that large area for 1,500 years, constantly improving their crops and tools.

At about the same time another group of Indians, who may have been still another branch of the ancient Cochise, settled in the hot arid valleys of the lower Gila and Salt rivers. They have become known as the Hohokam3, surviving through their descendants, the Pima and the Papago. The Hohokam lived in Arizona for 1,200 years, building at Snaketown more than 5,000 houses at a rate of 400 a year. (Ref. 45, 210)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN

The Olmec civilization seems to have faded out at this time and no clear cut explanation has ever been given. But in the Valley of Mexico the brilliant city-state of Teotihuacán began to blossom. Originally a settlement of moderate size surrounded by a number of similar settlements this was soon a full fledged city and not just a ceremonial center like many of those of the Olmecs. There were large scale irrigation works, cultivated tomatoes and peanuts as well as maize and other grains and the domesticated turkey. There is evidence of a far flung trade with other areas of Central America and perhaps the North American settlements. Farther south in Guatemala the Mayan people continued to expand, beginning what has been called the Classical Age and the peoples of Costa Rica and Panama lived about as described in previous chapters. (Ref. 215, 64)

Recent excavations at the ancient town of Cerros in modern Belize indicate that about 50 B.C. the Maya inhabitants undertook a massive urban renewal. This involved the construction of a massive urban complex with large open plazas, great pyramids and 103 public buildings and dwellings arranged in a careful plan with the entire center surrounded by a canal 1,200 meters in length. Apparently all this was undertaken because of the excellent trading position of Cerros on a Yucatan bay at the mouth of the New River. The largest pyramid had some 30,000 cubic meters of rubble fill, twice the size of a famous North Acropolis at Tikal and represents a considerable engineering feat. (Ref. 164)

SOUTH AMERICA

Multiple cultures continued in the area of Greater Peru. On the northern coast there continued to be the Vicus Society. Their pottery, featuring resistive (i.e. negative) painting, resembled the Gallinazo. In the middle south coast the polychrome pottery and embroidery fabrics of the Nazca developed about this time but actual dating is difficult because of the extensive looting of ancient dwelling sites that has taken place in the past. The Tiahuanaco Society continued to thrive in the high Andes in the Lake Titacaco district. Contact between these highlanders and the Nazca and Huari peoples of the lower lands undoubtedly occurred with exchange of pottery dyes and other materials. The two areas are only 120 difficult miles apart. (Ref. 45, 62)

1.  From America B.C. by Barry Fell (Ref. 65).

2.  The name was taken from an 18th century Spanish official.

3.  In the modern Pima language this means "those that have gone before".

America: 0 to 100 A.D.

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

In the very far north the Dorset Arctic tradition continued to thrive. (See particularly the 6th and 1st centuries, B.C.). Some further remarks about the Indians on the western coast and islands of Canada seem in order. Their houses were large and rectangular with walls and roofs made of hand split boards. The roofs were gabled and there were no windows. The short front walls had small doors, usually highly decorated, sometimes with carvings, sometimes with paint. There were plaited amts on the dirt floors and no furniture. Houses could be as long as 70 feet. Social classes included a ruling aristocracy, commoners and slaves. Being basically a sea people they built sea-going canoes, some 170 feet long, 61/2 feet wide and 41/2 feet deep, which could accommodate 100 people. They navigated the open seas easily and as we shall note in a later chapter, some of their voyages undoubtedly went to the Hawaiian Islands were the people became Polynesians. The currents and winds alone sometimes carry large logs from northern Vancouver Island directly to Hawaii. The canoes were made of one-half of a large tree trunk and carried only a mat which could be used as a poor sail. For sea voyages two canoes could be tied together and a platform put over both. One man steered with a paddle in the stern and kneeling pairs of men paddled strongly. Three types of fish-hooks were used, none of which have ever been seen in Indonesia or Southeast Asia. These northwest Indians did not have pottery.

THE UNITED STATES

This was the beginning of the maximum expansion of the Hopewell Culture with secondary areas of influence in the so-called Marksville group near the Missisippi delta and the Santa Rosa groups at the base of the Florida peninsula. Their rather elaborate decorations (usually for the dead) included copper from Lake Superior, mica from the Appalachians, obsidian from the Rocky Mountains, alligator teeth and conch shells from Florida and the Gulf and stone from Minnesota and Wisconsin. At the risk of over-emphasizing the rather bizarre hypotheses of Barry Fell, we shall mention that he writes that the builders of the Hopewell mounds were mainly Libyans, assisted by Negroid Nubian crew members who left sculptures of heads and African animals along the Mississippi River system in Ohio, Iowa, Oklahoma and Arkansas. He even suggest that Jewish refugees from the first Romano-Jewish war ended up in Kentucky and Tennessee.1

In his most recent book Fell (Ref. 2) gives a translation from Plutarch which allegedly tells of how Greek North Africans (Late Carthaginians) sailed westward from Britain passing three island groups equidistant from one another (Orkneys, Shetlands and Faeros?), and then to Ogygia (Iceland?) five sailing days away and then on to the northern coast of a continent, Epeiros, that rims the ocean. South Greenland would fit the alleged distance and direction. Then, says Plutarch,2 if one sails south along the coast one will pass a frozen sea and come to a land where the Greeks settled and married with the native barbarians. (The Davis Strait between Labrador and Greenland becomes an impassable mass of floating ice during the summer season.) As for the place where the Greeks married, Plutarch says it was in the same latitude as the Caspian Sea, thus Nova Scotia and New England. It is in connection with this that Fell quotes Dr. Silas Rand3 who spent a lifetime in the last century among the Micmac and who wrote a Dictionary of the Micmac Language, as indicating a prevalence of Greek roots in their language. An illustrative list of over 50 such Greek roots are given by Fell along with the Micmac equivalents, implying a derivation from the Greek spoken in North Africa in Ptolemaic times, words that were a part of the everyday language of Libya and Egypt. This concept has been reported false by the Smithsonian institute.

Sometime during the Woodland Period maize had made its way from South America and/or Mexico to the southern United States and had spread from there even into New England and the Mid-Atlantic states. Varieties of lint corn or popcorn appeared in the South. (Ref. 3).

In southern New Mexico and Chihuahua, Mexico the Mogollon people continued to live in their semi-subterranean pit-houses and appeared to have self governing villages under the leadership of civil and religious elders democratically selected. An important feature was a large ceremonial house known as the great kiva, three or four times the size of the usual dwellings. In southern Arizona and the neighboring Mexican state of Sonora the Hohokam people began extensive irrigation systems with dams on rivers and some canals 30 feet wide and 25 miles long. This society developed for over 1,000 years, but the exact date of its origin has long been debated, estimates varying from 300 B.C. to A.D. 500. (Please see the 5th century C.E.). At any rate, they made exquisite jewelry and pottery pyramids and used astronomy. This is another American culture which Barry Fell (Ref. 4) believes to be of Libyan origin carrying the tradition and navigational and astronomical knowledge of the Old World and which had arrived via Pacific travelers as manifested by the original maps made by the famous Maui. (See The Pacific: 300 to 201 B.C.). The frontispiece on Fell’s latest book (Ref. 5) is a map supposedly drawn by Maui showing North America and the eastern Pacific, using the primary meridian as a line through Alexandria, Egypt (as used by Eratosthenes) with an international date line at 180 degrees, passing about 10 degrees east of Hawaii. It shows Hudson Bay and the isthmus of Panama and survives on rock drawings in Nevada. Fell says that additions to the original Libyan lettering have been made later in Kufic Arabic, showing that the map was still in use, probably for educational purposes as late as A.D. 750. It is his contention that petroglyphs and writings from Nevada and California, carefully recorded and filed at the University of California and other places, could not be previously interpreted because the nature of the writing (Arabic) was not recognized. The difficulty in all this is that current authorities including southwest museum directors and southwest anthropology professors in recent publications make no mention of these concepts whatsoever. (Ref. 6, 7, 8).

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN

People in the far north of Mexico participated in the Southwest American societies are related in the paragraphs immediately above. Much farther south there was rapid growth in the Teotihuacan area and continued evidence of human sacrifice, common to all MesoAmerican societies. Skeletons wrapped in nets, ritually burned children’s remains and buried heads all testify to this. (Ref. 9).

The Mayan civilization continued in Guatemala, Honduras and El Salvador. The Mayas counted in 20s and had a much more manipulative representation than the clumsy Roman numerals of the same time. The Maya zero, represented by a shell-shaped sign ____, was a concept which did not reach Europe from India for almost another 1,000 years. The numbers 1,2,3 and 4 were represented simply by the corresponding number of dots, while 5 was a single bar. Thus 5 was ______, 7 was ____-, etc., while 10 was two bars. Eighteen in this system was ______ and 20, of course, was four bars, one under the other. For numbers higher than 20 a new row was started above the first, to mark the number of 20s in total. Thus the number 234 would be expressed by only two Mayan symbols 0 on top sign for 11 (meaning 11 sets of 20 or 220) and underneath the sign for 14, thus: _________

In the last chapter we noted the May trading center of Cerros near the base of Yucatan. In this first century of the Christian era this city went into a steep decline. It is probable that with increasingly strong and well-managed overland trading routes the riversea networks decreased in importance. (Ref. 10).1

1C. to A.D. 250), the city of Colha, Belize, was a center for craft specialists who mass produced such stone tools as adzes, axes, daggers and hoes, as well as special ceremonial items. These were apparently exported all over the Maya region. To date some 32 work-shops have been excavated. (Ref. 11).

Pre-civilization societies continued to build up in Costa Rica and Panama. Dozens of settlements each almost half a kilometer in length in Cerro Punta. Panama, suggest considerable population build-up in the valleys south of the Continental Divide in this era. The ceramics of this stage are similar in both Panama and Costa Rica. (Ref. 12, 13)

SOUTH AMERICA

The early Intermediat Period of Peruvian history continued with a developed Vicus Culture dominating the north. There is some evidence that the trephining of skulls, using knives of hard obsidian, was a common practice in Peru at this time, for whatever reason. On the aird plain between southern Peru and the Andean foothills the Nazca Indians lived, making featherd turbans and fine cotton cloaks embroidered in multi-colored wools. Many of these have been recovered in Nazca cemeteries. Engel (Ref. 14) says that at this period there was no evidence of maritime activity among these people and fishermen were still depicted on ceramics swimming in the water catching fish in nets. Recent examination of skeletons of this era show a number of ear-canal osteomas, probably secondary to this work in the water. Gradually there was a rejuvenation of the so-called classical Nazca art, after an initial period of decline. The Tiahuanaco society continued in the high Andes. (Ref. 15, 16, 17)

1 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

2 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

3 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

4 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

5 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

6 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

7 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

8 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

9 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

10 [264] FREIDEL, DAVID; ROBERTSON, ROBIN; AND CLIFF, MAYNARD B., "The Maya City of Cerros", Archaeology Vol. 355, No. 4: 12-211, July/Aug. 1982.

11 [304] HESTER, THOMAS R.; SHAFER, HARRY J., ET AL, "Colhas's Stone Tool Industry", Archaeology 36, No.6: 46-52, Nov./Dec. 1983.

12 [266] de SAPIR, OLGA LINARES AND RANERE, ANTHONY J., "Human Adaptation to the Tropical Forests of Western Panama", Archaeology 24: 346-355, Oct. 1971.

13 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

14 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

15 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

16 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

17 [3] ALLISON, MARVIN J., "Studies of Pre-Columbian American Diseases 1971-1976, National Geographic Research Reports. Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 1-11 (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

1.  Such concepts are really not new. Early American colonists, particularly one James Adair, persistently held that one of the lost tribes of Israel had come to America and mixed with the southern Indians. Others thought that the Welsh Prince Madoc or even Phoenicians had early come to America. (Ref. 1)

2.  The exact sources of the Plutarch material are not given by Fell. He says simply that Plutarch, writing in the 2nd century, allegedly got his material from old records in Carthage.

3.  Similarly, we have no source reference concerning Dr. Rand.

America: A.D. 101 to 200

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

In the far north there was very little change from the previous centuries. (See particularly 6th and 1st centuries B.C.). About the central and eastern United States there is some disagreement. Brian Fagan, the Distinguished Professor of Anthropology at the University of California at Santa Barbara, writes that there was continued Hopewell expansion with increased cultural development even up until the 5th century C.E. (Ref. 1), but the Encyclopedia of Archeology (Ref. 2) states that there was a rapid decline of the Hopewell at about A.D. 200. We know that the southeastern United States was inhabited but we have available only very limited information at this early period. Fell (Ref. 3) describes finding of what he believes to be Hebrew shekels dating from the Second Revolt of A.D. 132 in various parts of Kentucky and a nearby district of Arkansas.

The Mogollon, Hohokam and Anasazi cultures continued to develop in the southwestern United States. (Please see adjacent modules). The Mogollon people learned to grind and polish small stone slabs to make useful articles such as paint palettes, dishes and stone smoking pipes for tobacco. Their spear points were used with a rude throwing stick called the atlatl, an ancient weapon of the Americas. (Ref. 4)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

The Teotihuacan people of Mexico increased their city size to an eight square mile area, in the center of which rose the truncated pyramid of the sun - 210 feet high and 750 feet square. It was as large at the base as the great pyramid of Cheops in Egypt. At the height of its prosperity, which was sometime in these early Christian centuries, Teotihuacán had a population of 120,000 with an added network of villages surrounding the main city. Over 5,000 buildings have been examined in this area, including 400 work- shops for making obsidian tools and weapons and some 300 potteries. Irrigation channels were dug for both city and farm water. This center was 30 miles northeast of present day Mexico City.

At Izapa on the Mexico-Guatemala border, there was a distinctive art style resembling the earlier Olmec Culture and it may represent a connecting link between that and the later classic Maya Culture which developed to the east. In approximately this same timeframe, El Tajin, located in the Veracruz area a few miles inland from Santa Louisa, emerged as a major Huastec administrative and religious center. The Huastecs were "cousins" of the Maya and El Tajin, as their major city, soon counted a population in the thousands, with hundreds of buildings, temples, palaces, ball-courts and countless individual dwellings.

On the classical dating scale the Mayan civilization was nearing its peak with many great scale cities in the forests, particularly in Peten and the region of the ceremonial center of Tikal. For the most part they were a peace-loving people who farmed, wove cotton and made paper from the fibers of the fig-tree1. They developed a system of writing which was partly phonetic and believed now to have been inherited in great part from the Olmecs. On the new dating systems this peak period of the Mayas may have been about 250 years later. (Please see America: 300 to 201 B.C.) (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9)

It is interesting that the prominent British historian, Hugh Thomas (Ref. 10), denies that the Maya had significant writing, apparently basing his comments on a single given reference in a 1978 Scientific American article. But his reference, in the "Science and the Citizen" department of the May, 1978 Scientific American (Ref. 11) gives me an entirely different concept. Although admitting that much Maya writing had been destroyed by the invading Spanish conquistadors in the mid-16th century, the article lists several sources of remaining Mayan hieroglyphics. There are manuscripts painted on deerskin which are apparently in museums scattered across the world, as they are known as the Dresden, Madrid and Paris codexes; then there are 64 hieroglyphs that were written down in 1566 for the Bishop of Merida by a surviving Maya scribe; and finally there is a long inscription found inside three structures at Palenque (dated 7th to 9th centuries C.E.), consisting of some 600 glyphs, the translation of which is still proceeding under anthropologists and epigraphers from Yale University. The part that has been translated describes twelve successive rulers of the past and details of a current 13th ruler with birth, pedigree, accession, military achievements, ritual acts, etc. of all. More inscriptions turn up every year, on pottery, monument stones, buildings, etc. The written language involved at least 600 individual glyphs which could stand alone or be used in combinations of two or more.

This was a major developmental period in Costa Rican history with a dramatic increase in sites and population along with a trend toward social stratification. Many new artifacts appeared including elaborately sculpted metates of volcanic stone, ceremonial stone mace-heads, carved jade, figurines, ocarinas, whistles, stamps and rattles. Panama developed similarly and there were undoubtedly long distance Mesoamerican trade networks. (Ref. 12)

SOUTH AMERICA

Sometime in this or the next century Paracas in the middle of south Peru was abandoned, perhaps because of a severe tidal wave or other natural disaster. Some Nazca villages, however, survived for several additional centuries and the Tiahuanaco Culture of the high Andes remained untouched. The potato was used as decoration on Peruvian pottery as early as the end of this century. (Ref. 13)

1 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

4 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

5 [146] MILTON, RENE, "Teotihuacán", Scientific American, June 1967, page 38.

6 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

7 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

8 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

9 [236] WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

10 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

11 [193] SCIENTIFIC AMERICAN, "Science and the Citizen" section, 238: 92-96, May 1978.

12 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

13 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

1.  In contrast there was no paper in Europe at this time. China invented a paper but kept it secret for centuries. See The Far East: A.D. 101 to 200.

America: A.D. 201 to 300

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

For information concerning the Dorset Inuits of the far north, please see the 6th and 1st centuries B.C. and the 9th century C.E. For the northwest coastal Indians see the previous two or three centuries under this same category. Barry Fell (Ref. 1) insists that throughout the last pre-Christian and these early Christian centuries the New England Celts, which he has described, gradually migrated with their Indian wives and children across Canada westward eventually reaching British Columbia. He reports that much of the vocabulary and grammar of the Takhelne language of the Fraser Lakes area spoken yet today, is a Creole Celtic tongue related to Gaelic and derived from Godelic. In America (Ref. 2) he lists 54 words still used today by the Takhelne people along with the Godelic and Gaelic words and their much different English equivalents1. The table is quite convincing, but why is this not even commented on elsewhere in the literature?

THE UNITED STATES

Sometime in these early Christian centuries the "Effigy Mound" Culture developed in the upper Mississippi Valley as a regional variation of the Hopewell Culture. There the Indians built gigantic mounds in the form of animals - panthers, lizards, deer, bears and birds. Most of the mounds had burials, often at critical parts of the figure such as at the heart, hip or knee. Although probably of religious significance, no one really knows what these Minnesota and Wisconsin mounds actually mean. (Ref. 3) The southeast Indians will be discussed at much length in later chapters.

In the southwest the Mogollon, Hohokam and Anasazi peoples continued their development. A more detailed look at their cultures will be given in later centuries, corresponding to the time of the heights of their development.

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

We have mentioned previously (3rd century B.C.) that recent excavations near Coba on the Yucatan peninsula have revealed much of the Late Pre-Classic Maya period. The peak of this civilization appears to have been reached in this 3rd century C.E. and the finding have included the Nohosmul pyramid, rising 157 feet out of the jungle, 5.4 square miles of temple buildings, streets and plazas, 187 miles of roads and streets, some 80 feet wide with traffic circles and underpasses2. This development apparently followed the Guatemala Maya Society, although it is known that by A.D. 250 there was a true urban Mayan zone persisting at Kaminaljuyu at the site of present day Guatemala City. This was the beginning of the greatest era of Maya civilization, with one of the earliest large, ceremonial centers at Tikal, dating to A.D. 292, in what is called the early Classic period. There was a strong central Mexican (Teotihuacán) presence, as that city was continuing development with obsidian mining as a major enterprise. (Ref. 4, 5)

The Mayas, even for generations after their peak, spoke of two distinct culture heroes, Itzamna and Kukulcan, both bearded, although arriving at different times and from opposite directions, leading the Mayas to Yucatan. Their legends said that the largest and most ancient immigration was from the east through the ocean and led by Itzamna, guide, instructor and civilizer. Kukulcan, a later arrival, was different - arriving with 20 men wearing flowing robes and sandals, with long beards and bare heads, ordering the people to confess and fast3. He allegedly founded Mayapan and caused much building at Chichen Itza, and taught "peace". His humanitarian teachings coincide completely with those of Quetzalcoatl, of the later Aztecs. " Kukul" is the Maya word for quetzal bird and "can" is a serpent .

A colored painting from an interior chamber of a pyramid at Chichen Itza, copied by Morris, Charlot and Morris in 1931 (and now destroyed by humidity and tourists) showed a seashore battle involving two racial types, one with white skin and long, flowing yellow hair arriving in boats, and the other type dark-skinned and wearing feathered headdresses and loin cloths. A reed vessel on the pyramid painting recalls the reed boats used at Luxus in Morocco and the old Egyptian paintings of reed boats of the Nile. Where did these blond men come from? We do know from written accounts of the discovery of the Canary Islands by Europeans a few generations before Columbus, that those islands were inhabited by a mixed population called "guanches" - some small, swarthy and negroid, others tall, white-skinned, blond and bearded, all just like the Maya pyramid at Yucatan. The Berbers of North Africa were similarly mixed and remain so today. Blond and red-haired people are known to have been in the Caucasian plains east of Asia Minor and nowhere on the continent is red hair more common than in Lebanon. (Ref. 7) So, do we take our pick? As further confirmation of the presence of bearded men in this Central American area, we have Stephens (Ref. 8) account of his exploration of Copan, Honduras, in the 1830s. He describes finding multiple idols with the males all identified by beards and some with mustaches. The beards were like those on Egyptian statues but the latter did not have mustaches. One of the flat-topped altars described had ornaments suggesting the trunks of elephants! All of the monuments at Copan had sculptures and hieroglyphics.

SOUTH AMERICA

In southern Peru the remaining Nazca Indians made fanciful birds and animals of gold metal sheets and decorated their pottery with animals, demons and geometric forms in multiple colors. Their textile work was also intricate and colorful . We assume that the Tiahuanaco people continued to live in the high country although no particular datings from this century have been recorded. A crock of coins of all the Roman emperors of the first three centuries after Christ have been found buried on the coast of Venezuela. No one knows the source of these coins. (Ref. 9,10) As this is being written a newspaper item reports the finding of hundreds of pieces of Roman amphorae at the bottom of a Brazilian bay. The underwater archeologist responsible anticipates finding a sunken Roman ship, soon, and the amphorae will be dated with some accuracy by the pottery luminescence method in the near future, but he is confident that the date will be the 2nd or 3rd century C.E.

1 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

2 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

5 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

6 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

7 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

8 [203] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Incidents of Travel in Central America, Chiapas and Yucatan. (Dover Publ., Inc., New York, 1969 - Re-publication of original published in 1841 by Harper and Brothers).

9 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

10 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

1.  Ref. 66, page 198.

2.  One of the strange features of all early Central American societies is the fact that none of them used the wheel. Children's toy carts with wheels have been found, but no wheels were used otherwise. One explanation has been that the jungles and mountains made wheels useless, and yet why were they not used in cities with miles and miles of roads as just described?

3.  This legend from Las Casas' Historia de las Indias of 1559, as related by Heyerdahl (Ref. 6), pages 113 and 114.

America: A.D. 301 to 400

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

Please see previous chapters, particularly the 6th, 4th and 1st centuries B.C. and the 3rd century C.E., as well as The Pacific: A.D. 301 to 400.

THE UNITED STATES

It is apparent that Indian people inhabited most of the American continent throughout all these early Christian centuries. Most American chiefdoms were agricultural (Hopewell, Mogollon, Hohokam and Anasazi) but along the northwest coast there were unusually rich fishing grounds with whales and seals which supported large villages and a complex ceremonial life. In the southwest it was near the end of the Early Basket Maker period of the Anasazi. In their excavated graves, along with the baskets have been found skeletal remains of these ancient people, buried dressed in string aprons and loin cloths made of hair, furs and feathers. No clay vessels or fired pottery have been found. (Ref. 1, 2)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

At this time, the beginning of the Classic Period in Middle America, Teotihuacán had become the largest of the ancient Mexican empires, extending from the Valley of Mexico to Guatemala. In addition a new empire of the Mayas appeared in Yucatan, with paved roads extending throughout the realm. Although the city was ancient, there were now probably 1,000 people living around Cuella, in northern Belize. A twelve foot high platform, spread over more than an acre, has been dated to this 4th century in that place. Increasingly taller pyramids elevated temples as high as 30 feet above the ground. Norman Hammond (Ref. 3) who has recently excavated many archaeological layers at Cuello, says that he has demonstrated an independent Maya cultural tradition there at least 4,000 years old, and he believes that this area was the mainspring of Maya civilization - not highland Mexico or highland Central America, as some have claimed. The entire Mayan Culture was marked by a distinctive art style, the use of the corbelled vault and advanced mathematical concepts, including the use of zero, a complex calendar and the New World's most advanced writing system. (See also America: 300 to 201 B.C., America: 0 to A.D. 100 and America: A.D. 101 to 200). Mayan astronomers calculated the exact length of the solar year, the lunar month, the revolution of planet Venus and were able to predict eclipses. For the latter they used monuments similar in function to Stonehenge in England. Their sister civilization in Peten also continued on a high level and the skilled Huastec builders of El Tajun at Veracruz diverted fresh-water canals to fertile terraces between tidal rivers and brackish estuaries. This civilization flourished for 800 to 900 years. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

SOUTH AMERICA

More information about the interesting Moche Culture of Peru is warranted at this time, even though they may have lived at a much earlier period, and the accomplishments we shall mention now may be confused with the later Chan Chan Society. A history of their race and customs seems to have been left in their ceramic art. Portrait ceramics show the round face, high cheekbones and hooked nose, with flaring nostrils. The figures frequently depict vivid movement. Their landscapes had unusual detail and their goldwork emphasized mosaics of turquoise encrusted on gold. Using silver and copper in smelting techniques, they had the "lost-wax" method of casting and their own forms of welding, soldering, hammering, gilding and repousse. Although their origin and date of appearance is highly debated, the society apparently existed for about 1,000 years.

In the high country of the Peruvian-Bolivian border, the Tiahuanaco civilization persisted. In the south the Nazcas may have had a close relationship with the Paracas, and a place known as Necropolis may have been used as a cemetery for chiefs and priests of both tribes. More than four hundred mummies, all wrapped in shrouds and elaborate cloaks have been found there in a building under the sands. Some of the embroidery designs show strange, masked people who appear to be descending from above with the help of many ribbons, the significance of which remains unknown. (Ref. 7, 8)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [210] TAMARIN, ALFREDAND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

3 [263] HAMMOND, NORMAN, "Unearthing the Oldest Known Maya", National Geographic 162: 126- 140, July 1982.

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

6 [236] WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

7 [10] BELCHER, TAYLOR AND EDIE, "Great Golden Art of the Ancient Peruvian Artisans", Smithsonian 8:841, Dec. 1977.

8 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

America: A.D. 401 to 500

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

Please see 6th and 1st centuries B.C. and 1st, 3rd and 9th centuries C.E. regarding Arctic Cultures. At Ungava Bay, 750 miles north of Quebec City, there are rock walls dating to A.D. 500. Eskimo legend says they were built by a race of giants with a strange language - Vikings? (Ref. 1) Professor Fell (Ref. 2) and Libyan colleagues have found a 5th century inscription at Figiug Oasis, east Morocco, recording a flight of Christian monks to North America to escape the Vandals. The script was Libyan, the language Libyan Arabic. An early Christian inscription in Libyan Arabic dialect has allegedly also been found by Fell's associates at Oak Island, Nova Scotia.

THE UNITED STATES

In this century the Hopewell trading networks broke down for some unknown reason and the Hopewell influence declined sharply. It is possible that a population explosion strained the limits of the economic system and the breakdown resulted. But along the Mississippi the Mound Builders appeared, and these were the antecedents of the Choctaws Chickasaw, Natches and others. Perhaps the greatest Indian monument of all time was constructed near Chillicothe, Ohio. This Great Serpent Mound, representing a serpent with open jaws clasping an egg, is 1,254 feet long, winding along hilltops with a coiled tail. It does not appear to have any connection with the effigy mounds farther north. See also America in the 3rd century C.E. (Ref. 3)

In the southwest this was the Basket Maker III or Late Basketmaker period of the Anasazi Indians who were using fired earthenware pottery, the technique probably learned from the Mogollons to the south. The water supply for their crops had become inconsistent drought alternating with floods, but the Anasazi solved this problem by special terracing and the building of small dams with irrigation channels. One water-way in southwestern Colorado, however, was four miles long. These people had become skillful builders, using stone and beginning to construct complex homes which we now call pueblos. (Ref. 4, 5)

Once again we must report some almost unbelievable, unconfirmed statements of Barry Fell. In his latest book (Ref. 6) he writes that mathematical notation was revolutionized in this century when Nevada voyagers brought back the decimal system from India. Since European decimal ciphers were not used until the 11th century, this, if true, would place American mathematicians far ahead of their Mediterranean contemporaries. The decimal system required a new type of abacus, to the base ten, and such has allegedly been found in Indiana and is now in the Epigraphic Museum. Abaci from Nevada have previously been mistaken for gaming boards, according to this same author. It is very difficult to accept all these concepts at face value at this time without more corroboration, but Fell does present his evidence in a convincing manner and who knows but what time may yet prove him right?

The pioneering phase of the Hohokam ended about A.D. 500. Interchange with Mexico had continued through the centuries and now the bloody, Mexican ball game associated with religious ritual was introduced. Platform mounds similar to those in Mexico were also erected for use of dancers and musicians. A favorite design on Hohokam pottery was the snake, often shown being attacked by a bird (feathered serpent motive). After the end of this century the Hohokam began to spread out from the desert valleys, moving up the rivers north and northeast. (Ref. 7)

The Mogollon Culture farther to the east continued as previously and it is apparent in the literature that not all writers separate this from the Hohokam and/or Anasazi cultures, but in some respects it is definitely unique. (Ref. 8)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

This may have been the zenith of the Teotihuacan civilization which was the spiritual metropolis of Mexico. Despite a century of modern research no one still is able to say for certain who built this great city, what language they spoke or why they suddenly seemed to vanish. It overlooked a fertile valley with plenty of water and great supplies of obsidian, the raw material for utensils and weapons of great sharpness. Nine-tenths of the city is still buried today. (Ref. 9)

There was also continued growth of the Maya centers of Yucatan with extensive trading including the importation of salt, obsidian and other minerals such as hematite, pyrite and jade. Craftsmen, accountants, commercial diplomats and other experts were needed to run this network. (Ref. 10) According to Principal Epochs of the Ancient History of Yucatan, written in the Maya language from memory by an elderly Indian and translated by the 19th century Don Pio Perez1 the Mayas thought that they were descendants of the Toltecs of Mexico who had arrived in Yucatan between 144 and 217 of our era, but Bacalar and Chichen Itze were apparently not established until between 360 and 432. A few people continued to live in dispersed settlements around the old center of Cerros until about 450, but this would never again recover its place in the great trade network.

This century marked the end of the Period IV in Costa Rican history and was marked by the prolific jade carvings. The best quality jadeite may have been brought to Costa Rica from the north, indicating more and more contact with other Mesoamerican cultures.

Perhaps ceremonial metates, maceheads and jades were used there by an elite group who held these items as badges of office. Most of the jades take the form of the axe-god in which a forest clearing tool makes up the lower half of a pendant. (Ref. 12)

SOUTH AMERICA

In the heart of the central coast of Peru there is a long archeological gap from the time of the Chavin Society to about A.D. 450 when the Early Lima or the Maranga Society appeared with the building of a number of ziggurats on a large hacienda. Maranga territory, as revealed by pottery remains, stretched from the Chillon to the Lurin valleys. The people probably used lateral canals for irrigation. By the beginning of the 20th century there were still about 75 of their great pyramidal mound dwellings in and around Lima but they are gone now. In the lower Chillon Valley there are the ruins of a vast rectangular enclosure 700 feet long, made of trapezoidal clay blocks, each weighing several hundred pounds. They also made long, high, straight walls, miles long, running obliquely to the river bank. These people apparently came from "nowhere" and disappeared again after a few centuries.

During this same period the Tiahuanaco Society flourished in the high Andes. (See multiple previous centuries). In the south the Nazcas may have reached their apex with the construction of the puzzling giant geometric shapes and outlines of animals and plants, made by arranging stones in lines covering some 200 square miles and actually identifiable only from the air. Tons of small stones were so used and strings were stretched from posts to keep the lines straight. Carbon dating of some of the post remains indicates A.D. 500. Maria Reiche, who has spent her adult life in these desert drawings, believes that they are forms of a giant calendar. Another possibility is that they were part of a fertility cult.

In Columbia, 250 miles south-west of Bogata, in a dense forest there are more than 300 large stone statues, some 14 to 21 feet tall, some with teeth like cats and some which seem to be feeding on the children they are holding. Carbon - 14 dating indicates that these were made between this 5th and the 12th centuries. A certain affinity of these statues to those of Easter Island gives some further credence to Thor Heyerdahl's theories of South American migrations into the Pacific. (Ref. 13, 14)

1 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

2 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

6 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

7 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975),

8 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

9 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

10 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

11 [205] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Ibid. Volume II.

12 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

13 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

14 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

1.  As quoted in the Appendix of Stephens book (Ref. 11).

America: A.D. 501 to 600

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

CANADA AND THE FAR NORTH

See previous chapters and 9th century C.E., as well as Europe: A.D. 501 to 600.

THE UNITED STATES

The Mississippian Culture of Mound Builders, which now replaced the decaying Hopewell Culture, flowered along the Mississippi River and other river systems of the south.

Archaeologists do not agree about its origin. Some attribute it to the migration of ideas from Mexico or Central America and it is true that some of the sophisticated art does resemble Middle American. But even more of the art seems to have had roots in Adena or Hopewell and current thinking treats the Mississippian as an indigenous culture, an outgrowth of the Hopewell blended with late arriving Mexican elements. The characteristic feature of the culture is the pyramidal mound serving as a foundation for a temple or a chief's house. Some centers were very small but others were gigantic, as Cahokia at East St. Louis, Illinois, where there were more than 85 mounds and a village area that extended for six miles along the Ohio River. One of the largest of the mounds was about 100 feet high and its base covered 16 acres. The immensity of the labor involved, without the use of wheels or beasts of burden, is almost unbelievable. The entire enterprise may have taken several hundreds of years. The Mississippian population was dense in that at least 383 villages bordered the Mississippi River in the short distance of about 700 miles between points of entrance of the Ohio and Red rivers respectively and there were thousands of other villages up and down the other parts of the river system. (Ref. 1)

If we are to believe Professor Fell (Ref. 2) Libyan science and mathematics continued to flourish in the southwest. The Hohokam continued their colonizing migrations, beginning their colonial period sometime after 550, spreading artifacts over most of Arizona and taking with them their customs, including the sacred ball-game. Farther northeast the Anasazi or Pueblo Builders, continued advancement with better pottery designs and increased trade, importing abalone shells and turquoise. (Ref. 3) From a source still unknown they obtained the bow and arrow and they developed the hafted ax. Agriculture increased with the cultivation of better corn, squash and beans, which added protein to their diet. Their population then soared and their settlements spread so that they even had pit houses in the cliffs of the Grand Canyon. (Ref. 4)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

Teotihuacán in the Valley of Mexico was at the height of its power and was larger than imperial Rome, some estimating the population at 125,000 with an area of 20 square kilometers. (Ref. 5) It was a religious and cultural capital and a major economic and political center for Middle America. Its power extended widely with intermingling of tribes and cultures, so that there was a strong Mexican presence even at Kaminaljuyu (now Guatemala City). Even the lowland Maya region, as at Tikal, had Teotihuacan artistic traditions, although Tikal was only one-fifth as large as the Mexican city.

The Maya had a number of languages, all closely related but not mutually intelligible. There were two principal divisions - the lowlands groups, including Yucatec, Chol and Chorti - and the highlands (Guatemalan) which included Mam and Quiche. The educated Maya were profoundly intellectual and we have noted their mathematics (0 to 100 A.D.) and astronomy (A.D. 301 to 400) previously. A great renaissance of Mayan Culture now took place in the cities of Yucatan, gradually supplanting the importance of Peten, in the south. (Ref. 6, 7, 8, 9)  According to traditions, picture writings and Mexican manuscripts written after the conquest, the Toltecs1 were banished from their native country northwest of Mexico in 596 and proceeded southward. (Ref. 10)

This century marks the beginning of Period V of Costa Rican prehistory, with each of three archaeological zones developing independently. In Guanacaste-Nicoya there was the beginning of the famous Nicoya polychrome pottery tradition which resembled Maya ceramics of the Late Classic period of Honduras and El Salvador. The progress in Panama seemed to come more or less to a halt and this country never developed any truly state-centered societies as seen farther north in Central America. (Ref. 11)

SOUTH AMERICA

NORTHERN AND WESTERN SOUTH AMERICA

Along various parts of the Magdalena River Valley in Colombia and particularly near San Agustin are enormous piles of debris, some of which have been excavated revealing sculptured monoliths and the whole indicating a great ceremonial center something like a Maya complex. Radio-carbon datings indicate activity in this 6th century with continuation for another 1,000 years. Since it has some similarities to both the Olmecs and to Easter Island the question arises as to whether this astonishing statuary was local in origin or from migrating people from Central America or even from Polynesia. Just east of Popayan on the eastern hot-land part of Andean Columbia is an interior, isolated valley called "Tierradentro" where there are interesting monuments perhaps dating to this same era, although it may be a secondary society having existed a thousand years later. Accurate dating has not been accomplished. Tombs there have long ago been looted, probably of gold and jewels, but three dimensional statues reminiscent of Easter Island and representing anthropomorphic gods are comparable to those of San Agustin. (Ref. 12)

Peru consisted of about nine separate regions, each with its own local art style in this century. The Moche, or their descendants, and the Nasca were supreme but other states of some consequence were Cajamarca, Recuary, Lima, Huarpa, Waru, Tiahuanaco and Atacameno, all of which used gold, silver and copper for tools as well as jewelry. In Ecuador, beginning about A.D. 500, there were people of the Milagro Culture, noted for elaborate work in gold and for artificial mounds for burial places and home sites. Some of the latter seem to be associated with ridge systems and others with rectangular earth- works, probably made to farm lands subject to seasonal flooding. This culture may have been an off-shoot of the Moche of Peru, described in previous chapters. Similar farming ridges cover many thousands of acres in Bolivia and Colombia and are present near Lake Titicaca, although the dating of these has not been done. (Ref. 13, 14)

EASTERN SOUTH AMERICA

There were farming tribes in the Amazon rain forest, cultivating manioc. Farther south the Tuni-Guarania tribes had migrated from the Amazon basin into the Brazilian forest and savannah. In what in now Argentina, there was the Aguada Culture about A.D. 600, characterized by black and yellow pottery with feline motives. (Ref. 15, 16)

1 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

2 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

3 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

4 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [177] REINHARDT. KURT F., Germany: 2000 Years. (Frederick ~ngar Publishing Co., New York, 1960).

7 [146] MILTON, RENE, "Teotihuacán", Scientific American, June 1967, page 38.

8 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

9 [163] PAGELS, ELAINE, The Gnostic Gospels. (Random House, New York 1979).

10 [205] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Ibid. Volume II.

11 [266] de SAPIR, OLGA LINARES AND RANERE, ANTHONY J., "Human Adaptation to the Tropical Forests of Western Panama", Archaeology 24: 346-355, Oct. 1971.

12 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

13 [9] BARTHEL, THOMAS S., "The Talking Boards of Easter Island", Scientific American, 236:116-133, March, 1977.

14 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

15 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

16 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

1.  This suggests the probability of more continuity and interrelationships among the original Mexican populations than often stated. Modern histories do not mention the Toltecs as a separate people until about the 9th century.

America: A.D. 601 to 700

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

(See previous and 9th centuries)

THE UNITED STATES

By 600 A.D. the cultural primacy in North America had passed from the Hopewell area to the lower Mississippi valley, particularly in the fertile flood plain between St. Louis and New Orleans, the land of the Mound Builders. (Ref. 1).

In the southwest the Anasazi Indians continued to multiply, with Basket-maker sites extending from the region of present day Lake Mead in Nevada, through southern Utah into the southwest corner of Colorado and then down to northwestern New Mexico and northeastern Arizona. By both archeomagnetism dating of charred wood beams of burned pit-house ceilings and tree-ring dating, their society can be followed in this large area quite exactly. (Ref. 2) The Hohokam Colonial Period and the Mogollon Cultures continued south of the Anasazi.

About A.D. 600 a distinctive group of Indians appeared near the lower end of the Colorado River (southwestern Arizona and an extreme eastern slice of California). These were called the Patayan (also Hakataya) and were Yuman-speaking people who used the flood plains of the Colorado delta for farming, had a unique paddle and anvil pottery decorated with red paint and ground their corn on a trough-shaped metate. Living in this area for 900 years, they became then the modern Yumas, Cocopah, Maricopa, Havasupai, Mojave and Walapai. (Ref. 3, 4) Consistent with his other claims, Fell (Ref. 5) purports to read Islamic inscriptions on certain Nevada rocks and feels that Arabic Libyans made these shortly after A.D. 650 when Islam came into North Africa.

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

By A.D. 600 Teotihuacán in Mexico had a population of perhaps 150,000 to 200,000 and covered about 8 square miles. The city was laid out in a precise grid pattern with large city buildings and apartments for families, offering a maximum of privacy in a crowded city. There still is considerable confusion as to the people who lived in this community.

As mentioned in a previous chapter, old Indian legend called these people "Toltecs" and this may be accurate, even though current usage reserves this term for the later rejuvenated civilization centered at Tula in the 9th and 10th centuries. By at least 650, Teotihuacán was beginning to show signs of impending collapse and the reason for this is another thing that has not been clarified. (Ref. 6, 7, 8)

The lowland Maya made a strong comeback in this century, with several centers flourishing. At least 45,000 people lived at or around Tikal and its sprawling pyramids, temples and house mounds covered some 38 square miles in the dense rain forest of northern Peten.

The most elaborate structure was the so-called northern Acropolis, which covered 2112 acres with 100 buildings and at one time 16 temples. At the same time the Yucatan Mayas were also active. (Ref. 9, 10) The Period V Culture continued in Costa Rica, as noted in the last chapter.

SOUTH AMERICA

In Peru the balance of power after A.D. 600 shifted from the coast to the highlands where the city of Tiahuanaco and the Huari military machine dominated the central Andes by carving out empires that included not only all of Peru and Bolivia, but also part of northern Chile. There were still coastal people of the Nazca Culture, however, and a study of the skeleton of an 8 year old boy from around A.D. 700 in this area showed classical Pott's disease (tuberculosis of the spine) with a psoas abscess, renal disease, pericarditis and terminal miliary tuberculosis of his lungs. In the north there was still Moche influence, perhaps manifested at that time in the Chimu Society, although dating has been difficult. (Ref. 11, 12)

1 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

2 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

3 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

4 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

5 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

6 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

7 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

8 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

9 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

10 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [3] ALLISON, MARVIN J., "Studies of Pre-Columbian American Diseases 1971-1976, National Geographic Research Reports. Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 1-11 (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

America: A.D. 701 to 800

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

The Dorset Arctic Culture continued its many centuries of existence in the far north. Additional details will be given in the next chapter. We have little definitive information about the Canadian Indian tribes at this particularly period, but certainly the far western groups continued as previously and may well have been the sending-off point for the Polynesian migrations into the Pacific.

THE UNITED STATES

"The scale and flamboyance of Mississipian social dwarfed anything known before in North America."1 There were enormous ceremonial centers, with truncated pyramids and huge plazas (as at Cohokia, Mississipi) resembling Mexican centers, with brilliant artistry and a new religious symbolism, reflecting a fascination with human sacrifice, sun and fire. The people had corn fields, pottery, obsidian knives, warehouses, administrative buildings, copper, shell, stone and wood objects. Copper sheets were embossed with human portraits. There was apparently a nobility who lived in special homes arranged about the temples. This society flourished for at least 8 centuries (Ref. 1).

The central and lower Mississippi cultures were centered between St. Louis and Memphis but spread to Wisconsin, Oklahoma, and Alabama and was still in existence when the Spanish came with the white man's diseases. The Encyclopedia of Archeology (Ref. 2) says that the new traits of this culture were:

Rectangular, flat topped mounds used for temple bases
New pottery - using pulverized shell for temper with new shapes and decorations
Maize, as the chief crop

Some of the truncated platform temple mounds were up to 100 feet tall, with structures for religious and/or political purposes on top. Frequently there were several in clusters, spread over several acres. The temples area and residences were surrounded by maize fields with the Corn Mother goddess playing a vital role in the lives of the Mississippian people. Beans, peas, squash and sunflowers rounded out their crops. (Ref. 3).

The historic Indian tribes of the plains such as the Pawnee, Osage, and Arikara, for example, perpetuated the mixed horticultural and bison hunting economy of the previous 800 to 1,000 years. Some of their ancestors' large villages have been excavated along the Missouri and its tributaries. (Ref. 4)

The Colonial Period of the Hohokam continued in the southwest. Their ball courts varied greatly in size from 20 meters to over 100 meters in length. Some believe they were used for the religious Meso-American style ball games but others believe they were stages for a dance. (Ref. 5) According to the remaining available arrow heads, it was sometime between 700 and 900 that the bow and arrow began to be used, rather than the spear, by the Mogollon tribes. These people, first to use pottery in the southwest, developed increasing skill in this endeavor, as they made it by coiling and scraping, not with a pottery wheel. In northern Arizona and New Mexico the Anasazi Culture now shifted from the Basket-maker into the Pueblo Period, with five sub-divisions extending up to modern times. The Pueblo I period lasted two centuries from A.D. 700 to 900, with their pottery showing some strange new shapes, including some made to look like birds. (Ref. 6, 7, 8) Masonry rubble in the Chaco Canyon suggests a gradual shift to ground-level construction of multi-roomed houses which were the first pueblos. It was at this time that the Anasazi mothers started strapping their babies to hard, wooden cradleboards producing flattening of the back of their heads. Kivas became focal points of community and religious practices. (Ref. 9).2

MEXICO AND CENTRAL AMERICA

Legend says that the Toltecs built their capital at Tula in A.D. 720. About 750 much of central Teotihucuan was looted and burned. Perhaps developing drought and arid conditions, as well as military pressure from the north, contributed to the down fall of this civilization, which then shrunk to a series of villages over an area of one square kilometer. Its fall had repercussions throughout middle America. (Ref. 11, 12)

Although it is difficult to keep Fell's (Ref. 13) chronology sorted out, he seems to imply that it was in this century that Americans from the southwest, perhaps with Libyan influence, explored the Pacific and mapped Hawaii.

The lowland Maya Culture continued strong and the National Geographic Society (Ref. 14) dates extensive Mayan projects in Tikal, Guatemala, to this century. These included a summit temple 212 feet high. At the height of its power Tikal had 40,000 inhabitants and its nuclear area alone had more than 3,000 separate structures and some 200 stone monuments, not to mention reservoirs, a central acropolis and a square containing a market area, sweat bath and a ball-game court. A great Maya ceremonial center was at Palenque, Mexico, and one of the most beautiful city sites of the Classic Period was at Copan, Honduras. (Ref. 15) Some buildings, as at Uxmal, Mexico, had cement and rubble cores faced with a veneer of thin, finely carved limestone slabs and elaborately decorated moldings. Three rooms of painted narrative scenes of Maya life were completed at Bonampak, near the Quatemalan border. Henri Stierlin (Ref. 16) writes that the Mayan Yucatan civilization was in full bloom in this century and on through the 10th, creating new styles of architecture. Among the Maya, medicine was carried on by two separate groups: Hemenes, priests organized into a medical society; and the lesser, non-priestly hechiceros, who took care of treating wounds, opening abscesses, reducing fractures, controlling bleeding, etc. (Ref. 17)

In Costa Rica the Nicoya polychrome pottery tradition expanded and diversified, producing the first white-slipped vessels with brilliant red, orange and black painting. These appear to have been made almost exclusively in the northern part of Greater Nicoya, while buff to orange-slipped ceramics were made in centers of Guanacaste. (Ref. 18)

SOUTH AMERICA

NORTHERN AND WESTERN SOUTH AMERICA

Huari, capital of a political state which embraced most of Peru, was overthrown and abandoned about A.D. 800 and Peru was not unified again until the Inca conquest of the 15th century. (Ref. 19) The archeology of this entire period of A.D. 600 to 1,000 is called the Middle Horizon and it includes the emergence of the characteristic style of Tiahuanaco, near Lake Titicaca. There was control of food resources and population movements over a wide area but particularly near Tiahuanaco where the altitude is over 12,000 feet. This Middle Horizon Culture showed polychrome pottery beakers with human, animal and other designs. There was an urban area of perhaps one square mile with an estimated population of between 5,000 and 20,000. (Ref. 20)

Tiahuanaco had a bird-man cult (as the later Chimu and also Easter Island) and the later Inca traditions maintained that the legendary god-men who built Tiahuanaco extended their ear lobes and called themselves "Big Ears" (just as the original Easter Island inhabitants). Later Spanish explorers, particularly Pizarro's companion, Juan de Betanzos, who married an Inca woman, recorded the legend that the white and bearded Tiahuanaco leader, Ticci, stopped over in Cuzco on the way from Lake Titicaca to appoint a local successor and leave orders about producing the large ears, before he went down to the ocean, never to be seen again. This Ticci, who left the Peruvian coast, is undoubtedly the same Tiki-with-large-ears, of Marquesan myth, who led humanity to Polynesia but it is only on Easter Island that ear extension assumed social importance equal to that of Peru. What is definitely known is that Tiahuanacoid objects made in the upper Andes began to appear in the lower, central Andes about A.D. 750. Whether this merely represents the raiding of war parties to the lower lands or actual domination of the lower valleys by the Tiahuanacoid chiefdoms is not known. (Ref. 21, 22)

The remnants of the Moche kingdom continued to decline as the southern states dominated the area. On the coast of Surinam, in what later became Dutch Guiana, about A.D. 700 the sea encroached on the land so that the people were obliged to build a mound as a village site and presumably to make ridges for their crops. This mounded area was occupied continuously until at least A.D. 900. (Ref. 23)

EASTERN SOUTH AMERICA

On the eastern part of the continent there were two settled areas - the Amazonas and Orinoco Basin - and the southern plains. The chief settlement in the latter was the Parana basin where archeologists have found sites dating back to the high Holocene period. But in this 8th century great numbers of Tupis and Guaranis came from Brazil to settle in this region. They lived in fortified villages, eating corn, squash and fish. Even in Brazil, ethnologists have observed cultural traits that are typical of the later Africanized Ecuadorian coast. There are many items that speak for continent to continent migration. The practice of circumcision, for one, may link eastern South America with Africa, not just South Asia. (Ref. 24)

1 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

4 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

5 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

6 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

7 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

8 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

9 [252] FLEMING, STUART, "Chaco Canyon: Mystery of the Pueblos", Archaeology 35: No. 3 37-38, May/June 1982.

10 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

11 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

12 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

13 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

14 [155] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

15 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

16 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

17 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

18 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

19 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

20 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

21 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

22 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

23 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

24 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1.  Quotation from "Who were the Mound Builders?", by Brian Fagan, in Mysteries of the Past, Ref. 215, page 131.

2.  Although it is difficult to keep Fell's (Ref. 10) chronology sorted out, he seems to imply that it was in this century that Americans from the southwest, perhaps with Libyan influence, explored the Pacific and mapped Hawaii.

America: A.D. 901 to 1000

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

We have previously mentioned the Thule Inuit Culture which spread all across the Canadian arctic and Greenland after about 800 A. D. No one knows if the Thule people drove off or simply absorbed the Dorset tribes. Perhaps the latter simply couldn't adapt to the warming climatic change that occurred about this time. In summer the Thule people lived in tents, as had the Dorsets, but their winter houses were better. Foundations of these structures were dug into the ground with tunnel entrances, which trapped warm air inside, and walls and roofs were added of stone, sod or occasionally the baleen and bones bowhead whales. (Ref. 1, 2)

The eastern coast of Greenland is only about 250 statue-miles across the Denmark Strait from Iceland, so it is not remarkable that Icelanders soon knew of its existence. Of course the eastern coast of Greenland is and was very inhospitable to man and the journey around its southern tip to the more livable western coast was somewhat difficult. The fact that the climatic conditions were different in the 10th century and that at A.D. 1,000 parts of Greenland were actually green, probably helped. At any rate, Erik the Red, known as a criminal both in his original Jaeder, Norway home and also in Iceland, took to the sea about 980, landing and exploring southern Greenland, a land which had been reported as seen by another Icelander some 50 years or more previously. After three years of exploration, Eric returned to Iceland, got into more trouble and organized one of the largest arctic expeditions on record to return to Greenland for permanent settlement. He obtained 35 cargo vessels1 with several hundred men, women and children and all their possessions, including horses, cattle, sheep, pigs and dogs. Only 14 of these open ships were actually able to round the stormy south cape of Greenland to safely land on the quieter west coast, but there they built their settlements2. Seals, fish, whales and sea-birds were abundant and fur and walrus ivory could be exported to Europe.

At the very end of the century Leif Erikson, son of Eric the Red, while on a regular trade trip back to Norway, was entertained by the enthusiastic Christian King Olav Tryggveson and commissioned to take a Catholic priest and several religious teachers back to Greenland. Leif departed Norway just before Olav's death in 1,000 and did bring Christianity to Greenland and shortly thereafter allegedly to Vinland3 on the true North American continent. This mainland had been accidentally discovered by Bjarno Herjolfsson from Iceland when on his first trip to Greenland he had missed that large island and hit Newfoundland.

Recent excavations on the northern most tip of Newfoundland have revealed remains of houses, boat sheds and bronze equipment, obviously Norse and dated to about A.D. 1000. (Ref. 5, 6, 7) Brandel quotes from a lecture by Henri Pirenne: "America (when the Vikings reached it) was lost as soon as it was discovered, because Europe did not yet need it."4

THE UNITED STATES

In mid-continent the Mississippi Culture flourished. In the Ozarks of Arkansas, Oklahoma and Mississippi, bluff dwellers constructed rock-shelters, caves and open village sites. Baskets of twilled weave, flour sieves and containers, hunting, fishing, farming bone hoes and tools as well as antler and wooden digging sticks and pottery have been found. These sites were occupied throughout this century and after. It is probable that at about the end of the century the Mississippi group of tribes began to feel the sting of Iroquois attacks from the south, as there are reasons for suspecting that these fierce warriors came via the Gulf of Mexico, probably from South America. (Ref. 9)

Marvin F. Kivett, of the Nebraska State Historical Society, has identified the "Initial Coalescent Culture" that existed from about 900 to 1,400 in the Dakotas. This culture was formed when corn farmers of the central plains (now Kansas, Nebraska and Oklahoma) were forced by droughts to move up the river valleys northward into the Dakotas, where they merged with the initial middle Missouri Culture already established along the river of the same name. Today their descendants are believed to be the Arikara Indians of North Dakota. (Ref. 10, 11)

In the west the Fremont rock art existed at the same time along the Fremont River in Utah as the Anasazi Pueblo Culture existed a little farther south, all of this dating from 750 to 1,200. Construction began on the Pueblo Bonita at Chaco Canyon in New Mexico about A.D. 900. Although building materials of mud, stones and wood was the same as those used by the Mesa Verde Indians, the architecture was markedly superior in principle as well as in technical detail and artistry. The population appears to have been fairly consistent, running between 800 and 1,200 people. (Ref. 12) Studies of excavation sites and skeletons have revealed much about these people. One-third died in infancy; forty years meant old age, with teeth worn to the gums from the grit that ended up in the corn meal from the metate, jaw abscesses and arthritis. Clothes were made of hides and cotton cloth, stitched with yucca leaf fibers. Hundreds of tons of sandstone blocks were carried varying distances for construction of the pueblos. The men spent much of their time searching for firewood and hunting for animal food. When the hunt was poor, the remaining protein deficient diet sapped strength and when famine did occur there may have been cannibalism. (Ref. 13)

Snaketown, on the Gila River southeast of Phoenix, Arizona, was the capital city of the Hohokam until A.D. 1,200. In the 10th century these people entered the Sedentary Period. Population increased, as evidenced by the more numerous villages and longer canals. Specialized villages procured marine shells from the Gulf of California and worked them into jewelry that was traded as far north as Flagstaff. (Ref. 14) Their technique included a method of etching designs on shells using an acid solution made from the giant cactus, saguaro. (Ref. 15, 16, 17)

Harold Gladwin, in his book History of the Ancient Southwest5, gives the end of this century as the time of the first serious incursion of the Athapascan tribesmen into the Pueblo areas. These were the Apaches, who had slowly migrated down from the northern reaches of Canada, bringing their variety of the Athapascan tongue. This century also was the time of the Pueblo II period, with still further pottery changes.

At A.D. 1,000 the Mogollon farming period was coming to an end, but in the Mimbres River area of southern New Mexico, the pottery was decorated with very beautiful and complex triangles, scrolls and zigzag lines with life-like decorations of animals and men inside the bowls. No one knows what happened to these people. They may have been absorbed by others coming down from the northern plateaus. There is little question but what the modern Hopi and Zuni Indians, later considered as part of the pueblo builders, were influenced by the Mogollons. (Ref. 19)

In southern California the desert tradition continued until the end of the century when present day Yuma and Shoshone Indians may have moved into the area. The Shoshone language is related to the later Aztec. (Ref. 20)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

The present day concept is that the Toltecs originated as a blend of northern nomads and civilized Mexican groups in central Mexico, but they became Mexico's greatest militaristic power for two centuries. The Classic Period in the northern Lowlands ended with the invasion of these Toltecs, who established themselves at Chichen Itze in Yucatan about 1,0006, ruling the native people, although their homeland embraced much of northern Mexico and their capital was at Tula, about 60 miles north of present Mexico City. The Toltec style pyramid erected in Chichen Itze was dedicated to Quetzatcoatl, whose Mayan name was Kukulcan and the old Mayan and Mexican cultures blended there. The true Mayan civilization was gone and had given way to the Yucatec in Central America, with a major religious and political center remaining at Chichen Itze. In the highlands there was no actual collapse of the previous culture but even here Toltec influences began to appear. The Huastic civilization at Veracruz continued and burial chambers at that time indicate that there were elaborate entombment ceremonies, with the deceased accompanied in the grave by an attendant and various objects indicating considerable wealth.

An interesting side light to 10th century Mexico has been added by Jeffrey Wilkerson's excavations (Ref. 22) at El Tajin in Vera Cruz, where some ten ball courts have been found. The "game" was an important religious ceremonial, using a solid rubber ball about six inches in diameter and propelled from one end of the court to the other by use of hips and perhaps at times elbows, upper arms and knees. A player, perhaps pre-selected, and perhaps impersonating a god, was decapitated at the conclusion of the "game". El Tajin's rulers were named in the ancient Meso-American fashion according to their birth date in the 260 day Sacred Round religious calendar (composed of 20 rotating day names and 13 numerical prefixes). The chief ruler in this century, who may have been one of the last, was called 13 Rabbit and he was always represented in drawings by a rabbit on top of three dots and two bars, over his head. (See America: 0 to A.D. 100, regarding this mathematical notation). After 13 Rabbit's time, El Tajin appears to have been destroyed, perhaps by the Totanacs who live there now. (Ref. 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28)

Ritual human sacrifices occurred throughout the Classic Period in Central America, even in the Classic Maya Society and the Late Post-classic Period (A.D. 900-1,400) showed this on an ever increasing scale. (Ref. 29) The history of the bow and arrow in this region is difficult to clarify. It appears that this weapon was introduced to the Early Post- classic Maya about A.D. 1,000 by mercenary Toltecs from the Valley of Mexico. The bow then replaced the atlatl, which had previously been introduced by the Teotihuacanos. Actual descriptions of the use of bows and arrows by Maya, however, did not appear until some centuries later. (Ref. 30)

Costa Rica continued in the archeological Period V, with an increasing preference for level, fertile land suitable for agriculture. Active trade with other parts of Central America is revealed by the discovery of such objects as alabaster jars from Honduras and early varieties of Plumbate pottery, a ware with a metallic-type, vitrified surface made in Guatemala or El Salvador. (Ref. 31)

SOUTH AMERICA

By about A.D. 900 the Aymaras Indians established a culture in Bolivia (known as "upper" Peru) and this existed for some 300 years until they were subjugated by the Incas. By the year 1,000, or even earlier, all coastal evidence of Tiahuanacoan influence was gone. The invaders, if they were actually such, had blended with the local coastal populations. According to radio-carbon datings, nothing of value was produced in any place about Lake Titicaca after A.D. 1,000 and the beautiful pottery and fabrics had been replaced by motifs of Collao. Actual archeological knowledge of the centuries just prior to the Spanish conquest, however, is very poor. Except for the presence of two large centers - Tiahuanaco in Bolivia and Huari in Peru - actual dates and duration unknown, there is little concrete information. (Ref. 32)

1 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

2 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

3 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

4 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

5 [237] WILSON, DAVID, The Vikings and their Origins. (Thames and Hudson, London, 1970).

6 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

7 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

8 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

9 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

10 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

11 [241] ZIMMERMAN, LARRY J. AND WHITTEN, RICHARD G., "Prehistoric bones tell a grim tale of Indian vs. Indian", Smithsonian, Sept. 1980, page 100.

12 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

13 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

14 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

15 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

16 [65] FELL, BARRY, America B.C. (Quadrangle - The New York Times Book Co., 1976).

17 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

18 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

19 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

20 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

21 [205] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Ibid. Volume II.

22 [236] WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

23 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

24 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

25 [155] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Archeological Map of Middle America, Ibid. Oct. 1968.

26 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

27 [236] WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

28 [205] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Ibid. Volume II.

29 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

30 [283] NATIONS, HAMES D. AND CLARK, JOHN E., "The Bows and Arrows of the Lacandon Maya", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 36-43, Jan./Feb. 1983.

31 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

32 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1.  These were broader and stronger than the fast, slender Viking attack ships. (Ref. 3).

2.  There were two main settlements - Brattahlid and one farther north near the modern Godthab.

3.  The "grapes" of Vinland may well have been mountain cranberries, wild currents or gooseberries and the wild "wheat" described by Eric may have been Lyme grass. (Ref. 4).

4.  The quotation is from Braudel (Ref. 8), page 335.

5.  As quoted by Tamarin and Glubok (Ref. 18).

6.  Other ideas about the Toltecs have been mentioned on pages 427 and 451. Old Maya legends apparently confused their own history with that of the Toltecs, whom they considered their ancestors. Stephens (Ref. 21) quotes from Principal Epochs of the Ancient History of Yucatan, written in the Maya language from memory by an old Indian and translated in the early 19th century by Don Pio Perez, to the effect that the Toltecs first came to Chichen Itza in 432, stayed until 576 and then returned a second time in 936.

America: A.D. 1001 to 1100

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

The Arctic Thule Culture of northern Canada, northwestern Alaska and western Greenland existed at least from about A.D. 1000 to 1800. The people lived in circular houses, partially subterranean, with whalebone, turf and stone roofs and they used dog sleds with the dogs harnessed in a fan-shape, rather than in tandem. They had Umiak and Kayak boats and represented the final Eskimo Culture of the northern maritime tradition. (Ref. 1) Please also see adjacent modules.

Rose Palmer (Ref. 2) of the Smithsonian Institute confirms the distinct physical and language characteristics of the Northwest coastal Indians. She describes the Nootka and Kwakiutl people of Vancouver Island as having long, distinct faces with high hooked noses. They used copper and had well built houses 40 to 60 feet square, with gable roof s, fireplaces and doors facing the sea, along with family totems. The Haida of the Queen Charlotte Islands were also of a unique Indian type, larger, more stalwart and of lighter complexion. The women were tall and athletic in contrast to other typical Indian women, who tend to be short and fat. The Haida made long voyages in dug-out canoes of red cedar, some carrying 100 persons and equipment, to as far as Vancouver Island and Puget Sound. Wood carvings on totem poles often 50 to 60 feet high, formed part of the front of their buildings. All of the north coastal Indians remained fairly well isolated from the remainder of the continent and other Indian tribes by virtue of the high coastal mountain ranges which made access inland very difficult. (Ref. 3, 4)

Carbon- 14 dating of recent excavations of several buildings and a great hall of an old Viking settlement in northern New Foundland, puts the date as A.D. 1060 (+70 years).

This settlement was probably founded by Leif Erickson, who also apparently went ashore on Baffin Island, calling it "Helluland" and then on down the American coast to Labrador, which he called "Markland". "Vinland", also described by the Norse, undoubtedly was somewhere on the North American coast, possibly Rhode Island, Massachusetts, Labrador or Newfoundland. The latter seems most probable because of the recent excavations, but if so, its wine industry certainly disappeared quickly. At any rate, subsequent to Leif's visit to Vinland, Thorfinn Karlsefne settled this new land with 60 men and 5 women, along with cattle and other animals. Although at first friendly with the native aborigines, eventually there was war, with the Indians attacking in swarms by canoe, ultimately driving out the newcomers. Two Indian boys were captured, however, subsequently taught Norwegian, baptized and taken to Greenland where the colonies were thriving. The warm climatic situation of this century, which allowed an ice-free North Atlantic Ocean, certainly was a factor in these Norse voyages. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9)

THE UNITED STATES

The Mississippian and related cultures continued to exist in the mid-continent. Please see the preceding chapters. It should be mentioned, in passing, that Barry Fell (Ref. 10) feels that numerous artifacts which have been found along the Mississippi and Arkansas rivers, as well as among the Algonquin and Iroquois Indians, are in fact replicas of old Irish-Norse coins and English pennies which had been paid as Danegeld, and originally distributed along the North American coast and rivers by additional voyages of Leif Erickson. Gloria Farley, a co-worker of Fell, has described finding Norse runes in Oklahoma rock inscriptions, dating to about 1050. (Ref. 11, 12)

Southeastern Indians knew much more about metallurgy than generally realized. They made decorative and utilitarian objects from lead and had acquired and used copper from local sources. They fashioned beads, bracelets, earrings, ceremonial knives and axes, gorgets, and breast plates, some elaborately decorated with an eagle or hawk. This metallurgy seemed to be associated with the so-called Southeastern Ceremonial Complex, a cultural association variously called the Eagle, Hawk, Buzzard or Southern Cult. It was associated with fire and sun worship and bird motifs. Sun circles, bi-lobed arrows, forked eyes, hand and eye and crosses can all be found engraved on copper and shell. Before Europeans arrived the south was not rural, as the aborigines lived in towns. Although no one is sure of the location, there were Cofitachiqui, Mabila and Apalachee Indian centers, each of whose populations numbered in the thousands. Some were fortified and palisaded. A pole 5O or more feet in height erected on a small mound in a ceremonial ball game area was important in the culture. Certain death practices were similar throughout the South, in that bones of the dead were cleaned and stored in boxes or baskets. Granaries were commonplace and any town of consequence had a sweat house, or sauna. (Ref. 13)

Some writers have stated than in the southwest the Hohokam way of life began to disappear as the people pulled back to their original homeland in the desert. (Ref. 14) More recent material indicates, however, that they had not yet even reached their "Classical Period". (Ref. 15) The Anasazi and/or related pueblo people, survived at Bonito Pueblo (Chaco Canyon, New Mexico) with their new buildings showing a masonry of facing stones carefully applied to rubble cores, a Mexican technique suggesting contact with missionaries or traders from Mexico. This concept is disputed by some, however, when they point out that new road systems of this period appeared to radiate out of Chaco northward, rather than to the south and that many of the Chaco artifacts, particularly marine shells, were probably acquired by trade with other, native southwest tribes, such as the Hohokam. The inhabitants of Chaco Canyon cut down some 50,000 trees for pueblo construction and fuel, so that the once extensive forests were stripped, allowing erosion of the canyon. Some of the heavy logs for roofing beams may have been carried as far as 30 miles. To elaborate on the remarks above, Pueblo Bonito was reconstructed in this 11th century, with workmen tearing out old walls and building new ones of a core-and-veneer type involving outer walls of sandstone blocks with earth and ruble in the center. Lower walls were more than 3 feet thick, tapering as they rose, until the rear wall was 5 stories high. When finished this pueblo held 650 rooms and may have been occupied by 1200 persons. Seven other great pueblos were also constructed, some only a few hundred yards apart, each of similar design, in one complex. Overall there were about a dozen pueblo complexes in the Chaco Canyon with well over 2,000 rooms. At least 70 communities, similar in design but generally smaller, existed outside the canyon from a few to 100 miles away. Recent aerial studies have indicated that the great road system, mentioned above, connected these outliers to the center. The roads ran arrow straight, with cuts through some mounds and steps carved in cliff faces, all up to 30 feet wide. One of the larger outlying pueblos was on the San Juan River, 40 miles north of Chaco and known now as the Salmon ruins. Started in 1088 it was completed in 5 years and contained 300 rooms. Huge wooden beams were obtained in the La Plata mountains, more than 75 miles away. It had a great kiva and great tower with 6 feet thick walls rising from the second story of the town. The walls were supported by solid buttresses.

The Bonito people monitored the solar cycles with a solar observatory on Fajada Butte. Spiral patterns carved into native rock caught shafts of light between other rocks in a precise way, which indicated the solstices and equinoxes. A scarcity of burials at the Great Chaco complex has posed some questions and resulted in numerous theories. Was this only a large ceremonial center serving as a mecca for pilgrims coming in on the great road system? Or was it a type of federal city for handling the outlier's trade and political alliances? (Ref. 16) Near the end of the century the pueblo dwellers increased their defenses, building watch towers, doubling wall thicknesses and restricting access to their homes, suggesting that the Apaches were reaching this territory. (Ref. 17)

According to ancient Indian beliefs the San Francisco Peaks1 which are surrounded by a large volcanic area in northern Arizona, are the home of Kachina spirits. Some Indians had lived in pit-houses near those peaks since about A.D. 600 but suddenly in A.D. 1065 there was a violent volcanic eruption, with a cone of cinders and ash thrown a thousand feet high and a stream of lava flowed on the ground. Black ash covered 800 square miles and the terrified Indians left. When they eventually cautiously returned they found that the ash had trapped water beneath and had produced a very fertile area which could be farmed with very little extra moisture needed. Archeologists have given those Indians the name "Senagua", meaning "without water". The rich soil attracted others, including Hohokam, Mogollon and Cohonina and there was an interchange of ideas and cultures. (Ref. 18)

The Mogollon Culture of southern New Mexico and eastern Arizona had continued through the centuries in various stages of development. The people of that area now began to build houses in the pueblo style with buildings above ground. They had fine, polychrome member pottery, some with red designs on brown and some with rectangular designs with white stripes. Other pottery was black on white with complicated curvilinear and rectilinear designs. Cotton was grown and used as cloth. (Ref. 19)

A unique Indian culture, which was earlier considered of unknown antecedents and descendants, flourished about 950 to 1 150 in southwestern New Mexico, just east of what is now Silver City. They were called Mimbrenos, after their river valley and were peaceful corn growers who created some of the most beautiful of American Indian pottery. This had imaginative decorations and was all accomplished without the use of the potter's wheel or the kiln. This work is coveted by museums and collectors throughout the world. It is known now that these people were part of the Mogollons. (Ref. 20, 21)

MEXICO AND CENTRAL AMERICA

The Yucatec and the Toltec civilizations, which were discussed in the last chapter, were both failing by the end of this century. According to tradition, drought and sickness took their toll among the Toltecs and their monarchy ended in 10522. Their land then lay devastated for a century. On the Gulf coast, the Huastec Society appeared at about this time. (Ref. 22)

SOUTH AMERICA

In this century the coastal societies came under the control of the Chimu (formerly Chimor), who built the great capital of Chan Chan near the present city of Trujillo, near the sea. This was in the old Mochican area but was an entirely new capital. From this century until the subjugation of these people by the Incas, some four centuries later, the sequence of events is very unclear. Some of the buildings of Chan Chan are very large and may have been built in different periods. Some believe part of the edifices was constructed by invaders from the north (even from as far away as Ecuador) in about 1200.

Near Chan Chan the powerful Chicama River could be used, via a long canal, for irrigating a huge desert zone. (Ref. 24)

The Diaguites, originally of the semi-arid Argentine Andes, probably existed at this time and continued to live there until confrontation with the Spaniards some 500 years later. They have left ruins of small fortified settlements on easily defensible crests, approached by narrow, paved roads, always located near a river or spring. Farmland was terraced to save rain water. They made rock carvings and unusual pottery, one type of which is the "Santa Maria" urn, with a wide neck and side handles. (Ref. 25)

1 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

2 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

3 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

4 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

5 [160] OXENSTIERNA, ERIC, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

6 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

7 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

8 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

9 [156] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, Atlas of the World. 5th Edition. (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1981.

10 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

11 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

12 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

13 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

14 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

15 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

16 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

17 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

18 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

19 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

20 [223] UNDERWOOD, E. THURSTON, "The Mimbrenos: Masters of the Pottery Art", Southwest Heritage 6: 15-161, Summer, 1976.

21 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

22 [205] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Ibid. Volume II.

23 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

24 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

25 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1.  These peaks are just north of Flagstaff and Williams, Arizona.

2.  Trager (Ref. 23) refers to the epidemic and decline as occurring in the Mayan Empire, but this is probably just another error in that text.

America: A.D. 1101 to 1200

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

The Thule Arctic and the Northwest Indian cultures have been described in the preceding chapters. The west Greenland settlement of Norse was prospering in this 12th century and there were at least 16 stone churches and a fine cathedral at Gardar. Pope Paschal II appointed Erik Gnupsson as the first bishop of Greenland and Vinland in 1112. At this time the southern half of Canada undoubtedly had a great number of Indian tribes, but information about them is scanty. The Norse and the Indians were apparently hostile to each other. (Ref. 1, 2)1

1 (Ref. 3)

THE UNITED STATES

In the central and southern parts of the United States the Mississippi and coalescent cultures continued as noted in the preceding chapters. In the southwest, some- time after 1150 the Mesa Verde Anasazi constructed the famous Cliff Palace, some 325 feet long, 100 feet deep, with many subterranean, sacred rooms and turret-like towers. In mid-century, however, the building stopped and the population of this and the Pueblo Bonito in Chaco Canyon, New Mexico, began to decline and the pueblos were soon abandoned, perhaps as a result of loss of arable fields as the water table lowered or incident to the severe deforestation mentioned in the last chapter. It has been estimated that Chaco Canyon's population dropped to less than 20% of its 11th century peak. (Ref. 4) Increasing cold may have been another factor. Only the Mesa Verde people hung on in a slightly better climate. (Ref. 5) Other sources believe, however, that these pueblo Indians were driven or fled as the result of invasion by barbarian Athapascans (Apache and Navaho). In the northwestern part of Arizona at Wupatki in the sunset crater area of the Sinague, there was a structure containing over 100 rooms, with 3 stories, as well as an open air amphitheater resembling a ceremonial Anasazi kiva and a ball court. But the volcanic soils were now drained of their nutrients and farming was getting less productive.  (Ref.6)

McGuire and Schiffer (Ref. 7) state that the Classic period of the Hohokam began about A.D. 1150, to last for 300 years. This was characterized by adobe compounds enclosing rectangular rooms and plazas, platform mounds, extensive irrigation canals and polychrome and polished redware ceramics. The red-on-buff pottery was distinctive of all Hohokam sites. Hundreds of villages were scattered over the Gila and Lower Salt rivers of central Arizona. In the past other writers have claimed that the Hohokam had begun a sharp decline by this century and that any advancements seen were due to invasion of the area by another group, the Salado. This view has been discarded in the last 5 to 8 years. The most obvious change in the Classic period was in architecture. Multi-storied houses appeared and the canal system was further refined, with extensive networks and some canals carried water as far as 32 kilometers. Polished red vessels tended to replace the earlier red-on-buff pottery. Although some northern frontier villages were abandoned at this time, the population of the Gila-Salt Basin increased to perhaps 20,000. (Ref. 8)

MEXICO AND CENTRAL AMERICA

Tula, the capital city of the Toltecs, was violently destroyed in the middle of this century. Although it has not been completely excavated the indications are that it was a large city with all the principal features of Toltec art and architecture.

A new Indian civilization appears to have been in an active growth phase at this time in Aztlan1. No one is sure of the precise location of Aztlan, although Professor Sigberto Jimenez Morena suggests that it was an island village on the San Pedro River delta, some 450 miles northwest of present Mexico City, now called Mexcallitan. This has been called the Venice of Mexico because in rainy seasons the streets flood and the people move about by canoe. The adjacent Mangrove swamps have thousands of herons, including at least 15 different species. The Aztec legends say that their small tribe moved from Aztlan into the area of Tula, once the capital of the great Toltec Empire, and there they picked up what they could of the Toltec civilization from its descendants. Toynbee (Ref. 9) calls this nascent Aztec Society the "Mexic" and in this 12th century it consisted of various small states, with Chichimec people forming petty kingdoms along the Valley of Mexico. One site was Tenayuca. (Ref. 10, 11, 12, 13)

SOUTH AMERICA

The greatest activity of the 12th century in South America continued to be in the region of northern Peru and what is now Ecuador. By mid-century the Chimus, in their great kingdom of Chimor, had revived the old Moche Kingdom, in a political and geographic sense. They were great builders and extended the old Moche irrigation and road systems. Their black pottery, however, was in contrast to the vigorous polychromatic Mochica pieces. Gold was apparently plentiful and was used chiefly in the pure state, although sometimes alloyed with silver or copper. Fantastic, intricate and delicate golden objects of the Chimu were found in 1937 in the area of Lambayeque, Peru, near the Ecuador border. The population of the nation may have been 250,000 and Chan Chan, the capital, covered 3 1/2 square miles. Ca jamarquilla and Pachacamac were additional large cities, each larger than Rome or Alexandria.

Five or six hundred miles south of the Chimu the Chincha Basin was also being rejuvenated on a large scale, with cultivated land extending over about 12 miles on the formerly sterile sea coast terraces. Some 37,000 acres of land of the Canete Basin were now utilized and this was accomplished by construction of lateral canals 24 to 36 miles long. The Ica and Nazca basins remained quiet. (Ref. 14)

According to Inca myth it was in this century that Manco Capac and his sister-wife, Mana Ocllo, left the Island of the Sun in Lake Titicaca and went forth as son and daughter of the Sun God, Inti, to found the Inca Empire, "The Kingdom of Gold". (Ref. 15)

The Diaguites remained in the Argentine Andes and, although dating in inconclusive, sometime in this approximate time-frame they practiced an advanced metallurgy, using copper ore pulverized on stone mortars and mixed with zinc, gold and silver. This was then melted in hearths, using the wind as bellows, and finally poured into molds. Gold was beaten into very thin sheets and used to decorate masks and jewelry by the reverse hammering technique. (Ref. 16)

1 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

3 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

4 [252] FLEMING, STUART, "Chaco Canyon: Mystery of the Pueblos", Archaeology 35: No. 3 37-38, May/June 1982.

5 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

6 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

7 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

8 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

9 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

10 [138] McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

11 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

12 [146] MILTON, RENE, "Teotihuacán", Scientific American, June 1967, page 38.

13 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

14 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

15 [10] BELCHER, TAYLOR AND EDIE, "Great Golden Art of the Ancient Peruvian Artisans", Smithsonian 8:841, Dec. 1977.

16 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

1.   Aztlan is the source of the word "Aztec" and means "people of heron place".

America: A.D. 1201 to 1300

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

Runic inscriptions left by Norse explorers about A.D. 1300 have been found near Upernavik far up in Baffin Bay on the western Greenland coast. In addition, recent excavations in an old Thule Arctic Culture settlement still farther north, beyond the tip of Greenland on the Canadian Island of Skraeling, have revealed links of chain-mail, iron boat rivets, parts of barrel bottoms, pieces of oak (not native to that part of Canada) and European-style knife blades and spear points. All of this would indicate that the Viking Norse explored much farther north in America than previously believed, although at the moment one cannot say with certainty that these Norse artifacts were not carried north by Thule contacts made farther south. (Ref. 1)

The southern Greenland settlements were still very much Catholic and a crisis arose because of the absence of grain for bread and grapes for the sacraments. The local parish asked Rome for permission to substitute meat and beer, but Pope Gregorius personally insisted that at least bread be used. (Ref. 2)

No special information concerning the Inuit of the far northern climes and the Indian populations of central and western Canada during this 13th century has been located, and we assume that life continued in much the same fashion as noted in previous modules.

THE UNITED STATES

The Missouri River Valley Indians continued to farm in the Dakotas and the Mississippian Culture persevered with great ceremonial centers at Cahokia, Moundville and Etowah. The latter was a large site in Georgia, dating from 1200 to 1700, which was a fortified farming village with three temple mounds and carved stone figures of men, some of which were 15 to 30 feet in height. The figures were portrayed in the sitting position, suggesting a Mexican influence. The largest of the mounds there was 70 feet high with 380 square feet of base and probably containing 4,000,000 cubic feet of earth. (Ref. 3, 4)

The Mesa Verda cliff dwellers began construction of a great masonry temple, sun oriented and containing kivas three walls thick. Recently, excavations in the Montezuma Valley near Cortez, Colorado, have indicated tremendous pueblo type buildings and kivas on level ground. Dr. Arthur Rohn has identified 103 kivas at Yellowjacket and more than 80 at Mud Springs. It may be that the real center of the Mesa Verde culture was not on the mesa, but in this valley where conditions were better for agriculture. All of these complexes reached their peaks in this 13th century, but by 1300 the entire region was abandoned for good. Some of the Anasazi moved south to confront the Mogollons in the mountains, some simply went north and joined their relatives who were the ancestors of present day Hopis and some went eastward across the continental divide to the Rio Grande, where they developed the final phase of their culture from south of Albuquerque to Taos - the modern Pueblo Indians. The movement included the Sinaguas, who went to the Verde River Valley and built clusters of masonry houses along the cliff sides of the high mesas, there. The reasons for the rather sudden dispersion of these people are still a mystery. Tree ring studies indicate severe drought between 1260 and 1300 and it is possible that crops withered and the inhabitants had to move to eat. Farther to the southwest most authorities would agree that the Hohokam Classic period continued deep in the Arizona desert, building up to a peak of activity in the next century. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8)

MEXICO AND CENTRAL AMERICA

Chichen Itza on the Yucatan peninsula was abandoned by the Toltecs sometime before 1224 but a sparse native population remained. Constant local wars of the next three centuries destroyed 4,000 years of civilization in this land. In north Mexico, the Aztecs were one of the Nahua tribes of the Anahuac Valley, apparently having moved inland from their probable origin in the San Pedro River delta, and for centuries there were petty tribal wars in this area also, with sometimes one tribe prevailing and sometimes another. The Aztecs were not yet in power and they came south as refugees, picking up remnants of the Toltec civilization. The Aztec authority, Professor Miguel Leon-Portilla writes1 that the only thing they brought with them was an indomitable will. (Ref. 9, 10, 11)

In Central America, proper, there was no quantum jump in cultural achievement in these pre-Columbian centuries. The archaeological Period VI continued in Costa Rica with the zenith reached in the lost-wax method of casting gold and tumbaga (a gold-copper alloy) pendants, particularly in the southern Diquis area. Similar cultures continued in Panama and other adjacent regions. In none of these countries did a State-centered society develop. (Ref. 13, 14)

SOUTH AMERICA

Legend has it that there were small Inca tribe chiefdoms in a remote upper Andean valley in this 13th century, but nothing is really known for certain about their origin.

Chan Chan (300 miles northwest of Lima) was the capital of the Chimu people and at this time it had 50,000 inhabitants and covered an area of 9 square miles, with a strictly rectangular layout. A canal system, including one over 50 miles long, supplied the city with water. The city has been well preserved because of the sand which later covered it and the lack of rain. The Andes were just now coming out of the past into modern times and their great irrigation systems played a key role. (Ref. 15, 16)

Araucanian and Diaguite communities continued in the south Andes and some of the latter people migrated from the eastern to the Pacific slopes, perhaps coming under some influence of a Peruvian successor society to the Nazca political system called the Ika- Chincha chiefdom. The western Diaguites had a stratified society dominated by a warrior class and their decorations showed men wearing feather head-dresses and carrying spear throwers and long spears. (Ref. 17)

1 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

2 [138] McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

3 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

6 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

7 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

8 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

9 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

10 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

11 [138] McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

12 [138] McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

13 [265] SNARSKIS, MICHAEL J., "The Pre-Columbian Art of Costa Rica", Archaeology Vol. 35, No 1: 54-581, Jan./Feb. 1982.

14 [266] de SAPIR, OLGA LINARES AND RANERE, ANTHONY J., "Human Adaptation to the Tropical Forests of Western Panama", Archaeology 24: 346-355, Oct. 1971.

15 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

16 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

17 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

1.  As quoted by MacDowell (Ref. 12)

America: A.D. 1301 to 1400

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

The Thule Inuit were exceptional arctic hunters, using a variety of harpoon heads of different shapes and sizes, depending upon the immediate game available. The harpoon heads were very similar to those found in the Bering Strait area, suggesting a direct connection. (Please also see adjacent modules).

By this time the Norsemen on the southwest coast of Greenland had founded some 280 farms, 2 Episcopal residences, some monasteries and 17 churches, maintaining contacts with Iceland by open boats and being taxed by the Vatican in Rome. It is of interest that the route from Norway or Great Britain, via the Shetlands, Faeroes, Iceland, Greenland and Baffin Island to Labrador and continental America has no ocean gap wider than the length of Lake Michigan. (Ref. 1, 2) In 1362 the Norwegian king, Magnus Ericson, sent an expedition west to look for some of his people of a previous voyage who had failed to reach their Greenland destination. It is possible that the would-be rescuers entered what would later be Hudson's Bay1.

Regarding the Canadian Indians, please see previous modules.

THE UNITED STATES

There is an ancient church at Newport, Rhode Island, which Professor Fell (Ref. 4) says was built in this 14th century by Norsemen. He quotes the writings of an Italian explorer, Giovanni de Verrazana, who sailed in 1524 northward from Florida to Labrador to the effect that while sailing along the Narragansett coast he was astonished to see a tall, stone-built "Norman villa". On going ashore he found friendly, civilized Indians, some with fair skins, but they could remember nothing of how the stone structure had been built. This "Norma villa" was undoubtedly the Round Tower of Newport, in which some claim that Norse runes have been inscribed. Others deny entirely the antiquity of this building.

There is little accurate history of the North American Indians at this time but probably the tribal differentiation had about reached the point which was to be glimpsed by the Europeans in the last of the next century. Recent excavations at the ancient village of Crow Creek in South Dakota have revealed some 500 skeletons of men, women and children of the Coalescent Culture, apparently massacred by other Indians. The lack of females in the 12 to 19 year old bracket and the absence of very young children probably indicates that this group was taken captive. The skeletons showed evidence of multiple diseases and injuries, with a total of some 1137 incidents of abnormality identified. Bone cancer was virtually non-existent and arthritis was rare, but the bones did show evidence of infection, vitamin and protein deficiencies. No one knows why this massacre occurred among these usually placid, farmer peoples nor why their culture seemed to disappear entirely about A.D. 1400. Perhaps occasional or chronic malnutrition was a factor; perhaps the Missouri flood plain and terraces became over-populated; or perhaps an extended drought could have tipped the balance. (Ref. 5)

Recent research regarding a Mississippian Culture group called the "Dallas Society" of eastern Tennessee and northwestern Georgia has yielded much information about the life-styles of southeastern Indians of this and the next century. Three types of villages have been found, the largest probably originally containing 1,000 or more people, were located at key locations in the Tennessee River drainage and had multiple earthen mounds, fortifications and wattle-and-daub single room houses. The flat-topped earthen mounds served as substructures for civic or religious buildings. Intermediate-sized villages and small hamlets were located near fertile alluvial soils necessary for cultivation of corn, beans, squash and sunflowers. This agricultural diet was supplemented by deer and fish and wild plant foods, chiefly various nuts. (Ref. 6)

Excavations on Key Marco on the Gulf coast of Florida indicate that Indians living there between A.D. 1000 and 1500 lived in thatch houses built on stilts and used spear-throwers and swords armed with sharks’ teeth. They lived by hunting, fishing and gathering of shell-fish. They had some elaborate, wooden sculptures, which included animals, heads of deer, birds, etc. along with rush and bark matting, basketry and untempered pottery. (Ref. 7)

In the southwest United States, the Hohokam people built their most enduring monument, the four-story Casa Grande on the Gila River, about A.D. 1350. This was probably an elite residence, perhaps a storehouse and observatory. There were observation holes which could be used to identify the summer and winter solstices. It seems likely that their society had become very stratified, with high chiefs and lowly peasants. (Ref. 8) The transplanted Anasazi flourished in their new area in central New Mexico. By A.D. 1330 Arroyo Hondo Pueblo near Sante Fe had 1,500 people and similar pueblos developed all along the Rio Grande. (Ref. 9) Rooms, one on top of the other up to three stories, were carved into the cliff, and then other rooms of mud mortar and stone were built in front of these. The roof beams were supported by sockets carved into the cliff. Rock art and painted murals were common. An ingenious method of maintaining moisture in the field involved the spreading of gravel to reduce evaporation. Thousands of acres were so treated and these fields produce lusher plant growth even today. Agricultural products were augmented by the raising of turkeys and trading with eastern tribes brought buffalo meat. (Ref. 10) The original pueblo people, however, from this time on were pretty well replaced by descendants of the invading Athapascan-speaking tribes such as the Apache, San Carlos, Tonto, Mescalero and the Navajo. (Ref. 11, 12, 13)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

In this 14th century the Gulf coast of Mexico was occupied by the Totanac people while inland, the Aztecs, a branch of the Nuhua, reached the shores of Lake Texcoco in 1325 and built an impregnable capital in the marshes of the lake and on an island, within the next ten years. This capital city, Tenochtitlan, soon had more than 150,000 people and was laid out on a grid plan covering more than 4.6 miles, much of this being reclaimed swamp land. Canals reached all parts of the city and five causeways linked it to the main- land. This area is now a part of Mexico City. Of incidental interest is the fact that these Indians raised a special hairless breed of dog, a larger ancestor of the Chihuahua, for food.

The Aztec medical profession had an hereditary character and healers were divided into specialties, such as the "tictl", who used magic and some anatomical knowledge and the properties of plants and minerals. Others were teeth pullers, bone setters, etc. At Mayapan in the Yucatan there was somewhat of a Maya renaissance, founded by colonists from Chichen Itza. (Ref. 14, 15, 16)

Up to this time in this outline, we have had little or nothing to say about the Caribbean, when discussing Middle America. This is not to say that there were no people living on those islands, but simply that specific information has been meagre. It has been established, however, that Taino Indians, with ancestors in South America, were now spreading from Haiti out over Cuba, Jamaica and the Bahamas. These Arawak-speaking people pushed back or enslaved a more primitive tribe, the Siboney. They grew corn and yams, made cassava bread from yucca, spun and wove cotton and made ornamented, fine, brown pottery. Artificial flattening of infants' heads produced low foreheads in the adults. They used honey for sweetening and smoked cigars through their noses. The more southern islands, including Porto Rico, were inhabited by the cannibalistic Caribs. (Ref. 17)

SOUTH AMERICA

The Cuculis and Puerto Viejos, who lived along the lowlands of coastal Peru in this and the next century, used an ancient technique of digging wells that slowly filled over a 24 hour period, so that at the end of each day, a small sluice could be opened to let water into a network of canals leading into a man's garden. People of a hundred villages lived in this way in an area where today one cannot even find a lizard. Although the pottery of these people was poor, they had rich fabrics and some metal devices, including beam scales. Two Puerto Viejo villages have been unearthed, one at the southern tip of Chica, where the mountains enter the ocean and cut off the beach. The inhabitants had returned to the use of part underground houses, not previously used in this region for 3,000 years, although such structures had been found among the Diaguites on the Argentine slopes of the Andes. The Puerto Viejo built temples and palaces, too. One of these had a base of some 3,600 square yards and was built on a cliff. Some 3,000 acres of land were used for agriculture, chiefly for corn. (Ref. 18)

Legends state that the Incas already had a flourishing capital at Cuzco in this century, but certainly it could not compare with the great urban site of Chan Chan, capital of the Chimu Empire existing on the desert north coast, in this and adjacent centuries. No one knows exactly when Chan Chan was built on the threshold of the modern city of Trujillo. The Chimus dominated some 12 coastal valleys and a territory of some 125,000 arable acres. They apparently did not impose their rule beyond the boundaries of the Sechura Desert in the north. The use of supplementary and more stable water resources may have been the factor that favored the setting up of this kingdom, as the area is actually an oasis, extended by irrigation canals. Early Chimu art depicted many bird-men with long, hooked beaks. As on Easter Island, these men were frequently depicted navigating reed vessels. Except that the Chimu were urban dwellers with highly organized military and social systems, little was reported about them until very recently. A possible clue as to the origin of these people is in the report of Father Miguel Cabello de Balboa who interviewed Peruvians in the 16th century. The natives said that in "ancient times" a large group of families left the place of the Mochicas with a great fleet of "Balsas" (rafts) and sailed north to establish the Chimu Dynasty and culture. (Ref. 19, 20, 21)

1 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [66] FELL, BARRY, Saga America. (Times Books, New York, 1980).

5 [79] GREEN, MAUREEN, "A tough people in a tough time, the Vikings also had a gentler side", Smithsonian, Sept., 1980, page 60.

6 [284] HATCH, JAMES W. AND GEIDEL, RICHARD A., "Tracing Status and Diet in Prehistoric Tennessee", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 56-59, Jan./Feb. 1983.

7 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

8 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

9 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

10 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

11 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

12 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

13 [210] TAMARIN, ALFRED AND GLUBOK, SHIRLEY, Ancient Indians of the Southwest. (Doubleday & Co., Inc. Garden City, New York 1975).

14 [138] McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

15 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

16 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

17 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

18 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

19 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

20 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

21 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

1.  This statement is taken from Trager (Ref. 3), but as with all of his items, no reference is made as to the source of the information

America: A.D. 1401 to 1500

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

CANADA AND THE FAR NORTH

The last recorded voyage from Iceland to Greenland was in 1410. The worsening climate had reduced productivity of Greenland livestock and there was increasing navigational hazards from drift ice. Nevertheless, in 1432 a treaty had been reached between the Norwegian and English kings in an effort to stop English pirates from roving the Davis Strait and a papal letter of 1448 condemned these English pirates. All Greenland settlements were apparently abandoned by about 1500.

In the arctic there were Thule Eskimos and Aleuts and in the subarctic regions there were many Indian tribes, including Kutchin, Kaska, Chipewyan and Cree. There seems no doubt that the Thule people, previously described as inhabiting northern Canada and Greenland from at least A.D. 1000 onward, were the direct ancestors of todays Polar Eskimos, who live on Greenland's northwest coast. The Thule, like the Dorset before them, were artists of ivory carving, both for implements and decorative pendants. Although they apparently originally had pottery when they lived primarily in Alaska, their northeastern Canadian areas had a scarcity of clay and firewood, so they carved vessels out of soapstone for seal-blubber lamps, over which they boiled their meat or fish. At the end of this century large scale fishing enterprises began on the Newfoundland banks, where the warm waters of the Gulf Stream meet the colder arctic currents and the cod survive in amazing numbers. Basques, French, Dutch and English all scuffled for dominance, with the Spanish Basques finally being driven out. (Ref. 1) In 1497 Giovanni Cabato, a Genoese sailing under the British Union Jack and the anglicized name of John Cabot re-discovered Newfoundland and Nova Scotia for England. Three years later Corte-Real of Portugal explored the coast of Labrador. (Ref. 2) On the Canadian Pacific coast there were the Tlingit tribes and on the Great Plains were Blackfoot, Ojibwa, Ottawa, Huron and Micmac. The United States Apache are related to the Canadian Athapascan tribes, some of whom migrated to reach the southwest (Arizona) in this 15th century. By the 1490s there were about 200,000 Indians spread over much of Canada. (Ref. 3, 4, 5)

THE UNITED STATES

To supplement the remarks made in the paragraph above, in North America as a whole there were, in this century, about 1,000,000 Indians, with about 500 different languages. In northeastern United States there were Pottowatomie, Susquehannock, Iroquois, Erie, Miami, Illinois and Shawnee. In the southeast were Chickasaw, Cherokee, Creek, Chocktaw, Natchez and others. In the far west were the Nes Perce, the California tribes of Pima, Yokuts, Chumash, Cochimi and then inland the Shoshone, Utes, Apache and in the central plains the Sioux, Cheyenne, Kiowa, Wichita, Comanche and many others. (Ref. 6, 7)

Regarding the Indians of the Great Plains, the Huff archeological site, some 20 miles south of Bismarck, N.D., shows a remarkable village built by the ancestors of the Mandan tribe and occupied from 1400 to 1600. House lodges still number more than 100 and the Missouri River has been cutting away an untold number by eroding the bluff on which the houses rest. These structures averaged 38 feet by 30 feet, supported by central posts. The walls were of wattle and daubb and the roofs perhaps of sod. There is evidence of both horticulture and bison hunting. (Ref. 8)

The Mississippian Culture, which has been discussed in previous chapters, reached its climax about A.D. 1500, with the unique southern cult which included pyramids grouped around a central square or plaza with a wood, wattle and daub and thatch temple on its summit. These had a strong suggestion of influence from Mesoamerica. One of the most notable temple sites was Cahokia, at St. Louis, where groupings of pyramids and burial mounds cover several square miles. The largest is 104 feet high and covers 16 acres.

Bizarre articles of copper, shell, stone, wood and clay in some mounds in the south show a preoccupation with violence and death. Apparently southern Indians had kept captive slaves for centuries. For example: when the Whites arrived in the next century, the Lower Creeks had Yamasee slaves. The standard beverage in Mississippian times was the "black drink", usually made from parched leaves of the yaupon, a type of holly. (Ref. 9, 10)

In the southwest something happened to the Hohokams about A.D. 1450 and their climb toward civilization rather abruptly ceased and their society collapsed, cause unknown. Their descendants are probably the unassuming Pima, living in modest pithouse villages, much like their ancestors did a thousand years before. (Ref. 11) Pueblo Indians remained scattered across the southwest, but chiefly in the Albuquerque, Sante Fe, Taos area. Kiva walls in the great 1,000 room complex at Kuaua, north of Albuquerque, had 85 coats of plaster, with paintings of spirit dancers invoking rain and other blessings. (Ref. 12)

Designs similar to, but smaller than the famous giant, ground drawings near Nazca, Peru, have been found near Blythe, California overlooking the Colorado River. These are judged to date to this 15th century, are of human and animal forms and have been extensively photographed by archeologist Jay von Werlhof and photographer Harry Casey over a several year period. One 75 foot tall, human effigy resembles the broad-shouldered figures of Navaho sand paintings. Another human caricature is 170 feet high and may represent Ha-ak, a mythical creature, who ate children. (Ref. 13)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

A number of city-states had arisen as heirs of the Mexican Toltec priest-state, including the Totonac, Mixtec, Zapotec, Maya and then the Circun-Caribbean groups. One of these, Tenochtitlan, along with two lessor cities gained military predominance and held a loose power over most of central Mexico. After A.D. 1431, under the chieftains Itzcoatl and Moctzuma I, the Aztecs of Tenochtitlan mastered the other tribes of the valley and then crossed the mountains and dominated southern Mexico, as well. These Aztecs attained a high degree of development in engineering, architecture, art, mathematics and astronomy, whether through their own endeavors completely or through adoption of culture from pre-existing societies. Picture writing, rapidly approaching phonetics, was developed and agriculture, gold and silver workings, pottery and textiles were advanced. Moctezuma I and Nezahualcoyotl, king of Texcoco, an allied city-state, built a 9 mile long dam in Lake Texcoco, to separate salt water from fresh. Aztec aquaculture harvested spirolina, a high protein algae, carried as rations by warriors. It is still exported to Japan as a condiment, in the amount of 700 tons a year. The Aztec language was Nahuatl and 1,200,000 Mexicans still speak it today. Such world words as "chocolate", "tomato", "tamale" and "chili" have come directly from this source. (Ref. 14)

It is well known that the Aztecs used human sacrifices as a part of their religious activities, in the form of ceremonial cannibalism. Tenochtitlan priests ripped open chests of living victims with flint knives, tore out still beating hearts and ate them. The heads were hung on racks (perhaps the brains were eaten also) and the remainders of the bodies were tumbled down the steep-sided temple steps for the populace to eat. At times one thigh was given to the Supreme Council and other choice cuts to other nobles and then the remainders given to the victim's captor, who took it home and had it cooked into a maize and man stew, to be eaten by all the family. (Ref. 15) A subsidiary nation, Tlaxcalan, may have been preserved simply as a "stockyard" to supply human meat for Aztec raiders1. One possible explanation for the cannibalism, according to Michail Harner2, is that human flesh was the only source of some essential amino-acids needed by man. He explains that there were few or no domesticable herbivores in pre-Columbian Mexico and the poor could neither import game nor get the needed combinations of amino acids in their limited diets, so that cannibalism became their salvation. This is not accepted by the majority of Aztec specialists. (Ref. 16) Some have estimated that 250,000 people were sacrificed each year (Ref. 17), although other authorities say that on the eve of the Spanish conquest, there were only about 50,000 human victims a year. (Ref. 18) Still another estimate has been given by Bart McDowell (Ref. 19), who wrote that after the great Tenochtitlan was dedicated in 1487 between 10,600 and 70,400, depending on the source, were sacrificed with the ritual killings continuing without pause from sun-up to sun-down, four at a time, for four days. At least on some occasions, once captives were killed their bodies were flayed and the skin worn by priests for 20 days. Multiple pictures drawn by Aztec artists, under Spanish supervision, show these skin enrobed priests. (Ref. 20)

Mexican writers tend to indicate that the cannibalism was entirely a religious rite, re-enacting a mythical battle between the God Huitzilopochtli and his sorceress sister, Coyalxauhqui, whom he dismembered. (Ref. 22) Anawalt (Ref. 23) writes that as children of the sun the Aztecs felt a heavy responsibility to keep the sun (representing Hiutzilopochtli in his daily battle) strong, by giving it the most sacred of all foods - human blood. The most common blood offerings were from auto-sacrifice from every man, woman and child, from ear lobes, tongues, extremities, chest or genitals. Human sacrifice, however, was the most holy rite and took place on one or more days of each of the 18 months in the Aztec year. Most of these were captives or specially selected and prepared individuals.

The Aztecs did not have the wheel, but they had an intensive agriculture and probably some 12,000,000 peasants were expected to grow a surplus of some 20,000 tons of food for the city and its trading network. They had inherited techniques for quarrying and moving large blocks of stone, as manifested in their so-called calendar stone, a basalt disk 3.6 meters in diameter, 72 centimeters thick and weighing 24 metric tons. It was quarried with stone hammers and chisels, with wooden wedges inserted into cleavage planes. (Ref. 24, 25)

On the Goodman-Martinez-Thompson correlation dating system used by the National Geographic Society, the Aztecs did not turn on their previous superiors, the Tepehecs, until 1428 and then by 1519 had a tribute empire that covered most of central Mexico and stretched as far as Guatemala. The other dating correlation system is the "Spinden", which makes all Central American dates about 260 years earlier. The problem is not with relative dates in the American scene, which are consistent by the old Mayan calendars, but with relating these to the Christian calendar. A discovery in Vera Cruz in 1972 seems to confirm the former method to be the most accurate. A map will be found under this same section in the next chapter, showing the progression of the Aztec state and its relationship to other Central and South American empires.

The exact population of Mexico before the arrival of the Spaniards is, of course, unknown. Some have given well thought-out estimates as high as 25,000,000. But, as Braudel (Ref. 26) has pointed out, the Indian population of this 15th century suffered a demographic weakness because of the absence of substitute animal milk, a feature which necessitated breast feeding for 3 or 4 years, thus reducing the fertility. This was a factor in the failure of rapid revival of the Indian population after the devastating onslaught of the diseases and firearms of the Spaniards. Outside the Aztec area, Yucatan and the Mayan area of Guatemala were politically divided between petty, rival states. Yucatan continued to remain separate from Mexico until the time of the Mexican revolution.

No reader needs to be reminded that Christopher Columbus reached the Caribbean in 1492, claiming territory for his backer, the Spanish monarchy. All may not know, however, that he had previously sailed far down the coast of Africa and to Iceland and beyond in the north Atlantic, in earlier days. He certainly knew of the presence of Greenland and contrary to some reports, there never was any question about the earth being flat among the sailors of that time. The navigation problem originated, at least in part, from the fact that scientists of the day had accepted Marco Polo's location of Japan as being 1,500 miles off the China coast. This, added to Columbus' adoption of a markedly wrong diameter of the earth, resulted in his assurances throughout his western voyages that he had reached the Indies and was very near China and Japan. On each of his western trips, Columbus rode the Canary Current and the prevailing Atlantic trade-winds. (Ref. 27) On the first, he required 36 days from the Canary Islands to his Caribbean landfall. It is of interest that Curtis and Kathleen Saville made essentially the same trip in a rowboat in 1981 in 50 days. The return trip to Europe, however, cannot be made without going first north with the Gulf Stream, or with power. (Ref. 28, 29)

Columbus' misconception regarding the land he found is worth a little more detail. There are 360 degrees of longitude in the circumference of the earth and we know today that each degree is very close to 60 nautical miles, thus making the perimeter of the globe some 21,600 nautical miles. Erothenes, many centuries before Columbus, had estimated a degree of longitude at 59.5 miles, but Columbus accepted the calculations of a Moslem geographer, Alfragan, who postulated this figure at 56.667 Arabic miles. Columbus further misinterpreted this as the equivalent of 45 western, nautical miles thus making an error of 25%. This, plus his erroneous placement of Japan from the writings of Marco Polo, resulted in great confusion. The Canary Islands are on the same latitude as the southern tip of Japan and that was his reason for leaving from that point. He was unaware, apparently, that it was the Canary Current at that latitude that really allowed him to make the crossing. The true air-line miles from the Canaries to Japan number about 10,600, but Columbus' calculations were that it should be only 2,400. (Ref. 30)

At any rate, the Genoese Columbus, whose Spanish name was Don Cristobal Colon, took off on his first cross-Atlantic voyage with the famous Nina, Pinta and Santa Maria vessels, leaving Spain for the Canaries on August 3, 1492. Rough water had made him take 6 days between Spain and those islands, where the warlike Guanches were only partially conquered but were gradually being reduced to slavery. We know something about his ships. The Nina, about 60 tons3 probably had a 6 feet draught, an overall length of 70 feet, a 23 feet beam and a hold depth amidships of about 9 feet. It was square rigged with a lanteen sail on the mizzen and was provisioned for a year. For the seamen, the chief foods were wine, olive oil and bread in the form of sea biscuits or hard tack. They had some fish, salted meat, legumes and garlic. They sailed by dead reckoning, which means estimating the speed of the ship and then calculating the-distance travelled. Columbus repeatedly tried some celestial navigation but he made bad errors and actually relied almost completely on dead reckoning, at which we was apparently a master. One could not really tell longitude at that time, because there was no reliable maritime clock. The compass was the only fairly dependable instrument and even its variations from the pole star tended to be confusing. Nevertheless, the first crossing was not difficult, running on the trade winds and with the Canary Current, with the best day's run being 174 nautical miles. Columbus landed on the island of San Salvador in the Bahamas. (Ref. 31)

The adventurers immediately encountered Taino Indians, speakers of what was later to be identified as an Arawak language. They used dugout boats, some carrying 40 to 45 men and they used hammocks for sleeping, a trick soon adopted by the Spanish seamen. Deeper on the island many of the Taino were kept captive for eating purposes by the cannibalistic Caribs. Taino boys were castrated and the girls were kept to raise babies, which the Caribs thought to be particularly tasty. (Ref. 32) The Indians went essentially naked, wearing a few trinkets of gold leaf. The latter, of course, greatly excited the Europeans and they sailed through the Bahamas to Hispaniola (Haiti) in pursuit of gold, as well as Japan and the Grand Khan of China. They decided Cuba was the Asiatic mainland and it was there that the Santa Maria went aground. By this time friction had developed among the ships' captains and Columbus and the skipper of the Pinta sailed her away, leaving Columbus with the Nina and the grounded Santa Maria. A fort was built on Cape Haitian Harbor and 39 men were left there while the Admiral and the Nina sailed on January 16, 1493 for Spain, going first north and then east. Again Columbus' attempts at celestial navigation were somewhat ludicrous, but with luck and dead reckoning he hit the Azores and finally, after some trouble with the Portuguese there, he went on to Lisbon in a storm. All thought that they had found Asiatic islands. (Ref. 33, 34)

The follow-up to the discovery voyage of Columbus is not so well known. Queen Isabella sent him back to the Indies in September of 1493, with 1,500 men in a fleet of 17 ships, with the declared prime object of conversion of the Indians to Christianity and a second object of establishing a trading colony, with Columbus as governor. The ships sailed through the smaller leeward islands to Porto Rico and finally to Haiti, where it was found that the men left there on the previous voyage were dead. The first battle with Indians took place on St. Croix Island on November 13th. Columbus was able to take some of these vicious, cannibalistic Caribs as prisoners and made them slaves. Then he explored southern Cuba, which he thought was part of China, and/or islands of Malay and then he went on to Jamaica. On this voyage he established another colony on Haiti, but his men, who had no women on their ships from Spain, raped, robbed and enslaved the Indians. Fray Buil, who had been sent as the Christian priest, participated in the Indian enslavement and Columbus, himself, eventually returned with some 500 Indians for the slave markets of Seville, when he got home again in the spring of 1496. Colonists who were left in the Caribbean built the city of Santo Domingo in 1496 or 1497, as the first American urban community. (Ref. 35, 36) It has been estimated that the total population of Hispaniola (Haiti) in 1496 was 4,000,000, chiefly Indians, of course. (Ref. 37)

Since the Spanish royalty was not too happy with the paucity of gold and silver brought back from the New World after 2 trips, Columbus had real difficulty in arranging his third. Finally in 1498 he sailed again, to land in Trinidad and Venezuela on the South American coast. Another fleet supposedly went directly to provision the colony on Santa Domingo. In Venezuela the men did find guanin or tumbaga, an alloy of gold, silver and copper, with the amount of gold varying from 9 to 89% and the copper from 11 to 74%. They also found more cannibalistic Caribs and big fighting-canoes, with cabins amidships, which may have been factors in making the Spaniards just miss an area of great pearl fisheries. Returning to Santo Domingo, Columbus found 160 of the European colony (20 to 30% of the total) ill with syphilis. The natives had been shamefully exploited, the provision fleet hadn't arrived and some mutineers had been hanged. Francisco de Bobadilla, who had been sent to the island by the Spanish monarchs as Chief Justice, blamed Columbus for the various problems, arrested him and had him returned to Spain in chains. The year was 1500.

This section would not be complete without further comment concerning the much debated question of the origin of syphilis. Morison (Ref. 38) states that there is abundant evidence of syphilis occurring in a mild, endemic form in the pre-Columbian American Indians, but it was not until after the arrival of Columbus' sailors that the disease became rampant on both continents. For whatever reason, the interaction of the European men and the Indians made the disease violent on both sides of the Atlantic.

SOUTH AMERICA (See map in the next module)

NORTHERN AND WESTERN SOUTH AMERICA

There were many different Indian peoples in this part of South America. Of the Andean groups the great Inca Empire was dominant, but there were also the northern Caribs, Caraja, Mundurcu and the Savana-Orinoco group, among others. Sometime in the era just before the dominance of the Incas, the Chimu kingdom deteriorated markedly, perhaps because their farmland had been over-irrigated and insufficiently drained and had become salinized. The lowlands of coastal Peru were, and are, saturated with salt and to be useful the land must be excellently drained and well flushed. Deforestation also resulted in a dessication so that the underground rivers, so important for the low lying savannahs, began to disappear. Today the ruins of Chan cover an area of 14 square miles, with 10 surviving walled compounds (fortresses) forming the heart of the city.

The Peruvian Incas subdued the coastal Chimu civilization early in the century, although as we have seen, it may already have been in decline. It was in the reigns of the 8th emperor, Viracocha, and his son Pachuciti and grandson Topa that the Incas expanded out of their original Cuzco region and soon had an empire 200 by 2,000 miles in area with a population of perhaps 10,000,000. Engel (Ref. 39) writes that only when Prince Pachacuti mounted the throne in A.D. 1438, does tradition become reliable and concomitant with provable fact. Everything prior to that is summed up in a bunch of names that may have very little true value. It is probable that in the time of Viracocha, the so-called empire was still restricted to the narrow Cuzco Valley, in an area of a few thousand acres, surrounded by hostile neighbors. The sudden blossoming and conquering of territory then matches that of Alexander the Great or of the great, ancient Persian kings. The word "Inca" does not imply a race; it belongs only to a dynasty and the system that dynasty imposed on a number of South American peoples. The entire imperial expansion lasted only 100 years, but due to the deportation of conquered peoples and the planting of garrisons, the Incas made their Quechua language into the "lingua franca" of the Andes and it remains so today, even 4 centuries after the competing Spanish language appeared. (Ref. 40, 41)

There have been millions of words written about the Inca civilization. In this outline we can only hope to summarize some of the more important and interesting features. Inca governors subdivided the entire population into groups of 10 persons4 and were thus able to control activities of every farmer and craftsman. All the people lived in small villages, but there was a system of post and military roads and coastal navigation was well advanced. Agriculture was extensive, with a complex pattern of irrigation and terracing. Art, architecture and metal working were all well developed. They had a calendar and advanced surgical techniques. The famous royal highway of the Incas incorporated the earlier Moche roads into a 6,000 mile network, one road connecting Quito in the north to Cuzco in the center and eventually down to the Maule River in Chile. Another coast road ran absolutely straight for miles on end. These roads averaged 20 feet in width, were of ten paved with stone or cut through rock and many deep chasms were bridged. Nothing in Europe compared to these roads from the time of the Romans until the era of Napoleon. (Ref. 42, 43)

The Incas had a number of effective plant medications, including quinine from cinchona bark for malaria, coca, containing cocaine for both tranquilizing and stimulation, as well as atropine, ipecacuana, curare, theophyllin and various mind-altering plants such as peyotl, teonancatl and ololiuqu. Surgery was usually a separate profession. Skulls were trepanned, but whether this was for medicinal, religious or other reasons is not known. (Ref. 44)

Inca-style jars, with black on cream decorations and lines forming grids are called aryballoses and are identical with some in a French museum made by north African Berbers. There appears to have been no local precursor to Inca pottery. Even at Cuzco, shards of Inca pottery lie above fragments of an entirely different, un-related style. No pottery earlier than the Incas has been found either in Machu Picchu, Ollantaytambo or in Chinchero, where there were most imposing complexes. In other places, deep to the layers of Inca pottery, one finds the Killki type, which Engel (Ref. 46) states to be in no way related to the Incas'. To quote Engel directly concerning the Killki:

"The 'keros' or hardwood flaring vessels with flat bottoms and polychrome decorations, are supposedly associated with Inca times. There is an astonishing collection of them, and it is really regrettable- that almost nothing has been published regarding these archaeological treasures. The shape of the keros is clearly Tiahuanacoid, however, and the many-colored decorations ornamenting them indicate that many of them, if not all, belong to the period of protohistorical transition. Flowers, European costumes, or African faces are depicted on them. I do not think these keros constitute an element very typical of the final pre-Columbian period."5

A further confusing fact is that the Inca construction technique of using enormous polyhedral blocks without mortar appeared abruptly in this 15th century and the only comparable architecture is in far away Polynesia in the Marquesas Islands. One of the Inca cities, Ollantaytambo, has an adjacent terrace rising 300 feet high, with stairways too steep for horses to climb. On a crest above are enormous carved, monolithic slabs weighing over 100 tons each and there is no way of knowing whether these were raised there under the direction of the Tiahuanacos or the Incas. Their size and the difficulty of emplacement rivals both Stonehenge and the temples of Egypt. (Ref. 48) By 1471 the Incas had pushed south into Chile and northern Argentina, while after 1493 the new emperor Huayna Capac concentrated on the north, founding Quito in modern Ecuador as a northern capital. His sons, however, fought bitter civil war, dividing the northern and southern parts of the empire.

Along the western frontier of what is now Argentina, lived the Chiriguanos, a Guaranis tribe with Caribbean customs, who had settled in the lower Andes in pretohistoric times. Finally they conquered all the lower Andes from the Bermejo River to Santa Cruz in the north. It is known historically that several tens of thousands of them made trips of over 600 miles and were a permanent menace to cities like Cuzco and Machu Picchu because of their penchant for the women, salt, wool and metal objects of those centers. Other tribes dotted the whole northern and western South American areas - the peaceable Arawaks, the Chiquitos, who used curare-poisoned arrows, the Mojos, the Yuracares, the Mosotenes and the Chimanes and many more in far flung regions where they remain in a primitive state today. Some paid tribute to the Incas, some fought. (Ref. 49)

Much of the original capital city at Cuzco, on the eastern slope of the Peruvian Andes at just over 11,000 feet altitude, has been excavated, including the famed Inca Shrine and the Temple of the Sun, the walls of which were faced with gold plates. The Inca rulers were absolute despots, taking 2/3 of each conquered peasant's harvest. In the south both Pachacuti and Topa Yupanqui had difficult campaigns to subdue the Collaos, which although desolate now, must have been one of the most densely populated areas of the Andes at that time. This opened the way to the eastern slopes and to Bolivia and from there Topa subdued the Diaguites of Chile, down to the edge of Araucanian territory. The area of Collaos had huge stone storehouses and silos, each capable of containing tons of grain. By the end of the century the empire covered 37 degrees of latitude. (Ref. 50, 51)

EASTERN AND CENTRAL SOUTH AMERICA

There were as many and varied peoples in eastern South America as in the Andes. There were various forest groups and in the south the Puelche, Charrua and the Mataco stone-age people. No one knows for certain the date of arrival or the origin of the aborigines of Brazil, but many recognize what appears to be a common cradle in southeast Asia. The tropical Malays and the jungle Brazilians have a striking physical analogy and many common cultural elements, such as the poisonous blow pipe. Such jungle equipment could certainly not have survived the barren arctic tundra and very possibly indicates an involuntary passage along the Urdaneta (Japanese) Current and down the American coast, or even more reasonable, although unprovable, a migration of Malaysians across the Indian Ocean west to Madagascar, then to the tip of South Africa and then, riding the southern Atlantic current, to Brazil. (Ref. 52) Most of the eastern South American Indians, particularly those of Brazil, were cannibals, with the dominant tribes often fattening their victims like cattle before the kill. The victims' lard was collected in buckets and a portion of the meat was smoked and hung, as fish or other animal flesh is preserved.

Enemies appear to have been barbecued. In Tannahill's book Food in History (Ref. 53) on page 266 there is a gruesome picture depicting this, with the title, "Comment les sauvages rotissent leurs ennemis."6 The picture shows an arm on a barbecue frame over a fire, a human body on the floor with the head just chopped off and another person apparently in the act of eviscerating this victim. Some children have a man's head and two men seem to be holding a human thigh in the background. At home these warrior-farmers lived in the nude, their bodies painted. Their houses had thatched roofs made of laths from long bamboos cut with a stone axe. They used bows, harpoons and boats. Manioc and corn were grown in clearings made by burning trees and they of ten had to move to be near fresh water.

The name "Brazil" was taken from the brazilwood trees found there. It seems probable that Portuguese fishermen knew of the existence, not only of the Azores, but also the coast of Brazil long before the time of Columbus and certain customs in both Brazilian and Argentinian Indians are compatible with an African connection, also. (Ref. 54) In 1500, the same year in which Columbus was taken back to Spain in chains from his third trip to the Caribbean, the Portuguese Admiral Pedro Alvares Cabral landed in Brazil.

Actually he had been headed for India via Cape of Good Hope from the Cape Verde Islands, with 13 caravels, when contrary winds had driven him westward. He took possession of Brazil in the name of Manoel I, of Portugal. (Ref. 55)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [189] SCHLEDERMANN, PETER, "Eskimo and Viking Finds in the High Arctic", National Geographic 159: 575-602, May 1981.

5 [93] HESS, BILL, "The White Mountain Apache: Seeking the Best of Two Worlds", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

6 [206] STILLMAN EDMUND AND EDITORS OF LIFE, The Balkans. (Time, Inc., New York, 1964).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

8 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

9 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

10 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

11 [269] McQUIRE, RANDALL AND SCHIFFER, MICHAEL B., "On the Threshold of Civilization: The Hohokam of Arizona", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 22-29, Sept./Oct. 1982.

12 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

13 [290] CASEY, HARRY, "Desert Intaglios", Science 83, Apr. 1983, pp. 50-54.

14 [138] McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

15 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

16 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

17 [129] MARINATOS, SPYRIDON, "Thera, Key to the Riddle of Minos", National Geographic 141: No. 5, page 702, May, 1972.

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

19 [138] McDOWELL, BART, "The Aztecs", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

20 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

21 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

22 [148] MOCTEZUMA, EDUARDO MATOS, "New Finds in the Great Temple", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

23 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

24 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

25 [149] MOLINA MONTEZ, Augusto F., "The Building of Tenochtitlan", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

26 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

27 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

28 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

29 [188] SAVILLE, CURTIS & KATHLEEN, "They row, row, row their boat across the Atlantic Ocean", Smithsonian, Oct. 1981, pp. 192-215.

30 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

31 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

32 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

33 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

34 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

35 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

36 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

37 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

38 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

39 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

40 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

41 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

42 [221] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., Change and Habit. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1966).

43 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

44 [10] BELCHER, TAYLOR AND EDIE, "Great Golden Art of the Ancient Peruvian Artisans", Smithsonian 8:841, Dec. 1977.

45 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

46 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

47 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

58 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

49 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

50 [10] BELCHER, TAYLOR AND EDIE, "Great Golden Art of the Ancient Peruvian Artisans", Smithsonian 8:841, Dec. 1977.

51 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

52 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

53 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

54 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

55 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

1.  Anawalt (Ref. 21) says there is no proof of this concept. The vassal provinces did pay tribute, but probably not in humans for sacrifice.

2.  As noted by James K. Page, Jr. in "Smithsonian" 8: 24-28, June, 1977. He referred to Harner's remarks in "Natural History", Vol. 86, No. 4.

3.  In this instance the word "ton" as applied to the size of a ship has been taken from the Castilian tonelada and the Portuguese tonel, meaning a tun of wine, which is a large cask equivalent in volume to 2 pipes (hogsheads) or roughly equal to 40 cubic feet. This later became a unit of capacity for English vessels and has nothing to do with weight. (Ref. 32).

4.  This is reminiscent of the organization of the Mongol armies.

5.  This quotation is from Engel (Ref. 47), pages 206 and 207. The underlining is mine. All of this brings up the mysterious possibility of pre-Columbian European visits, again.

6.  Tannahill reports that the picture was taken originally from I a Cosmographie Universelle, Vol. 2, Paris, 1,575.

America: A.D. 1501 to 1600

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

It was mentioned earlier in this chapter that this century has been called the "Little Ice Age" because of an overall drop in temperature. Although the Thule Arctic Culture was probably little affected, the arctic glacier now extended well down on Greenland, destroying the agricultural base there, which had helped to support neighboring Iceland. (Ref. 1)

Only 12 years after Columbus' first voyage to America, Breton fishermen were working the cod banks off Nova Scotia and soon were on the mainland, trading with the Indians for furs. Gaspar Corte-Real had discovered Newfoundland for Portugal and the French explorers Verrazano and Cartier initiated the "French Kingdoms of the North" to give needed revenues for the luxuries of the court of young Francois I. Giovanni de Verrazano (actually a Genoese) sailed all up the coast from Chesapeake Bay to the Strait of Belle Isle. Jacques Cartier followed in 1534, named the St. Lawrence River and then tried for a sea route to Asia, finding only auks, cod, herring, wolf fish, wapiti, elks, beaver and even a polar bear. Scurvy became rampant among his Frenchmen and the Hurons with whom they dealt. After that period for 50 years there were only trappers and traders, with trading posts at Quebec and Montreal. The name "Canada" is an Indian word meaning "village". (Ref. 2, 3, 4, 5)

THE UNITED STATES (See map on page 1009)

By 1600 there were probably 1,000,000 Indians, speaking some 2,000 languages, in the United States. (Ref. 6) New York state and the lower Great Lakes region were the lands of the Iroquois. Their village sites were built away from waterways and were sometimes fortified. They farmed maize and possibly beans and squash and hunted. Pottery was used for cooking and storing tobacco for their pipes. (Ref. 7) In 1845 settlers near Onandaga, not far from Lake Ontario, found a stone which was inscribed "Leo VI 1520" and this may indicate a Norse settlement proscribed by the then Pope Leo VI, some 14 years before the arrival of Jacques Cartier. (Ref. (Reference)) In 1584 Sir Walter Raleigh sent Amandes and Barlow to found a colony at Raleigh, Virginia, but it was subsequently lost, as were two following attempts in 1587 and 1589 by John White on Roanoke Island.

The century ended without even a trading post belonging to Britain in the New World. (Ref. 8)

Although there were the limited French and English efforts just mentioned, Spain owned America in this 16th century, as far as Europeans were concerned. After the Caribbean was ravaged by the dregs of Spanish civilization, as we shall note in the next section, it was the turn of the Gulf Coast of the United States. A first expedition, led by Ponce de Leon (who had been on Columbus' second trip), landed in Florida in 1513 claiming that region for Spain. In the 16th century "Florida" meant the entire area of present day Florida, Georgia, Virginia, Alabama, Mississippi and possibly more. Ponce may not have been the first Spaniard in Florida, as one early writer says that when- Ponce arrived at Charlotte Harbor on the Gulf side, a Spanish-speaking Indian greeted him. This native, however, may have escaped from a passing Spanish ship or come from the Antilles on his own.

Archeological and linguistic evidence discloses numerous pre-Columbian contacts between these two places. In spite of all the stories in children's histories about Ponce de Leon's trip to "find the fountain of youth", he really sailed to Florida to capture slaves and find precious metals, if available. He was authorized to make war on the Lucayhos aborigines, if necessary. Florida was erroneously regarded as just another island and the term Lucayos (or Bimini) frequently included Florida. On his first voyage, Ponce was not very successful, obtaining little more than a handful of Indians, some of whom he trained as interpreters, but when he returned in 1521 he opened war against the Caluysa and they killed him. (Ref. 9)

There were apparently many shipwrecks of European vessels along the southern coasts in the 16th century - some say 10,000 - and the Southeastern Ceremonial Complex of Indians began to use the silver coins and jewelry for their own pendants, gorgets and beads. All of this means that the Algonquians, Siouans, Muskhogeans and Iroquoians living by the ocean knew a great deal about the Europeans before they actually landed. In 1520 Lucas Vasquez de Ayllon commissioned Francisco Gordillo to sail to the northerly part of La Florida and he did so, going clear up to Chesapeake Bay, even making a short exploratory inland trip in the vicinity of Pawley's Island. After some other explorations by subordinates, Ayllon himself set forth in 1526 with 7 ships, 500 men, 100 women and Negroes, 89 horses and interpreters to settle in the region of the Cape Fear River or the Santee River. The enterprise did not prosper as one provision ship wrecked and sank and Ayllon died after an extended sickness. The remaining people relocated farther south near the future George- town, Carolina, where most died of disease, drowning or Indian warfare. A few remnants returned to Hispaniola. A little later Narvaez landed in the vicinity of Tampa Bay and detected gold among the natives' possessions. They claimed it had been obtained in Apalachee, a province in the north. Certainly there was gold in the Appalachian Mountains, but whether the Indians had mined it in truth or obtained the gold from shipwrecks or from Mexico, is not known. Narvaez searched for the source but was unsuccessful. – The only survivors of this expedition were Cabeza de Vaca, the black Moor slave, Esteban and a few others. The first two and one other wandered for 8 years across the southern United States, including Texas, Arizona and New Mexico to the area inhabited by the Pima Indians, finally reaching Mexico City. (Ref. 10, 11)

Leaving Spain in 1538, Hernando de Soto landed in the vicinity of present day Tampa Bay in 1539 following Narvaez' trail with 600 men and more than 200 horses. He went up the peninsula, wintered in Apalachee, then struck out northward to Cofitachiqui, west- ward to present day Alabama and across the Mississippi into Arkansas before finally dying and being buried in the Mississippi River. On his travels he visited the Queen of the powerful Coitachiqui Chiefdom, occupying a central position in present day South Carolina, and was impressed by the numerous houses, large mounds and the grand wooden mat-covered temple. The queen and her court wore long pearl necklaces - those in her possession reputedly weighing all together some thousands of pounds. Her warriors had copper-tipped pikes, maces, battle axes and perhaps 50,000 bows and quivers. The Cofitachiqui language is unknown. Supposedly Cofitachique contained at least 500 houses, as did Caxa in Alabama and Ocale in Florida. All was not sweetness and light, however, as the Spanish say that an army of 10,000 Timucuans contested De Soto's trip through Florida and up to 7,000 warriors assaulted him in Mabila. But de Soto and his Spaniards brought small-pox, measles, tuberculosis, chicken-pox, scarlet fever, typhus, influenza, whooping cough and the common cold so that within a few decades the southeast became markedly depopulated and the economic and political structure of Mississippian life collapsed permanently. Furthermore, the Caluyas and the Cofitachiqui may already have been depleted and some settlements abandoned before De Soto arrived as a result of the migration of infected survivors from a great 1530 plague in Mexico City. (Ref. 12, 13) Thus, before proceeding with a further description of the Spanish invasion, a few more words about the southeastern Indians prior to the advent of Spanish explorers seems advisable.

All southern Indians were essentially farmers and maize was the staff of life. Farming techniques had progressed far beyond any primitive slash and burn type of agriculture. The impression for years has been that the squaws did most of the work, but this is not correct. These Indians lived chiefly in towns and had their fields in the countryside. While women may have attended small garden plots, men did much of the work in the principal fields, clearing them, girdling large trees with stone axes and knives and fire, disposing of stumps, breaking the ground with hoes consisting of wooden handles with stone, conch shells or large animal bones at the ends. The maize was grown quite scientifically, planted at stated intervals in hills. As growth occurred, more dirt was piled up around the hill, keeping down weeds, trapping moisture and ensuring a higher yield. A Timucuan practice in Florida was to plant one crop of maize in the early spring and another in the summer on the same ground. It was also possible to grow dent, sweet, pop and other varieties of corn, which matured at different intervals. Although secondary in importance, hunting and gathering did occur. Deer were important, not only for food but for skins, and bears were hunted particularly for their oil, as well as fur and meat. It is not known whether maize was brought up from Meso-America overland via Texas or by sea through the West Indies. (Ref. 14)

It was in the Virginia and Carolina Tidewater area where mixing of the northern hunting-oriented culture with the southern maize-agrarian civilization can best be documented. The Algonquians, originally spread over Canada, were late arrivals in the Tidewater, becoming in part, the Powhatan Confederacy in Virginia and Pamlico and Machapunga of eastern North Carolina. A feature conspicuously absent in the Tidewater was the temple platform mound. Other Algonquians were the Roanoke, Croatoan and Chowanoc. At the time of white contact there were powerful chiefdoms which might almost be called empires all over the south and southeast, including the Cofitachiqui, Powhatan, Natchez and Calyusa. When the Natchez Sun died, his subjects staged an elaborate funeral which included immolation of his wives. Nearer the east coast local natives had had extensive contact with Europeans for generation before Raleigh's Roanoke fiasco, some from Spanish land contact, such as with Ayllon and otherwise with ships either wrecked or coming ashore for provisions.

In spite of their early failures, Spain did not give up. Tristan de Luna took 1,500 men, women and black slaves to try 2 settlements, one at Pensacola and the other at Saint Elena (Port Royal). Lack of supplies, disease, internal bickering and native hostility again defeated the expectations. St. Augustine was founded by Menendez with more than 1,000 soldiers, farmers, artisans, their wives and Negroes in 1565. At first it was really a military base from which to attack the thousand or so French Huguenots, who had fortified Ft. Caroline just north on the St. Johns River. After these French were finally expelled, St. Augustine, with only a mediocre harbor and sandy, relatively unproductive soil, declined in significance. But from St. Elena, founded in South Caroline in about 1566 on the site of present day Parris Island Marine Corps base, soldiers and missionaries trekked into the interior, planting at least five garrisons in the Carolina back country and on the western side of the mountains. For 6 years a Father Sebastian Montero lived among the pagans, teaching them Spanish and the rudiments of Christianity. St. Elena existed for about 21 years and once had about 400 people in some 60 houses. (Ref. 15, 16)

St. Augustine was burned in 1586 by the English privateer, Sir Francis Drake and he also made an unsuccessful attempt to destroy Santa Elena. He then stopped by Roanoke Island and picked up some of Raleigh's distressed soldiers. The few colonists who remained had either been killed or absorbed by the Indians, when a relief ship finally arrived in 1590.

The Indians bartered skins and furs with the whites. Chief Powhatan reportedly had 4,000 deerskins in a single wardrobe. But the whites took many of the natives captives – Ayllon and DeSoto counting their take in the hundreds. (Ref. 17)

In the southwest, Texas had been claimed for Spain by Alvarez de Pineda in 1519 and by the 1520s large quantities of horses, cattle and sheep had been brought into New Mexico. In the area of that state and Arizona, there were at that time about 40,000 Pueblo Indians. At about the same time that De Soto landed in Florida, Francisco Vasquez de Coronado had Friar Fray Marcos start north from Mexico on an exploration of what is now New Mexico. He used Esteban, the Moor who had wandered previously from Florida to New Spain, as a guide. Esteban's black color was accepted as a novelty by the Indians and some even thought he was a god. In the following year Coronado himself led an expedition searching for the "Seven Cities of Gold", reaching just south of Sante Fe and then back into the Texas Panhandle and on to the region of Independence, Kansas and the Nebraska border. He had 250 horsemen, 70 Spanish soldiers, 1,000 friendly Mexican Indians, baggage animals, sheep, goats and a train of priests. Others of the original party went around the north end of the Gulf of California and followed the Colorado River up to the Grand Canyon. On his way back to Mexico Coronado viciously attacked the Acoma1 Indian city about 40 miles west of present day Albuquerque, in spite of the pope's edict about humane treatment of the Indians, and in 3 days and nights the Spanish killed 600

Acomas and imprisoned and enslaved that many more. But Spaniards fell, too, and Coronado returned with only 1/3 of his original 300 plus white men. That Acoma pueblo, originally built by Kersan Indians on top of a rock mesa with edifices 3 stories high, was already ancient and may have been the oldest inhabited site in the United States. In spite of that bloody fight, those Acomas were converted to Christianity some 30 years later by a barefoot and unarmed Franciscan priest, Father Ramirez. (Ref. 19, 20, 21, 22)

Beginning in 1596 Juan de Onate took an expedition from Mexico City to El Paso and then to Sante Fe and on to Quivera, Kansas and then returned via California, at the top of the Gulf. This was followed in 1598 by the arrival in the New Mexico area by 400 Spanish men, women and children with their 80 wagons and 7,000 head of live stock. Some 3,000 sheep were included. (Ref. 23, 24) In the far west an Englishman did upstage the Spaniards, as Sir Francis Drake anchored in 1579 just north of San Francisco Bay, claiming the land for his queen, calling it Nova Albion (New England). (Ref. 25)2

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

In 1513 Nunez de Balboa crossed the Isthmus of Panama and became the first known European to view the Pacific Ocean. Although by the end of the 15th century the Aztec Empire had passed its zenith, in 1519 there were still 60,000 households in Tenochtitlan and the population of the empire has been estimated to have been about 5,000,000 with 25,000,000 to 30,000,000 overall in Mexico. Both Mexico and Peru (as we shall see later) were very densely settled. The two American foods - maize and potatoes – were higher in caloric value than any old world crops except rice and this allowed a denser population per square mile than anyplace outside the East Asian rice-paddy region. Maize alone leads to niacin deficiency and the disease, pellagra, but middle American Indians soaked maize in a lime solution that broke down the molecules to make "hominy grits" and allowed human digestion to synthesize the needed vitamin. In some areas the native tomatoes were cultivated and eaten also and this further supplied the otherwise missing vitamins. It is of interest that in the New World, pellagra became known as "Columbus' sickness". But even before the Spaniards came, soil erosion in Mexico was already becoming a problem.

The Aztecs ate chiefly tortillas. Beans supplied some protein, the tomato (originally a weed in the maize fields) supplied vitamins A and C. They occasionally had wild game and raised small dogs for eating. This dog and the turkey were their only domesticated livestock. They also ate tadpoles, water flies' larvae, white worms, frogs, fresh water shrimp, newts, winged ants, agave worms (Maguey slug) and the iguana. We have mentioned in the last chapter that they were also somewhat prone to eat human flesh. Throughout the Caribbean people ate large, fat spiders and plump insects from decaying wood. Manioc was a Cuban poisonous plant, but properly prepared it was edible. The roots were peeled and grated and the juice squeezed out and subsequently boiled to make a harmless sauce, with the residual sediment making tapioca. The pulp was sieved and shaped into flat cakes, cooked slowly to make a soft, flexible bread called "cassava". When dried, it could be kept 2 or 3 years. The manioc root, itself, although protein deficient, was not eaten by locusts and could be left in the earth as long as 2 years, without deteriorating. (Ref. 26)

NOTE: Insert Map 56. The Aztec, Maya and Inca Empires

Columbus and those who followed started a great exchange of foods. From Europe to the New World came wheat, chick-peas, sugarcane, some vegetables and cows. Back to Europe went maize (soon a staple in northern Spain, Portugal and Italy), potatoes (a source of vitamin C), chocolate, peanuts, vanilla, tomatoes, pineapples, lima beans, scarlet runner, red peppers, green peppers, tapioca and the turkey. (Ref. 27) In Mexico the climate favored the growth of many medicinal plants which were used by Aztec doctors. Among these were narcotics, medications for abortion, diarrhea, skin diseases and fever. It is interesting that the Spanish soldiers, after their arrival, of ten preferred the Aztec physicians to their European educated ones and in the latter part of the century Philip II sent one of his physicians, Francisco Hernandez, to Mexico to study native medicine and make a catalog of medicinal plants. (Ref. 28) We insert parenthetically the fact that the great majority of the Spanish troops were simple men, merely fleeing the poverty of Europe. No important Spanish family took any interest financially, militarily or intellectually in the conquest of the Americas. (Ref. 29)

Every school child knows how the Aztecs, under King Montezuma, were brutally conquered by Hernando Cortez and his handful of Spanish soldiers, in 1521. What is not always realized is that initially the Indians of Mexico welcomed the white, bearded strangers and it is thought by some that the Europeans were considered to be gods, returning as prophesied in some of their ancient legends. At any rate, Cortez landed his ships in the Vera Cruz area, where there were both Huastecs, who spoke a dialect of Maya and the Totonacs, who were vassals of the Aztecs. The former were famous for unusual stone sculptures and may have invented Quetzalcoatl, who became a primary god of the entire region. When Cortez decided to attack the Aztecs after 5 months of reconnoitering, the rebellious Totanacs joined him. (Ref. 30, 31, 32) The numerous Christian friars and priests, who had accompanied Cortez, learning of the Aztec human sacrifices, were adamant in the necessity to chastise and then baptize the heathen Indians. With his Indian mercenaries, picked up along the way, Cortez marched inland toward the capital city. A relief expedition from Hispaniola in 1520 brought small-pox which spread ahead of the Spaniards through the Indian population. It was thus that the disease was raging in Tenochtitlan when Montezuma was killed by his own rivals, who did not want to surrender to the Spaniards. The new leader and many of his followers died within hours of the small-pox, which spread even to Guatemala in the same year. (Ref. 33). Mc Neill (Ref. 34) con firms that smallpox and measles, brought by Europeans, killed millions of native Americans and had more to do with the collapse of the Aztec power than merely military operations. The population of Mexico dropped from a probable 25,000,000 to 30,000,000 to 3 million by 1568. (Ref. 35)

Of course the Aztecs and the immediately adjacent tribes were not the only native inhabitants of Mexico. In the far south Chol-speaking Maya Indians hunted the Chiapas jungle with bows and arrows and incidentally probably encountered many of the old abandoned stone cities of their classic ancestors. The Spanish practically annihilated those people, however, leaving the Chiapas rain-forest essentially vacant. (Ref. 36)

Within two decades of their first landing in Mexico, the relatively few Spaniards had explored the New World from the Atlantic to the Pacific and from Kansas to Argentina. Is there any reason to think that previous sailors landing on the Gulf end of the Canary current could not have done the same? (See Chapter 5). The old Mayan Culture had long gone, but some of the remains were found in Yucatan as early as 1517 by Hernando de Cordova, whose landing party at Cape Cotoche was ambushed by Indians. He was attacked again in Champoton where 62 men were killed and many wounded, so that one ship had to be abandoned because of shortage of crew. In 1526 Don Francisco de Montego was given license to conquer and people the "islands" of Yucatan and Cozumel and to take or buy Indians as slaves. In one battle in this hot, dry land, 1,200 Indians were slaughtered and at Chichen Itza a second great battle resulted in the loss of 150 Spaniards and the wounding of almost all the rest. By 1535, not a single Spaniard remained in Yucatan. When some returned in 1537, many were sacrificed and eaten, but eventually in 1540 the Spanish town of San Francisco de Campeche was founded. (Ref. 37) Perhaps some of these Indians were descendants of the ancient Maya, Yucatec-speaking families, using bows and arrows, were living in the rain forests of Guatemala at that time. (Ref. 38)

Year by year the map of the New World was charted in gold, silver and blood. Quickly the Spaniards superimposed their own civilization and by 1539 there was a printing press and by 1551 a university in Mexico City. By mid-century some 20,000 Negroes had been brought to Cuernavaca and Vera Cruz. There were productive silver mines in Mexico by the 1540s. Thomas (Ref. 39) says that while the Spaniards conquered Central and South America on horses, mules sustained the conquest. Convoys carrying gold and silver and linking Lima, Cuzco, Panama, Vera Cruz and Mexico were established with these valuable animals. The great harbor at Porto Bello, Panama, became the most thriving town in the Americas as the Atlantic terminal of the mule track across the isthmus carrying the Spaniards' treasure from South America. (Ref. 40, 41, 42, 43)1

1 Lempira was a great Indian leader, who fought against the Spanish conquest for two years in Honduras, beginning in 1537. Trujillo, on the Honduras Caribbean coast, was an early Spanish stronghold, with a massive brick fortress with the cannon pointed seaward. (Ref. 44)

Some of the relative values of things in Central America may be seen in Braudel's (Ref. 45) comments about Panama in 1519. A horse was worth 24 1/2 pesos, an Indian slave 30 pesos and a skin of wine 100 pesos. Pedro de Alvarado, who had become governor of Guatemala, heard of rich lands in Peru and led an expedition of 500 men to Quito in 1534, by boat. It is probably an indication of the long time, extensive maritime experience of the people of that area that Alvarado's Indian navigator carried him directly from the Port of Iztopa (near present San Jose, Guatemala) to the Bay of Manta in Ecuador. That was a trip across open ocean of about 1,300 miles, minimum. Land travel, however, would have been at least 1,900 miles, not considering the ups and downs in the mountains, lake detours and the like through mountainous jungles that were actually probably almost impassable. (Ref. 46)

The situation in the Caribbean Basin in this century deserves further discussion. By 1501 Spanish settlers in Hispaniola (Santa Domingo) had already introduced black slaves, the first in the New World. While Columbus was kept in the Spanish court, still under the cloud from his 3rd voyage, Amerigo Vespucci returned from the west Atlantic, proclaiming that there was an entire continent there, a fact which resulted eventually in its being named after him. Columbus was finally allowed a 4th trip, although refused permission to visit his old Santo Domingo domain. He had 150 men in 4 ships and they made the Atlantic crossing on the trade winds, landing on an island just south of Dominica in 21 days3. About 2 weeks later he sent a warning to a large Spanish fleet carrying gold that they should not leave the port of Santo Domingo because of an approaching hurricane. The fleet commander laughed at the warning and started for Spain, only to have his flagship go down and his fleet scattered by the storm. 200,000 castellanos of gold went to the bottom of the Gulf. Columbus' squadron, anchored in a protected area, escaped damage the first night, but did receive some battering the next day.

Columbus initiated further explorations among the Caribbean islands. At Bonacca he intercepted natives in a large, 8 feet wide dugout canoe, carrying 25 men and numerous women and children - all wearing dyed cotton coverings and shirts. The women had colored shawls and the men carried long, flint-edged, wooden swords and copper hatchets. It has since become obvious that these Indians were trading between Bonocca and Honduras. The fleet went on to the mainland, anchoring in a harbor where later the city of Trujillo, Honduras was to be founded and there encountered the Jicaque Indians, dressed as those he had seen in the canoe. This was apparently the remnant of a Mayan Honduran kingdom.

The fleet then sailed south along the coast of Central America, encountering terrible storms, with Columbus quite ill and eventually they passed present day Nicaragua and Costa Rica, where they anchored and traded some with the Talamanca Indians. The Spaniards were impressed with the local fauna, which included deer, pumas and wild turkey. On farther south in Panama they encountered Guaymies Indians, who painted their faces white, black and red and these men even had some real gold. The possibility of mines in that region enticed Columbus into starting a settlement there. When 10 or 12 houses had been built, it stopped raining and the river mouth, where the caravels had been anchored, dried up to the point where the ships were stranded. This was followed by savage Indian attacks which eventually resulted in the loss of 10 men and abandonment of the village. When the rains returned the little fleet took off again for Hispaniola, abandoning one ship, which had been afloat for a year. Two more vessels were leaking badly and when Jamaica was finally reached these were intentionally run aground for the remaining 116 men to use as houseboats, as they were no - longer seaworthy. Two dugout canoes were sent to Santo Domingo for help from Columbus' old enemy, Governor Ovando; half of the remaining men mutinied and tried to leave; the Jamaican Indians quit feeding the Spaniards and relented only when Columbus awed them by predicting the eclipse of the moon of February 29, 1504. The mutineers were finally defeated and- ultimately, after more than a year, all were rescued by a ship from Santo Domingo. Part of the rescued men stayed in the Caribbean to eventually help to settle Puerto Rico, while the others returned to Spain with Columbus. The old Spanish queen was dying and Columbus received no glory.

We have already noted the decimation provoked in the West Indies by small-pox in 1519. Some type of plague, perhaps typhus or influenza, hit the islands again in 1567 with some becoming completely depopulated. (Ref. 48) Early in the century the Spanish abducted the native Arawak Indians from the Bahamas for slave labor and those islands also remained uninhabited for more than a century. (Ref. 49) In addition, Spaniards transported somewhere in the range of 2,000 to 5,000 Indians from the United States to the West Indies. But the Cuban governor's report of 1530 showed that 1/3 of the island's natives died during the year and this was the excuse for the importation of African slaves. The viruses brought by these blacks helped to decimate the Indian natives. Both before and after Menendez founded St. Augustine, Florida Indians (particularly the Calyusas) had gone by canoe to Cuba either voluntarily or against their will, but in any case they died off as fast there as the native Cubans. Menendez married the daughter of Chief Carlos and when she made a trip to Cuba with her court, most of them soon died. In 1570, about 100 years after the arrival of Europeans, the population of Hispaniola had been reduced to 125 people. By the end of the century blacks and whites, along with Indians imported from elsewhere in the New World, had replaced the aboriginal populace of the Greater Antilles.

We should note, that just as in the Pacific, ships were not able to go straight eastward across the Atlantic from the Caribbean, because of the prevailing winds and currents. Spanish ships first made a rendezvous at Havana, then sailed close by the Gulf Coast through the Bahama Channel in the Gulf Stream along the coast to the Carolinas, where westerly winds returned them to Spain. As previously noted, many were wrecked on the mainland coasts. (Ref. 50)

SOUTH AMERICA

NORTHERN AND WESTERN SOUTH AMERICA

The first South American contact of the Spaniards occurred in 1501 when the Bay of Santa Marta and the Gulf of Cartagena in Colombia were explored. According to the chroniclers the natives were then living on the seacoast on a 90 mile strip below an altitude of 3,300 feet, engaged in gold metallurgy. The Spanish called them the Chairamas, whence came the name of the Tairona society, which may mean a place where metal is melted. The actual mines may have been located farther west and the Chairamas may have obtained it from the Taumacos, who dominated the gold bearing regions. Nevertheless, the fighting between the coast Indians and the Spaniards was bloody and the latter never did really conquer the area, as the Taironas withdrew to the mountains where they finally disappeared, probably from disease and hunger. The ruins of their original settlements have been in part excavated and have revealed stone buildings reached by roads and paved stairways some of which were 60 feet wide and by bridges of stone blocks. There were rock carvings and farming terraces and artificial mounds, perhaps for ceremonial use.

In the next 25 years several Spanish towns were established along this northern coast of South America. In 1528 the Welsers of Augsburg even appeared in Venezuela, but Spanish ill-will and terrible local atrocities brought their financial enterprises to failure. (Ref. 51, 52)

Before the days of the Spaniards some of the desert coast land of Peru was inhabited. Every 25 miles or so the desert is cut by a stream or river, which has created an oasis and made life possible. In the past some of these were the sites of very large cities, but during Hispanicization provincial life turned away to the central Andes and the coast remained practically bare. Like Mexico, parts of South America were densely settled at the time of European discovery. The Andean population was about 25,000,000 to 30,000,000. The people of Peru were mainly vegetarian, although there were some fish and occasionally communal game hunts for deer, llamas, guanacos, bears, pumas, foxes and vizcacha. Guinea pigs were raised in nearly every household along with ducks. The chief foods, however, were maize, potatoes, squash, beans, manioc and sweet potatoes, peanuts, tomatoes, avocados and chili peppers. Maize would not grow above 11,000 feet but potatoes and other tubers such as oca and guinoa, would. The potatoes were preserved by combined freezing and drying methods and the result was called "chunu", of greatest importance to highland People4 The slave workers of the silver mines of Potosi (now in south central Bolivia) subsisted almost entirely on chunu. That city was founded in 1545 at the altitude of 13,780 feet and by 1,600 had 100,000 people. Although the Spaniards spent most of their time looking for gold, silver was the real treasure of South America and soon the quicksilver mines of Huancavelica in Peru did not supply sufficient mercury for the amalgam processing in all the American silver mines and additional supplies had to be shipped from Spain and Yugoslavia. (Ref. 53)

Besides the empire of the Incas, South America had the Chimu Kingdom, with a capital at Chan Chan and then some less complex societies, called chiefdoms. Two types of the latter existed: (1) A militaristic society, with hereditary classes governed by war chiefs and with usually four classes; caciques or chiefs; people of rank; farmers; and slaves. (2) Theocratic societies under a shaman who officiated in a temple. War was necessary to maintain cannibal practices and to procure trophy heads, which were important symbols in the magic rituals of Chavin, Paracas, Nazca and Tiahuanaco religions. This rite disappeared in the Inca civilization, which seems to have taken over the area previously occupied by the Chimu princes. The explorer Pizarro does not even mention Chan Chan, but those people left many cultural developments in the central Andes, including administrative organization, communications by road, agriculture, long canals allowing intensive farming and perhaps trade and navigation. Their princes dominated only a few valleys, however, and the Incas exerted a much greater influence on the region as a whole. (Ref. 55)

In the Peruvian coastal areas which had been irrigated, there was already considerable salting of the soil and the population was collapsing. In addition, the small-pox which the Spaniards had brought to Mexico and the West Indies had spread even faster than they did and it was ravaging Peru by 1525. The reigning Inca, Huayna Capa, died of the disease and civil war followed between his two sons. It was into this wreckage of an empire that in 1532 Francisco Pizarro arrived with 106 foot soldiers and 62 horses. As when the Europeans landed in Mexico, Pizarro was at first mistaken for a god, but late in the year he moved his troops inland and seized one of the warring Inca princes, Atahualpa, in the midst of his vast army at Cajamarca. Intimidated by the horses and the obvious fire-power, the Indians put up no resistance, but the prince obtained his temporary release by paying the most fabulous ransom in history - a chamber 8 feet high filled with various objects of gold and jewelry along with 2 similar sized rooms filled with silver. After Pizarro had melted the metal down and distributed part of it among his men, he conveniently garroted Atahualpa on a false charge and appointed still another- royal brother, Tupac Hualpa, as the slain emperor's successor. He did not last long either and was succeeded by Manco. It is no wonder that relations between the two peoples steadily deteriorated so that by late 1535 the situation had become intolerable, from the Inca standpoint.

Manco escaped and assembled an army 100,000 strong to start a resistance to the Spaniards that was to last 36 years. The latter had now been reinforced and were strongly entrenched at Cuzco so that the Incas were unable to reclaim that city. Manco retreated to the juncture of the Andes and the Amazon basin and when pursued even there by a Spanish force, he retreated to Vitcos in the Vilcabamba River valley. Attacked again, he retreated once more while the spoils of Vitcos fell to the Spaniards, including some 20,000 prisoners and 50,000 head of llamas and alpacas. Hidden in the upper Vilcabamba, Manco recouped his forces, while in the meantime Pizarro had been murdered in his palace by some of his own disgruntled soldiers. Some of these then ran and took refuge with Manco and his Incas, where they taught the Indians the Spanish fighting techniques and horseback riding. Later these same Spanish renegades turned on Manco and slew him (1544) leaving the resistance against the Spanish to be led by Manco's son, Sayri Tupac. Some years later Sayri was offered a pardon by the Spanish crown and early in 1558 he married his sister, Cusi Huarcay5. Actually Sayri was never really crowned and died of illness in 1560. All five of Atahualpa's daughters married high ranking Spaniards and the dynasty was eliminated. All of Pizarro's expeditionary forces eventually met disaster. In addition to his own assassination, his three brothers all met violent deaths in one fashion or another. His men either had their heads cut off by the king's executioners or died in brawls or in native battles. The first bishop of Cuzco, Vincente de Valverd, was eaten by the inhabitants of Puna Island, while trying to flee back to Spain. (Ref. 56)

In the meantime many other conquistadores were traveling all over the northern part of South America, looking for gold. In 1535 Sebastian de Balacazar, veteran of the Inca conquest and founder of Quito, was told of a king who sprinkled his body with gold dust before swimming in his sacred lake. The legend named the mysterious king "El Dorado - the Golden man" and it fanned the lust for the precious metal among all the Spanish explorers. Gonzalo Jimenez de Quesada led an expedition inland from Columbia's northern coast in 1536, struggling through forests and swamps. Decimated by fever, malaria and attacks by hostile natives, only 200 of his original 900 men reached the Chibcha villages that were strewn across Colombia's Cundinamarca plateau. He found no gold, but did found the city of Santa Fe de Bogota, now the capital of Colombia. Others explored this same country, including the German Nicolaus Federmann and his countryman Philip von Guttan. Spaniards, including Gonzalo Pizarro, brother of Francisco and Francisco de Orellana also headed to the interior and when the latter came down a great river he encountered a tribe whose long-haired women drew a bow better than any man. Orellana gave the name "Amazonas" to the river, after those warrior women of the old Greek legend. Toward the end of the century, the hunt for gold shifted toward Guiana and then to the island of Trinidad, where the Spanish met the English adventurer Sir Walter Raleigh, who was on a similar search. Eventually some gold was found between the years 1525 and 1533 in Colombia and as has been noted, Potosi in Bolivia became for 100 years the biggest source of silver in the world. (Ref. 58, 59, 60)

After conquering the Incas in Peru, the Spanish tried to extend down into Chile about 1536, but they were pretty well stopped by the cannibalistic Araucanian Indians. Pedro de Valdiva did reach far enough south to found the city of Santiago in Chile by 1541. There, eventually as elsewhere in South America, silver mines were found and worked by the natives under Spanish direction. Recent study of skeletons of colonial Indians who mined silver in Tarapaca, of northern Chile, has shown evidence of the occupational illness of pneumoconiosis and silicosis from silver mining. Little is known of the Araucanians who lived on the western slope of the Chilean cordillera and on Chiloe Island prior to the arrival of the Spaniards. There were at least three groups, each speaking a dialect of an exclusive South American language. Estimations of their number, when the Spaniards arrived, vary from 500,000 to 2,000,000. Peaceful relations with them were not really established until the 18th century, although they were farmers and not basically hunters. Only the Quechus and Aymaras tribes were city builders, while the Mapuches lived more agricultural lives. The tribes fought each other and captives were ritually tortured and sacrificed. Cannibalism was practiced. (Ref. 61, 62, 63)

A few last words are indicated before we leave the west coast of South America. In 1526 when Francisco Pizarro left the Panamanian isthmus on his second and most intensive voyage down the coast, he encountered Peruvian merchant rafts coming north – rafts as large as Pizarro's caravel. The first one was a 36 ton raft with 20 Indians, masts with cotton sails, well rigged. The secret of control lay with multiple center-boards (guaras) in line along the center of the vessels, the skillful use of which allowed steering and beating up-wind to some degree. Some of the larger vessels had thatched bamboo huts with 4 or 5 rooms. They often carried salt along with other provisions for the 200 to 300 hundred mile trips between ports. Dry balsa wood would be too water absorbent for these rafts, but green balsa, when put to sea still filled with sap, is very water resistant. The description of these vessels from the early Spaniards is indisputable evidence that the Peruvians were capable of extensive ocean travel. (Ref. 64)

EASTERN AND CENTRAL SOUTH AMERICA

Horses which had been introduced far to the west in Peru by Pizarro were, within a few years, to be found running in large, wild herds even in the pampas of eastern South America. Sugar cane reached Brazil in about 1520 and sugar mills were set up in about 1550, so that soon there appeared the eternal trinity - the master's house, the slaves cabins and the sugar mill. Still the master had to sell his product and it was European trade that commanded production and output in Brazil and elsewhere in the New World. (Ref. 65) As early as 1521 the Portuguese began building forts in Brazil, hoping to reach the legendary empire of gold from the east, across the Chaco. The Guaranis tribes, already used to pillaging the rich Incanized slopes of the eastern Andes, helped the Portuguese expeditions. When the Spaniard Martinez de Irala reached the upper Andes in 1548, that part of Peru and Bolivia were already under Portuguese control. But Asuncion, now in Paraguay, 600 miles inland from the Atlantic, had been settled in 1542 by the Spaniard de Vaca6. Farther south the Spaniards had constant skirmishes with the Diaguites, who now used bow and arrows, but who were soon wiped out by disease. According to one priest, the Diaguites practiced circumcision, which recalls our note on page 212 regarding Mochican pottery vessels depicting circumcised prisoners. South of the Diaguites but still east of the cordillera there was a small group, the Huarpes, who may have been related to the former, but were described as tall, thin, brown men with lots of hair. The Chacos lived on the savannahs farther east and much farther south lived the Comechingons, between about the 29th and 34th parallels. The first Europeans to see them described them ashaving beards and wearing long, wool tunics. The chroniclers added that the Comechingons could mobilize as many as 40,000 warriors, although Engel (Ref. 66) feels that this must be an exaggeration.

Bahia was founded as the administrative capital for the Portuguese in 1549 and between 1575 and 1600 coastal Brazil had become the foremost sugar producing territory in the western world, averaging 1,600 tons a year, shipped to Europe. Soon there were shops on the streets of Sao Paulo and after 1580 Portuguese middlemen invaded the whole of Spanish America as shopkeepers and peddlers. The natives were nomadic and not easily made into a labor force and tended to slip away as the Portuguese arrived, so slave ships shuttled between Angola and Brazil, with payment given in Africa in low grade Brazilian tobacco. Then in half a century Paulist bandeiras spread out from Sao Paulo over half the continent from the Rio de la Plata to the Amazon and Andes in search of slaves, precious stones and gold. (Ref. 68) It has been estimated that by 1583 there were 25,000 whites, 18,000 civilized Indians and 14,000 Negro slaves in the territory. The towns of Brazil, which Braudel (Ref. 69) has described as so many miniature versions of Sparta or Thebes, were run by the men of property, the Spanish cabildos.

Argentina had been discovered even earlier in 1516 by the Spanish Juan Diaz de Solis and the coasts explored by Diego Garcia in 1526. Buenos Aires was founded in 1534 by Pedro de Mendoza but the village soon died out or was destroyed. When it was rebuilt in 1580 it was chiefly by Portuguese merchants. Their ships streamed west across the Atlantic laden with rice, fabrics, black slaves and perhaps some gold, would arrive at Buenos Aires, then go up the Rio de la Plata to Ascension, where they would trade for silver reals coming down the Pilcomayo River. (Ref. 70)

Magellan and 265 men rounded Cape Horn as early as 1520 on their famous globe circling trip, but it was about 1579 that Europeans came in contact with the natives of Patagonia. They were described as being light-skinned men with thick, bushy black, wiry hair, who smeared their bodies with red paint and grease. The Europeans attempted a colony there and brought sheep, which the Patagonians promptly hunted. Today there are no true Patagonians left.1

1 (Ref. 71) In the service of Spanish merchants, the Portuguese Sebastian Cabot reached the Rio de la Plata about 1530

1 [224] VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

2 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

3 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

4 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

8 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

9 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

10 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

11 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

12 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

13 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

14 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

15 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

16 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

17 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

18 [277] CANBY, THOMAS Y, "The Anasazi: Riddles in the Ruins", National Geographic 162: 562-592, Nov. 1982.

19 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

20 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

21 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

22 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

23 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

24 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

25 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

26 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

27 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

28 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

29 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

30 [236] WILKERSON, JEFFREY K. "Man's Eighty Centuries in Veracruz", National Geographic 158: 202, Aug. 1980.

31 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

32 [273] ANAWALT, PATRICIA R. "Understanding Aztec Human Sacrifice", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 38-45, Sept./Oct. 1982.

33 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

34 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

35 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

36 [283] NATIONS, HAMES D. AND CLARK, JOHN E., "The Bows and Arrows of the Lacandon Maya", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 36-43, Jan./Feb. 1983.

37 [204] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Incidents of Travel in Yucatan, Volume I. (Dover Publ., Inc. New York, 1963 - unabridged re-publication of 1843 work by Harper & Bros.).

38 [283] NATIONS, HAMES D. AND CLARK, JOHN E., "The Bows and Arrows of the Lacandon Maya", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 36-43, Jan./Feb. 1983.

39 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

40 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

41 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

42 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

43 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

44 [308] EDWARDS, MIKE, "Honduras: The Eye of the Storm", National Geographic 164: No.5: 608-637, Nov. 1983.

45 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

46 [36] COE, MICHAEL D. "Archeological Linkage with North & South America at La Victoria, Guatemala", American Anthropologist 62: 363-393, 1960.

47 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

48 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

49 [274] BENCHLEY, PETER, "The Bahamas", National Geographic 162: 365-395, Sept. 1982.

50 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

51 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

52 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

53 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

54 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

55 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

56 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

57 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

58 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

59 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

60 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

61 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

62 [3] ALLISON, MARVIN J., "Studies of Pre-Columbian American Diseases 1971-1976, National Geographic Research Reports. Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 1-11 (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C., 1980).

63 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

64 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

65 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

66 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

67 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

68 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

69 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

70 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

71 [302] WARNER, OLIVER (with DR. J.C. BEAGLEHOLE), Captain Cook and the South Pacific. (Cassell, London. American Heritage Publ. Co., Inc., New York, 1963).

1.  Late Anasazi people of the Acoma pueblo. (Ref. 18)

2.  Juan de Cabrillo and Bartolome Ferrelo had previously explored the west coast to Oregon

3.  Trager (Ref. 47) has given a gross misstatement on page 161 to the effect that Columbus' 4th voyage took 8 months for the Atlantic crossing

4.  It should be noted that because the Andes Indians had the custom of replanting the smaller potatoes and eating the larger ones, potatoes at that time were generally only peanut-sized. The large potato of today is the product of centuries of more enlightened horticulture. (Ref. 54)

5.  As in ancient Egypt, this incestuous situation was the rule among the imperial family of Peru. (Ref. 57)

6.  Other authorities state that the Spanish entered Paraguay in 1524, intermarrying with the Guarani and founding Asuncion in 1537. (Ref. 67)

America: A.D. 1601 to 1700

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA (See map in next module)

In the early 17th century northern Europeans, already experienced in smuggling and raiding Spanish-American shipping, began to establish permanent colonies of their own in America. The north Europeans ' advantages included their access to the sources of shipbuilding material (particularly around the Baltic), fewer political commitments and diversification of European interests and finally more sophisticated devices for obtaining capital and spreading risks - the chartered joint-stock company. (Ref. 1)

CANADA AND THE FAR NORTH

The Thule Arctic Culture, which has been discussed in several previous chapters, is generally conceded to have ended about 1700, merging into the Modern Eskimo Culture. Samuel Champlain was sent out to Canada from France in 1603 to map the known rivers. Establishing Quebec as a base, he explored Lakes Huron and Ontario and sided with the Algonquin and Huron Indians, while defeating the hostile Iroquois. The Jesuit priest, Pierre Francois Xavier de Charlevoix, who wrote a Histoire de'la Nouvelle France in the 18th century, accumulated much information about the French-Iroquois war of 1610. He told of terrible atrocities committed by the Hurons on the Iroquois prisoners, including cannibalism1. Champlain was the most versatile of colonial founders, a sailor, soldier, scholar and man of action, artist and explorer. (Ref. 2) The friendly Hurons became the middlemen for the fur trade between Montreal and the Indian trappers of the Great Lakes areas. Nova Scotia was founded as the French colony of Acadia in 1632. (Ref. 3)

At the death of Champlain in 1635 Canada was the property of a joint-stock company, the Hundred Associates. Settlement advanced very slowly, however, and by 1643, a year after a stronghold had been built at Montreal, there were not 300 Frenchmen in all New France, exclusive of Nova Scotia. Even by 1665 Quebec contained only 70 houses and 550 people. The French fur traders, however, soon carried their commerce 2,000 miles inland to the Tetons. They could live on the barest vegetation and in the crudest shelter, in terrible weather. It was those French guides who later staffed the Lewis and Clark expedition. (Ref. 5, 6) In 1685 the governor of Canada wrote to Louis XIV complaining that the colonial French had not civilized the Indians, but on the contrary, the Frenchmen who lived among the savages themselves became savages. (Ref. 7)

Throughout the entire first 2/3 of the century New France had to continually fight the Five Nations of the Iroquois League and largely because of this the Hundred Associates gave up in 1663 and surrendered their charter, allowing Canada to become a crown colony of Louis XIV. In 1665 the Marquis de Tracy arrived with 800 soldiers to wage a total war campaign against the Iroquois, killing and burning their fields and villages. (Ref. 8) The new military regime was absolute, with severe laws stringently enforced by torture, when necessary. The Marquis' chief claim to fame is that he brought girls along to be the soldiers' wives and these, along with a few descendants of extraneous unions of coureurs de bois with young Indian girls, are primarily the ancestors of all present day French-Canadians.

Robert Cavelier de La Salle, born at Rouen and educated in a Jesuit seminary, emigrated to Canada early in life and from letters brought to life much later, it is apparent that he started his first exploratory trip south from Canada as early as 1671. In 1675 he visited France and received a grant of the government and property at Fort Frontenac (now Kingston, Ontario), which had been previously established in 1672 under the name of Fort Cataraqui. La Salle rebuilt the fort and in the spring of 1678 was commissioned to undertake the exploration of the Mississippi River. (Ref. 9) We shall here more of him in the next section.

The first commercial venture into the Hudson Bay area was in 1668 when Fort Charles was built by Scottish entrepreneurs. Two years later the Hudson Bay Company was chartered with title to nearly 1.5 million square miles of territory. French and Scotch-English fought minor skirmishes in this region over control of the land and its furs for the next 100 years. (Ref. 10)

THE UNITED STATES

By this time the eastern Woodland Indians were using some 275 plants for medicine, 130 for food, 31 as magic, 27 for smoking, 25 for dyes, 18 in beverages or flavoring and 52 for various other purposes. Most of the tribes of the northern United States and southern Canada belonged to the Algonquian linguistic stock, comprised of the Micmacs, Wabanakis, Etchemis, Montaignais, Natick, Abnaki, Massachuset, Penobscot, Wamponoag and Delawares, in the eastern area. The original name for the Delawares was "Lanape" and there is some evidence that they may have had some contact with the Dutch as early as 1609. Squeezed between the New York state Iroquois League, the Susquehannocks and the more southern Powhatan Confederacy, part of the Lenape moved on west and part stayed to become dependent on and eventually in some degree to fuse with the European settlers. (Ref. 11) The early history of the Shawnees is not known with certainty, but they considered the Delewares their "grandfathers". By 1650 they were living in southern Ohio and northern Kentucky where they remained for several years. Then, after quarrels with neighbors, they dispersed somewhat, from the Gulf Coast to the Delaware Valley in western New Jersey. (Ref. 12)

In what was then the "west", in addition to the Shawnee, were the Potowatami, Menominee, Cree, Ojibwa, Ottawa, Arapaho, Blackfoot and Cheyenne. A most interesting observation, recently validated to some extent by Professor Fell, is that the most western of these tribes have Mongolian physical features and Siberian root vocabularies, while their eastern cousins have markedly European physiognomies and marked grammatical and vocabulary similarities to the Semitic language of the Phoenicians (or North Africans). Even a few Celtic words have penetrated the eastern Algonquian dialects and finally there are some Norse words. Fell feels that the eastern Algonquians themselves are in great part descended from early Mediterranean colonizers and their tribal traditions, which included their ancestors crossing the sea and some of the local archaeological evidence, might be confirmatory. (Ref. 13) Few historians would back up Fell in these hypotheses and apparently no blood factor studies have been done that might tend to either deny or confirm such ideas. The Indians of North America used little cylinders cut from blue or violet sea-shells threaded on a string as money called "wampum". Even Europeans used this legitimately until 1670 and some even after that. (Ref. 14) In 1649 the Virginia assembly had even set standard values - one yard of wampum (peake or roanoke) equaled two shillings sixpence and one fathom equaled five shillings. If the peake was black it had double the value. (Ref. 15)

Early Spanish, French and English colonists in southeastern United States encountered a 50 settlement confederation of the Creek Indian Confederacy in an area now consisting of Alabama and Georgia. The confederacy included various peoples with several languages, including Chickasaw and Choctaw. To the north of the Creek also lived the Cherokees, some 60,000 strong in about 100 settlements. Their ancestors had built large mounds in West Virginia and Tennessee. On the lower Mississippi were the Natchez, inheritors of the Mississippian Culture. (Ref. 16) Mystery surrounds the Westos and Ricahecrians, who appeared menacingly on the South Carolina and Virginia frontiers in this century. Were they one and the same people? Did they speak Iroquoian or Siouan? Many of the coastal Indians relied heavily on the sea, eating mollusks and catching fish with spears. Bows and arrows, bone hooks, basket traps and poisons. Until Franciscans established missions and promoted agriculture, Gaule Indians in coastal Georgia depended primarily on marine life. As agriculture spread, time became available for perfection of crafts such as basket-making, carpentry, woodworking, pipe-making, weaving, pottery, tanning and even certain kinds of metal work. Tobacco cultivation created a demand for pipes, some finely wrought from clay and decorated. (Ref. 17)

The Calusa were not typical southern Indians and there is much mystery about them, also. They were excellent seamen, constructing large, seaworthy, dugout canoes, some of which would hold up to 80 men. Among almost all southern Indians the men were tall for that time, usually 5'6" but some 6' or more. Both sexes were well proportioned, with the men wearing deerskin breechcloths and the women skirts. Mantles of deer, bear or buffalo skins, woven feathers and Spanish moss provided warmth in the winter. Elaborate tattooing was widespread, with extensive body decoration indicating higher rank. Ornaments were worn by men and women alike. They lived in an essentially law-abiding society, although their laws and morals were different than their later white counterparts. Men could have as many wives as they could afford and young girls normally had sexual relations freely. Divorce was easy, but adultery resulted in severe punishment both for the guilty one and the clan. There is little question that Indians scalped their victims, even before Europeans arrived. (Ref. 18)

The Powhatans in the Virginia Tidewater were the most densely populated of any Indians of the south, and even in 1650 after white contact had begun its depopulation from disease, Dobyns2 estimated that there were 1,357,000 Indians in the South as a whole. Archeological finds backup this high population density. We have already detailed in the last chapter the story of the early Spanish explorations in the southern United States and something about their contacts with the Indians. The early English crossing of the Atlantic westward had to take essentially the same course as Columbus and the Spanish, because of the currents and winds that have been mentioned on several occasions. Raleigh's expedition to Roanoke Island, in the last century, sailed through the West Indies before the Gulf Stream carried his ships northward and the early Jamestown settlers had to follow the same course. In the first half of the 17th century 60,000 Englishmen sought refuge in the New World, chiefly in the United States. In addition there were a few Dutchmen and Frenchmen and a sprinkling of Swedes and Finns, as we shall see below. After the original colonization period along the Atlantic coast, there was a period from about 1640 to 1660 when the colonies were left pretty much alone, because of civil war and its sequelae in England. From 1675 to 1691 or after, however, there was a time of troubles in the colonies, including Indian Wars, local rebellions, French incursions, etc. It will be most convenient to discuss the history of this century under regional headings:

NEW ENGLAND COLONIES

This designation included colonies of New Hampshire, Massachusetts Bay, Rhode Island and Connecticut. By 1700 there were 130,000 people in this geographical area, with 7,000 in Boston and 2,600 in Newport. These settlers all belonged to the more independent classes and possessed a great mass of intelligence, which was to greatly influence the government and commerce of America for generations to come. (Ref. 20) The first Englishman to explore the New England area was Bartholomew Gosnold, who sailed from the Azores in 1602 to go along the coast from Maine to Cape Cod. He built a house on Cuttyhunk, traded with Indians and left smallpox on the new continent. He was followed by Thomas Hunt, taking Indians as slaves in 1615 and perhaps again introducing smallpox. By 1617 an epidemic of this disease reduced the Indian population by over a thousand, some say as much as 10,000. (Ref. 21)

NEW HAMPSHIRE

Two small proprietary colonies were set up - one in New Hampshire and one in Maine. The latter belonged to Sir Ferdinando Gorges, whose heirs soon sold out to Massachusetts, but small settlements at Portsmouth and Exeter, N.H., which began as personal estates of Captain John Mason, persisted even af ter being sold to the crown. New Hampshire was not truly a separate province from Massachusetts until after 1691. In 1690 the first man-of-war built for the British navy in America, the "Falkland", was completed at Portsmouth, New Hampshire.

MASSACHUSETTS BAY

Some Puritan separatists, who had seceded from the Church of England to the Netherlands, under William Brewster and accompanied by William Bradford, founded the new Plymouth colony in 1620. They immediately set up their own self government under the Mayflower compact. The Mayflower expedition was subsidized by a loan of 7,000 pounds and it had 149 people, including about 40 "separatists" (i.e. separating from the English Church), chiefly from Leyden where they had previously gone. In the first winter in the new land over 1/2 died of scurvy or general debility. They had tried to hit northern Virginia, but missed their target. After the first few seasons, William Bradford became their governor. These Pilgrims deserve to be famous for two things; first, they survived and secondly they proclaimed the Mayflower compact, a bold assertion of their right to self -government. Following the Mayflower was the great Puritan migration of the 1630s. The promoters of the Massachusetts Bay Colony put up 200,000 pounds. The group was led by John Winthrop, a Puritan (different from the "Separatists"), who only wanted to "purify" the Church of England. They first sailed in March, 1630 with 500 men, women and children. On arrival, they raised cattle, Indian corn and vegetables and soon developed both a fur trade and cod fishing. Winthrop was very concerned about the saintliness of his colony, but not his customers, as he sold cod and later ships to Roman Catholics and to slave-holding Virginian planters alike. This colony was at once a theocracy and an oligarchy, yet it adopted trial by jury, freedom from self-incrimination, and levied no taxes on those who could not vote. But there was no religious tolerance. Baptists and Quakers-were the Devil's agents and the Quakers were the worst. By the penal law of the colony any Catholic priest, who reappeared there after having once been driven out, was subject to death. (Ref. 22) Witchcraft was persecuted, but chiefly after Winthrop's death. (Ref. 23) The Puritan migrations continued until 1637 when the English Puritans decided to stay and contest their fate in England, itself, as its Civil War started. That war kept Charles I from suppressing the Bay Colony and its government became a model for the other colonies. In 1634 Massachusetts joined with her neighboring Puritan colonies to form the New England Confederation. This was a loose union formed to settle boundary disputes and give mutual protection from Indians, French and Dutch. Free, public education was soon established, a printing press appeared in Cambridge in 1639 and Harvard University was established in the same city in 1650.

In 1675 serious Indian troubles began in the so-called King Philip's War. Metacom, chief of the Wampanoag and called King Philip by the English, was one of the original friends of the Pilgrim fathers and a frequent patron of Boston stores. But he became surly over various chastisements and developed a plot to attack the settlers. The chief's Harvard educated Indian secretary, Sassamon, tipped off Governor Winslow, however, and Sassamon was subsequently killed by other Indians. The murderers were found, tried and hanged. Two weeks later war broke out with Philip's Wampanoag and their allies, the Nipmuch. The New England Confederation retaliated with a declaration of war, thus involving Connecticut. The Indians were not organized and had only hit and run tactics. The Narragansett tribe on the Bay sheltered some of the Indian refugees, giving Winslow the excuse to attack them with 1,000 men and finally winning in the roughest battle ever fought on New England soil, save the later battle of Bunker Hill. Philip was killed in August 1676 and most of his Indians were captured. The women and children were used as house servants and the men were shipped to the West Indies as slaves. The war in the area of Maine did not end until 1678 and the Indians there retained their land and later helped the French against the English. (Ref. 24)

When the Catholic king, James II, assumed the English throne in 1685 the Massachusetts Bay Colony was given a new administrator, Sir Edmund Andros. When William and Mary ascended the English throne, however, the people of Boston jailed Andros and returned to their pre-Andros government. New troubles began in 1689 when the French and their Indian allies began to raid in Maine and New Hampshire. The New England authorities at Boston struck back directly at Port Royal and Quebec, as the first offensive of the King William's War. The campaign, under Sir William Phips in 1690, was a fiasco. The dreary war dragged on and although King William ended the European end of the conflict in 1697 with the Treaty of Ryswick (see Europe), the American battles continued until 1699.

RHODE ISLAND

This Puritan colony was founded by the Reverend Roger Williams, who had been banished from the Massachusetts Colony. Williams was loved by the Indians, lodged with them, learned their language and respected them. He felt that it was possible that God might feel their religion equal to Christianity, a heresy of that day. The only unity in the colony was one of religious liberty. Its fate was to be found with the other Puritan colonies in the New England Confederation.

CONNECTICUT

Connecticut, too, was formed as a migration from the Massachusetts colony, led by the Reverends Hooker and Stone. The original settlements were along the Connecticut River at Hartford, Windsor and Wethersfield. New Haven was settled separately, but all joined together as Connecticut, in 1662. A code of laws was drawn up, beginning with penal laws, which were actually borrowed from the Bible. (Ref. 25) Like Rhode Island, this colony's history in this century is bound to that of Massachusetts, in the Confederation.

MIDDLE COLONIES

This designation included New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania along with the small area of Delaware. By 1700 there were approximately 65,000 people in this group of settlements.

NEW YORK

In 1609 Henry Hudson sailed up the river bearing his name and by 1629 his Dutch people had settled New Amsterdam at the mouth of the river, using a Dutch Company charter. The famous purchase of Manhattan Island from the Wappinger Indian Confederacy for a few trinkets occurred in 1626. (Ref. 26) The social structure was a type of feudalism and the colony did not do well. By 1660 New Netherland had only 1/2 the population of Connecticut. The Dutch traded with the Delaware Indians some, but then got into warfare at the future site of Esopus on the Hudson. The Delawares then sold most of their land and moved to the Susquehanna Valley in Pennsylvania. In 1644, as a by-product of a Dutch-English War, the Duke of York sailed into the New Amsterdam harbor with four English frigates and took the city without a shot being fired. New York has never been racially or geographically homogeneous, even in the beginning. The Jesuit Simon Le Moyne visited the area of future Syracuse in 1654, finding important salt deposits there.

New York did not contribute to the defense of New England in their early troubles and the Duke of York pretty well made his own laws and levied his own taxes. The province extended from Canada to the edge of Maryland and the cost of administration was great.

In 1683 the Duke instructed his Irish governor, Colonel Thomas Dongan, to summon an assembly primarily for the purpose of raising f unds. It met and enacted "The Charter of Liberties and Privileges", declaring that the assembly had the supreme legislative authority and that no taxes were to be levied without its consent. Shortly thereaf ter, however, the erstwhile Duke of York had become King James 11 and he promptly disallowed this declaration of rights and New York became a royal province, with no assembly. With the subsequent banishment of King James, there was much confusion in the colony and this was augmented by a combined French and Indian attack from the north, resulting in the destruction of the town of Schenectady.

NEW JERSEY

The Duke of York originally gave New Jersey as a gift to two friends, George Carteret and Lord John Berkeley. Philip Carteret, cousin of Sir George, came over from England to take possession in 1665. He gave a liberal grant of political privileges - the best on the continent - to the few hundred Dutchmen and English Puritans who lived there. A representative assembly first met in 1668. The situation became very complicated a few years later when there were two Jersies - East New Jersey, with an assembly meeting at Elizabethtown and a West New Jersey, with an assembly meeting at Salem or Burlington. Confusion in land titles for the next 75 years resulted from these conflicts. The proprietors did not surrender their governmental powers to the crown until 1702.

PENNSYLVANIA

William Penn got the charter for Pennsylvania from Charles II in 1681 and brought over Quaker dissidents from England, Wales, the Netherlands and France. The voyage took two months and one-third of his people died of small-pox, en route. (Ref. 27) The Quakers, as we have noted previously, were a left wing Puritan sect founded by George Fox in 1650. Penn established the city of Philadelphia in 1682, where some Swedes and Finns were already settled. Germans of the Mennonite sect soon also arrived and settled, so that by 1700 Philadelphia had outstripped New York City and was pushing Boston as a cultural center. Yellow fever killed 220 people in Philadelphia at the end of the century. (Ref. 28)

DELAWARE

The Swedish West India Company had established the small colony of New Sweden, centering on Fort Christina on the site of present Wilmington, in 1638. This consisted of only 200 to 300 Swedes and Finns, but they brought log construction and the log cabin to America. Peter Stuyvesant, of the New Netherland Colony, annexed this weak Swedish settlement in 1655 so that when the Duke of York took over the Dutch possessions, this area became part of that. William Penn later purchased the region from the Duke and for years it was called the "Three Lower Counties" of Pennsylvania. The Charter of Privileges, which Penn brought back in 1699, allowed these three counties to have their own assembly, but their governor was always the same as Pennsylvania's. These three counties, however, were the future state of Delaware. (Ref. 29)

CHESAPEAKE BAY COLONIES

VIRGINIA

The first true and lasting settlement in the United States was made at Jamestown, off Chesapeake Bay, in 1607 by Englishmen who, according to de Tocqueville (Ref. 30), "were seekers of gold, adventurers without resources and without character.”3 Existence in this nucleus of the Dominion of Virginia in the early days, was miserable. Of the initial group, consisting of 104 men and boys, 51 died of disease and starvation within 6 months. Help from Indians and the arrival of a supply ship saved the rest. That ship also brought 2 women and 5 Poles, who had been recruited to begin the production of pitch, tar and turpentine. (Ref. 31) In the end, however, salvation came with the Indian crop, tobacco. (Ref. 32) Between the years 1616 and 1624 Virginia was changed from a trading post to more of a genteel, permanent community. There were several factors in this transition. One was tobacco, of which Virginia exported some 50,000 pounds as early as 1618. A second factor was the institution of private property and a third reason was political, in that English common law was in effect along with a representative assembly.

The Indians of the Tidewater at the time of the planting of the Jamestown colony were the powerful Powhatan Confederacy (Tsenacommacah). They were Algonquians, but Iroquois, Sioux and Muskogeans all lived close by. There were rumors of blond, blue-eyed Indians to the south, but these were probably survivors from Raleigh's lost colony or shipwrecks. Although a century earlier Tsenacommacah may have had over 100,000 inhabitants, the population was considerably less in this 17th century. The microparasites introduced by the visits of Verazzano, Menendez and Raleigh had already done much of their destructive work. Contemporary writers accused the Powhatans of sacrificing children, but this was a mistaken concept of the huskanaw, an initiation rite in which at the appropriate time children were collected and sent to a designated spot in the woods, where for weeks they subsisted on a limited diet. Perhaps some drugs and rigorous mental and physical ordeals were supervised by their priests, but they were not killed, although some of the weaker may have perished. The local chief at the time of the Jamestown founding was Powhatan, whose daughter was the famous Pocahontas, captured in 1613 by Samuel Argall, to be used to influence the chief to make peace. She married John Rolfe in 1614, visited England and died there in 1617, though her son Thomas survived. Thomas Rolfe was not the only mestizo born from the white-Indian contact at Jamestown. (Ref. 34)

The Virginia Company was reorganized in 1619 and a new leadership was established. Captain George Thorpe, a pious Anglican, who had started to build a college in Jamestown, might have risen to leadership, but in 1622 Opechancanough, successor to Chief Powhatan, rebelled and massacred some 300 whites, burying an axe in Thorpe's skull. Thereafter the settlers waged a relentless war against the Indians, burning and pillaging their villages and cutting down or carrying off their crops. This also gave the opportunity for capturing slaves, which the English, as the Spanish before them, did with enthusiasm, using them locally or sending them to Bermuda or Barbados. A treaty was negotiated with the rebellious tribes in the Potomac River area in 1623. After a toast was drunken symbolizing eternal friendship, the Chiskiack chief and his sons, advisers and followers totaling 200, abruptly dropped dead from poison and soldiers put the remainder out of their misery. It was perhaps from this encounter that Captain William Tucker and his men brought back 50 Indian "heads", presumably scalps, though somewhat more may have been included. The second and last major conflict in the Tidewater was the 1644 massacre, plotted again by the aged Opechancanough, with more than 500 colonists killed. One out of every 16 Virginians perished. (Ref. 35)

In the meantime in 1624 Virginia had become a crown colony with a governor and council appointed by the king and it was well governed and prospered. Although the Indians had grown and smoked tobacco for centuries, their variety was too bitter for the whites and John Rolfe imported a new species from the West Indies and perfected a method of curing it. This was the tobacco that was to be exported. The transplanted English soon imported or manufactured locally their own wampum, the blue beads which had become standard trade items. An aboriginal canoe in 1624 was worth 10,000 blue beads, a stack of mats brought 20,000.

The most serious Indian conflict in the latter half of the century was the fighting associated with Bacon's rebellion. Susquehannocks had moved into the Potomac area and although they at first were treated badly, Governor Berkeley had them protected by scattered forts.

But whites continued to be killed, including the overseer at the plantation of Nathanial Bacon, Jr., so Bacon and his neighbors denounced the governor for depending so much on the frontier forts and implied that he had a secret interest in Indian trade. Bacon's men surprised the Occanechees, who were allies of the Susquehannocks, burning and capturing their fort and shooting or burning to death almost all the Indians. Hostilities flared all along the frontier and Governor Berkeley finally in June of 1676, authorized a full campaign against the natives, with Bacon as commander. When Bacon became sick and died, however, Berkeley regrouped and had Bacon's followers executed and their property confiscated. Although he then negotiated still another treaty with the Indians, the whites continued their destruction so that by 1700 there were only approximately 1,400 aborigines left in the Tidewater. Near the end of the century the depleted Powhatans were led by the good Queen of Pamunkey, who actually accepted a tributary status to the whites. The English policy of encouraging tribal rivalries, of dividing and conquering, had succeeded. Farther inland the Tuscarora, Cherokee and Seneca warriors, although possibly never seeing a white face, were well aware of their presence in the Tidewater because of the commerce and the small-pox epidemics that reached them. (Ref. 36)

We should add a few final notes before we leave Virginia in this early colonial period. In 1609 "Martin's Hundred" had made a settlement at Walstenholme. It was actually larger than Jamestown, but it disappeared in an Indian massacre and has only recently been excavated. The "dig" shows that the Englishmen were in full metal armor like medieval knights and the heavy armor and a closed helmet hampered movement, restricted vision and muffled warning signs of approaching enemies. It is no wonder they were no match for the Indians. (Ref. 37) An interesting sidelight is also to be found in recent recovered fragments from a 1619 shipwreck in Castle Harbor - 5 sherds of Roman pottery. It was initially thought that these might have been picked up from old gravel beds along the Thames, used for ballast pebbles in the ship, but experts have said definitely that the gravel did not come from the Thames. So, the riddle of Roman pottery in Castle Harbor remains unsolved. (Ref. 38) Could this have some bearing on Barry Fell's hypotheses about European visitors to the American hemisphere around the time of Christ? Finally we should note that English ships brought the first black slaves to Virginia in 16194 but in the first 40 years no more than 300 arrived altogether. By the 1680s, however, they were brought in at the rate of 60,000 every decade. (Ref. 39) In time both Negro and Indian slavery assumed more and more importance in Virginia. Often young Indians were taken into apprenticeships, but of ten the terms never expired and in essence it was still slavery. According to a 1669 law, foreign - that is non-Virginian Indians - captured in war and those imported by sea and sold, were to remain slaves for life. Governor Berkeley owned native slaves. A frequent reason for the hostilities with Indian enemies and allies, alike, was the opportunity to capture slaves. Rather than peltry, they were the real plunder. The Indians them- selves kept slaves and had severe punishments for runaways. They severed their Achilles tendons or cut off their toes and half of their feet, carefully folding the skin over the stumps so that they would heal. The slaves could then work in the field, but could hardly run away again.

MARYLAND

Maryland was a part of Virginia until 1632 when King Charles I gave a slice of that original colony to his friend, Lord Baltimore (George Calvert of an old Yorkshire family). Baltimore died quickly, however, and his son got the charter and administered Maryland from England. It was basically a Catholic colony and although named Maryland ostensibly after Queen Henrietta Marie, it was in reality named in honor of the Virgin Mary. Tobacco was the one great cash crop. Servants might be of any class from poor gentlemen working off the cost of transport, to convicted felons. Many of the English sovereigns transported Scottish and Irish prisoners from the civil wars to Virginia and Maryland, as well as to the West Indies. Negroes were also imported and in 1664 the Maryland assembly passed a "black code" which declared each Negro to be a slave for life by virtue of his color. At all times during the century, except for a short period in the 1650s, Catholics were the ruling class in this colony, although with increased immigration Protestants became finally the overwhelming numerical majority. (Ref. 42)

THE CAROLINAS

In this century the English began referring to the great land south of the James River as "Carolina". Going south from the James, one had to go 500 miles to encounter another European settlement and that would be the Franciscan mission at Port Royal Sound. Mississippian style villages with council houses or rotundas, plazas and fields of maize were still present throughout that area. Lord Ashley (John Colleton, a Barbadian planter) received a Charter for the Carolinas in 1963, but there was no settlement there until 1670, when Charleston was founded. Even then little was accomplished until the Huguenots came in 1680. Those French formed, eventually, the aristocratic South Carolina while North Carolina was settled by poor whites moving in from Virginia. The two Carolinas were not separated in this 17th century, however.

The aborigines surrounding Charleston already had guns, which they had obtained from the Spaniards and even from some Virginia traders. Some tribes, such as the Westos, were well armed, using more European weapons than bows and arrows and they terrified their less well-armed neighbors at the time. They lived on the Savannah or Westo River near present day Augusta, in part of the kingdom of the Cofitachique. Whether there was any connection between the two tribes in uncertain. The Westos have now become extinct, apparently having been destroyed by the Shawnees (Savannahs) who subsequently migrated westward again into Alabama, then northward into Kentucky and the Ohio country and eventually to Oklahoma. Among a few others, the pack trains of Abraham Wood, working out of Charleston, helped to supply the Westos with guns. He knew a great deal about the southern Indians, most of which were tribes that were remnants of the Cusabo chiefdom. None were strong enough to protect themselves and they looked to the English, the Spaniards or the Westos for protection. But Woodward felt that the Westos depended too much on Virginia and, changing his alliances, he and other Carolinians resolved to exterminate the Westos and install the Shawnees in their stead. (Ref. 43)

A group of Indian fighters called the "Goose Creek men" then emerged and assumed more power in the colony. Most of them were originally from Barbados, and at the end of the century one of them, James Moore, even became governor. These men soon brought most of the southern aborigines into their commercial orbit, at the expense of Spain, Virginia and later France. The Creeks, Shawnees (Savannahs), Cherokees and Yamasees usually could get cheaper guns, hardware and clothing from Carolinians than from anyone else. Incited by the Goose Creek men, the natives overran Spanish missions, burned chapels and sometimes the padres and carried off booty. First to fall were the Guale missions and some of those in Timucua. Timucuan, Guale and Yamasee Indians lived in those missions which in 1670 had stretched north from St. Augustine to the Savannah River. Yamasees from both the coastal missions and the Chattahoochee, for protection, began moving in large numbers closer to Charleston. Then the Goose Creek men began to use the Yamasees to demolish missions in Guale and Timucua. The booty included silver plate, ornaments, peltry, and especially slaves, all of which the Carolinians exchanged for guns, powder, hardware and textiles. Af ter white contact, the Indians relied less on agriculture and hunted more, with young ones ranging hundreds of miles, some even crossing the Mississippi River and covering more than 1,000 miles before returning home. (Ref. 44)

Carolina, established relatively late, nevertheless soon had an Indian slave trade that overshadowed other mainland colonies. In late century these normally came from the interior and were marched in large numbers to the coast for sale to English purchasers. As in Africa, natives captured and sold natives. Westos, Savannahs, Lower Creeks and Yamasees, among others, raided remote towns and brought their prisoners to Charleston. Incidentally, yellow fever killed 150 people in Charleston in 1698. (Ref. 45, 46) Sometime during this century the London Company started a settlement in what was to be South Carolina, which thrived on ambergris, a secretion from the whale's intestine that was to be found floating on the sea. It was used in perfumes. (Ref. 47)

EXTRA-COLONIAL AREAS OF THE UNITED STATES

THE SOUTHEAST

Spain began establishing her second great mission system in the province of Apalachee after 1630, well after the founding of Jamestown. By the 1670s some 20 smaller missions radiated from the principal one at San Luis (Tallahassee) and a road connected that province with St. Augustine. Still Spain's grasp on the area was weak and the garrisons averaged only 300 to 400 men and even these were not the flower of the Spanish army. They were greatly outnumbered by the surrounding natives and, as we have noted in the preceding section, these were of ten encouraged to attack by the Carolinians. The priests did make many converts, however, and since the cross had long been one of the symbols of the Southeastern Ceremonial Complex, the padres reported that the Indians fervently came forward to kiss the newly erected cross. Even as early as the preceding century Franciscans had learned the tongue of the Timucuan and Apalachee and that knowledge helped preserve much information about those peoples. Some Timucuans and other natives were actually reading, writing and singing in Castilian, as well as writing in their own language. But the missionaries could also be cruel and they whipped Indians who missed Mass, forcing them to be porters transporting goods some 200 miles from St. Augustine without pay, among other penalties. It is no wonder that they could easily be influenced to revolt. (Ref. 48)

Because of the fear of the French in Louisiana, Spain had a mission on the Neches River in 1690 and later a garrison at Pensacola, Florida. Even so Florida remained sparsely populated. There were droves of wild pigeons, parrots and other birds, so that many boats came away loaded with birds and their eggs. (Ref. 49)

THE MISSISSIPPI RIVER REGION AND LOUISIANA

The French explorer Jean Nicolet, who had lived among the Hurons since Champlain's expedition of 1618, explored the Lake Michigan and Wisconsin regions in 1634. (Ref. 50) Courcelles and Frontenac explored farther in the Great Lakes regions in - 1671 which was about the same time that Robert Cavelier de La Salle made some preliminary investigations down in the headwaters of the Mississippi River. In the following year Jacques Marquette explored the region around Chicago and a few years later, with Father Louis Jolliet, went down the Mississippi to the Arkansas tributary. (Ref. 51)

We noted above, in the section on Canada, that La Salle obtained some permits from the French crown to continue studies of the Mississippi. He and his party left Fort Frontenac (Kingston, Ontario) in the fall of 1678 and after some backtracking, failure to get more funds from the French king and other troubles, La Salle and his trusted aid De Tonty arrived at the Miamis River in November, 1681 with a party of 23 Frenchmen, 18 savages, Abenakis5, and Loups, 10 Indian women and 3 children. They reached the Mississippi in February 1682 and on their course down river first fell in with the Chickasaw Indians, who practiced the flattening of the heads of their children. They reached the Gulf of Mexico on April 7, 1682 and formally took possession in the name of Louis XIV.

Some of the adventures and hardships experienced by La Salle's company on its trip down the Mississippi are best taken from La Salle's own Memoirs, as translated in 1844 by Falconer (Ref. 52). La Salle wrote that he undertook the trip to satisfy the wish of the late Monseigneur Colbert, finance minister of France, of finding a port where the French might establish themselves and harass the Spaniards in those regions from where they derived all their wealth. He described the mouth of the Mississippi by saying that the coast and the banks were overflowed for more than 20 leagues above the mouth, making it inaccessible by land. He told of an assembly of more than 18,000 Indians of various nations, some of whom had come from a distance of more than 2,000 leagues (probably 600 to 700 miles) to throw themselves "into his arms". Because these Indians had already carried on war against the Spaniards, even without firearms, La Salle felt that it would be possible to form an army of more than 15,000 savages who would follow him to attack the adjacent provinces where there were not more than 400 native Spanish. He was apparently speaking of New Bisca, the most northern province of Mexico. He strongly advised the French crown to consider settling the Mississippi mouth region because "-firstly, the service of God may be established there by the preaching of the Gospel to numerous docile and settled nations--. They have already temples and a form of worship." He added that provinces which might be seized were very rich in silver mines; that the river itself was navigable for more than a 100 leagues for ships and 500 leagues for barks and overall for more than 800 miles from east to west.

Concerning the trip down the river, itself, the following information has been taken from writings of both La Salle and the Cavalier Henry de Tonty, as translated again by Falkoner. (Ref. 53) La Salle actually made 5 voyages under extraordinary hardships, extending over more than 5,000 leagues, most commonly on foot, through snow and water, almost without rest over 5 years. He traversed more than 600 leagues of unknown country among many barbarous and cannibalistic nations, against whom he was obliged to fight almost daily, although he was accompanied by only 38 men. Many of the various tribes he encountered lived in settled villages consisting of hundreds of cabins, of ten made of mud, with cane mats. In one such village the cabin of the chief was 40 feet square, the walls 10 feet high and 1 foot thick, with a 15 feet high, dome-shaped roof. The chief was seated on a camp bed with 3 of his wives and more than 60 old men, clothed in large white cloaks of mulberry bark were present. Sieur de Tonty was told that when the chief dies, his youngest wife, his house-steward and 100 men accompany him into the other world. In one village of the Natchez, there were more than 300 warriors. De Tonty contrasts these lower Mississippi people with those in Illinois- who lived in some of the finest lands he had ever seen. He said the Illinois Indians were brave but extremely lazy, except in war, when they think nothing of seeking their enemies at a distance of 600 leagues. Polygamy prevailed there also.

Finally La Salle's application to form a colony on the south of the Mississippi was authorized and this time he approached from the sea in the summer of 1684, with 4 vessels. Unfortunately, after passing Cuba they inadvertently missed the river and finally landed in what appears to have been Matagora Bay. La Salle built a fort there, left 130 men to man it and then left in March, 1685 with another 50 men to find the Mississippi. Still not locating his goal, he built another fort on a river he named "Vaches" and abandoning the first fort, 70 men, women and children moved to this new place. But 30 of his company had died and the master carpenter had been lost. Still this second fort had more people than the colony of Smith of Virginia or of those who embarked in the Mayflower. This was the settlement on which France based claims that Texas was a part of Louisiana.

While La Salle's ship Belle sailed along the coast with his papers and equipment, he took 20 men and started overland, still seeking the Mississippi delta. He returned in 4 months but the Belle had apparently been lost. The leader then selected 20 men to accompany him back to Canada overland, leaving the fort on April 22, 1686. He became ill on the Trinity River, however, and had to return to Vaches. There then remained about 40 of the original 180 people, who had landed in Texas. La Salle again started north in January of 1687 only to be assassinated along with some of his most faithful followers, by a group of 4 disgruntled Frenchmen, at Navasoto, Texas. A few of the party eventually reached St. Louis, where De Tonty was found. In the spring of 1686 he had sailed down the Mississippi and, reaching the sea, had sent canoes east and west, vainly seeking his old companion and friend. The few survivors left in Texas from La Salle's expedition were subsequently either captured by Indians or by Spaniards, and taken to Mexico. (Ref. 54, 55)

The failure of this expedition did not deter the French government in its pursuit of Gulf settlement. In 1697 the Canadian D'lberville sailed down the Mississippi and with other voyages planted a colony which he left in charge of his brother Bienville. The brave and generous De Tonty joined D'lberville at the mouth of the Mississippi about the year 1700. (Ref. 56) This was at about the same time that Cadillac was founding a fort at Detroit in the north.

THE SOUTHWEST

Governor Don Juan de Onate set up the first Spanish government in the southwest at Santa Fe, 10 years before the Pilgrims landed in Massachusetts. For the next 200 years Spanish outposts in Arizona, Texas, California and New Mexico slowly developed an economy. The Spanish introduced 2 indispensable elements in the life of western America - the horse and the cow. The horse, originally terrifying the Indians, eventually set them free from Mexico to the Canadian tundra. The Spanish also left the whole heraldry of ranching in the language - corral, mesa, arroya, patio, adobe, mustang, sombrero, desperado, poncho, alfalfa, bronco, lariat and others. (Ref. 57) By 1630 there were 1,000 people in Santa Fe and the immediate area, including 250 garrisoned soldiers. There were 50 friars distributed in 90 villages, each with their own church.

Trouble between civil and church authorities was not long in appearing. By 1680 the population in the area had increased to 2,800 and there were towns at Pecos, Taos, Santa Cruz, San Marcos, etc. but all were evacuated when an Indian revolt of Zuni, Hopi, Tano and Keres Indians, under Pope', revolted. Some 2,000 refugees reached El Paso. Pope' made himself governor, but his bad reign and a long drought led to disarray, allowing recapture of this area of present day New Mexico and western Texas by Diego de Vargas rather easily in 1692. (Ref. 58, 59)

Alonso de Leon had established a mission at San Francisco de los Tejas, near the Neches River in 1690, but it was abandoned in 1693. (Ref. 60) Father Eusebio Kino visited the Pima Indians on the Gila River in southern Arizona in 1697 and, finding them friendly, he established a mission near present day Tucson, in 1700. The Pima were experts with bow and arrow and had war clubs and rawhide shields. (Ref. 61)

THE FAR WEST

The Great Plains and the far west were certainly moderately populated with many and varied Indian tribes in this century, but in the absence of contact with whites little accurate information is available. The reader is referred to the l8th and l9th centuries.

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

Already Mexican Society was divided into several classes based chiefly on race and color. First there were the Indians, living primarily in their villages under the rule of the caciques, with their numbers greatly dwindled. The second class was the Creoles, a white population born in Mexico and descendants of the conquistadores. Next were the Mestizos, who were half -breeds, half Indian and half white and finally the Gachupines, natives of Spain sent over for administration. Instead of being incorporated into Spanish civilization the Indians regarded all white men as their enemies and the Creole landowners encroached on the Indian villages' land. Government attempts to protect the Indians were foiled by corrupt officials and Indian ignorance of the law. (Ref. 62) The few remaining primitive Chichimec Indians of the north Mexican desert were still being hunted and run to earth "like wild animals". (Ref. 63)

The decay of the Spanish Empire in Europe did not enable the Creoles to usurp powers of self-government, however, because they were themselves victims of the Gachupin bureaucracy. This bureaucracy tapped the wealth produced by the labor of the native population. On the surface all was peace, passivity and decay, but explosive forces were slowly developing. Communications remained primitive; there were no roads; and Mexican industry was suppressed in part because of jealousy of the Spanish merchants. Mexico was unable to develop any native commercial class.

The drop in the Indian population of Mexico in just 5 or 6 generations was almost unbelievable although the exact figures are still being debated. Tannahill (Ref. 64) says that by 1605 central Mexico had only 1,075,000 people, down from 25,000,000 at the time of Cortez and that the decrease was due to war, economic upheaval, exploitation and new diseases, representing one of the most comprehensive human catastrophes of the world. The deliberate encouragement of alcohol in the forms of pulque and mezcal among the Indians must also have been a deteriorating factor. State revenue from pulque in New Spain was equal to one-half the revenue from the silver mines. (Ref. 65) William McNeill (Ref. 66) writes that the entire population of Mexico was, at 1,600,000 in 1620, a 90% drop with drastic psychological and cultural consequences. Faith in established institutions and belief s cannot withstand such disaster and skills and knowledge disappear. Thus, it was easy for the Spaniards to transfer their language and culture to the New World.

Masses of goods were shipped from Seville to Central - America and the responsible merchants expected to be paid in silver bullion. In 1637 there were allegedly heaps of silver wedges lying in the street in Porto Belo, Panama. Most of this, of course, had been brought up from the Potosi mines of South America. (Ref. 67) The silver was landed at the port of Panama and then moved by mules and boats (on the Chagres River) across the isthmus to Porto Belo on the Caribbean. But the muleteers and boatmen had to be fed maize, which itself was imported from Nicaragua or Chile. The year 1626 was a barren year and 100 to 150 tons of maize had to be obtained from Peru to keep the silver going. (Ref. 68) The Welch buccaneer, Henry Morgan, captured Panama City in a treaty violation with Spain, but although at first put on trial, he eventually was made Lt. Governor of Jamaica and put in charge of ending piracy. (Ref. 69) In 1695 the Spanish started to build a road from Campeche to Guatemala and encountered many ancient buildings on deserted, overgrown terraces, the remnants of the previous Indian civilizations. (Ref. 70) Yucatec-speaking Indians, fleeing disease and general disruption, went from the rain forests of Guatemala, with their bows and arrows into the region of Chiapas, Mexico, where they were subsequently known as the "Lacandon Maya". (Ref. 71)

The society of New Spain was dominated by the clerical heirarchy. Beneath an archbishop were 8 other bishops and members of the Inquisition. The Indians became Catholics while still remaining pagan; the clergy rapidly became degenerate, while growing richer. The ideal of the New World Church - or at least that of many of its clergy - was a despotic government, a privileged priesthood and an ignorant laity. (Ref. 72)

Every European major power was interested in the "sugar islands" of the Caribbean and there were many possessions and trading of island territories between Spain, France, England and Holland. (Ref. 73) The Dutch had brought the cane from Brazil when they were expelled from Recife in 1654 and it soon reached Martinique, Guadeloupe, Dutch Curacao, Jamaica and Santo Domingo. After 1685 production showed an uninterrupted increase and this sugar production required a tremendous labor force, this resulting in the black slave importation. But cane left little space for food crops and edibles had to be imported from Europe or North America. The same could be said about the lack of skilled craftsmen and engineers6. Even nails and boilers for the sugar mills had to be brought from Europe. (Ref. 74, 75)

England established colonies on Bermuda in 1612, Barbados in 1627, and Jamaica in 1655. By 1676 some 400 ships, each carrying about 180 tons of sugar, left Jamaica.

By 1690 there were an estimated 40,000 slaves on that island, working the sugar estates and their revolts and desertions resulted in almost continuous military action throughout the last decades of this century. (Ref. 77) The British from Bermuda began settling the Bahamas in mid-century but were subject to pirate raids by Spanish and French and they did not establish real sovereignty until late in the next century. (Ref. 78) It was not until 1680 that sugar spread to the western half of the island of St. Domingue, which had been French until the middle of the century.

By this century the Caribbean Taino Indians were extinct and the African slaves took the places of these vanishing Americans, perhaps in part because they were resistant to malaria. This disease arrived in the Gulf area after 1650, with the imported Africans. The first epidemic of yellow fever occurred in Guadeloupe and St. Kitts in 1635 and in Yucatan and Havana in 1648 after the Aedes Aegypti mosquito had voyaged over on ships from Africa. As a result of these diseases even the whites decreased in numbers or disappeared as the blacks increased. (Ref. 79, 80) Overall perhaps as many as 340,000 black slaves were brought from Africa in this century alone. (Ref. 81, 82) Settlement in these West Indies was for a long time more extensive than on the American mainland, however, and by 1700 there were 121,000 inhabitants in this area.

SOUTH AMERICA

NORTHERN AND WESTERN SOUTH AMERICA

Even at the beginning of this 17th century the Spanish were continuing to search for "Eldorado, the Land of Gold", but up to the early decades, except for a few nuggets of gold, a fairly good supply of emeralds and some cinnamon, there was little to show for the century of exploration. The entire west coast of the continent had been explored, however, and the foundations had been laid for every one of the 20 republics of Central and South America, excepting Argentina. In one generation the Spaniards had acquired more territory than Rome conquered in 5 centuries-and the Spaniards organized and administered all that they conquered. (Ref. 83) The Spanish New World was first divided into two great viceroyalties of Nueva Espana (Mexico) and Peru, to which La Plata (Argentina and Chile) and Nueva Granada (Columbia and Venezuela) were later added. Portuguese traders had infiltrated all of Spanish America. Even in a town like Santiago, Chile, with 10,000 people, one could find a Portuguese merchant. They often also doubled as bankers and occasionally, as in Potosi in 1634, public opinion accused them of being "new Christians" or even Jews and subsequent Inquisition trials put an end to their property. (Ref. 84)

By 1650 Potosi, in Bolivia, was the largest city in South America, with 160,000 people, with Indian peasants forced to work in the great silver mines under extreme hardship conditions. (Ref. 85) The South American Indians felt that they could not work or go on trips without chewing the coca leaf mixed with ground lime. Containing cocaine, this half-stimulant and half-narcotic does deaden fatigue, pain, and hunger and facilitates breathing at high altitudes. The terrible effects of widespread use of the purified drug, however, are now becoming all too obvious in the United States. (Ref. 86) It is not well known, but statistics from the archives of the Peruvian viceroyalty show that at least 300,000 Africans were brought into Peru in this century. By that time the number of native Indians had fallen to 700,000 so one may judge the impact of this importation of blacks. The lowlands of Ecuador and Colombia had also been Africanized to an unknown degree. In the highlands of the Andes, however, any African traits are ancient and from tropical Asiatic (Melanesian or Australoid) fringes or even of ancient Atlantic crossings by Africans.

EASTERN AND CENTRAL SOUTH AMERICA

Only in this century did the Portuguese finally win tremendous areas in the New World. Economic and political power was concentrated in the hands of great plantation owners in Brazil. By 1623 there were 350 sugar plantations in that country and 25 years later there were 150,000 to 200,000 civilized people, with 3/4 being Indian, Negroes or "Mixed". The state of Maranhao was created and Jesuit missions were established along the Amazon. In 1635 the Dutch invaded and occupied the whole northern part of Brazil and a little later they wrested the whole Gold Coast from Portugal. They were thrown out in 1654, but in the meantime, the locals had learned a great deal about sugar production from the Dutch. At the end of the century slaving operations in the interior of Brazil were being resisted by the Jesuits, who tried to protect the Indians.

Gold was found in 1690 in the central region of Minas Gerais, today one of the richest states in Brazil. A few years later diamonds were also found in the same region. (Ref. 87) As in Central America, malaria arrived with the African Negro and yellow fever came only slightly later. (Ref. 88, 89, 90)

In central South America, east of the Andes, and in the more temperate southern zone were wide open lands suitable for sheep and cattle breeders. The original Gauchos, who were mixed Spanish and Indian and almost entirely lawless, preyed on those cattle, simulating in many respects the old nomads of central Asia of a thousand years earlier. (Ref. 91) Since indigenous animals were few in what later became Argentina, the empty countryside was soon filled with European horses and cattle, which banded in wild herds across the great pampas and so existed until the 1 9th century. The Indians had some of those horses, too, so that the natives of Argentina and particularly the Araucanians of Chile continued to be tough adversaries for another two centuries. (Ref. 92)

Paraguay was founded by Jesuits in 1608. (Ref. 93) It is of some interest that the first Europeans to sail around Cape Horn, instead of through the Strait of Magellan, were the Dutchmen Willem Corneliszoon Schouten and Jacob Le Maire and the cape was named after the former's birthplace, Hoorn. They were en route to Indonesia in 1615. (Ref. 94)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

3 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

4 [218] de TOCQUEVILLE, ALEX15, Ibid. Volume II. (Original publication in 1840).

5 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

6 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

7 [217] de TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

8 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

9 [63] FALCONER, THOMAS, Discovery of the Mississippi. (London, 1844 - as reprinted by Shoal Creek Publishers, Inc. Austin, Texas, 1975).

10 [212] TANNER, OGDEN, The Canadians. (Time-Life Books Inc., Alexandria, Va. 1977).

11 [253] BECKER, MARSHALL J., "Search for the Lenape Indians", Archeology 35: No. 3, 10-19, May/June, 1982.

12 [293] EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

13 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

14 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

15 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

16 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

17 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

18 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

19 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

20 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

21 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

22 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

23 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

24 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

25 [217]  DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

26 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

27 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

28 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

29 151. MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

30 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

31 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

32 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

33 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

34 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

35 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

36 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

37 [102] HUME, IVOR NOEL, "First look at a Lost Virginia Settlement," National Geographic. June, 1979, page 735.

38 [103] HUME, IVOR NOEL, "New Clues to an Old Mystery", National Geographic 161: 53-77, Jan. 1982.

39 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

40 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

41 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

42 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

43 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

44 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

45 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

46 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

47 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

48 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

49 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

50 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

51 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

52 [63] FALCONER, THOMAS, Discovery of the Mississippi. (London, 1844 - as reprinted by Shoal Creek Publishers, Inc. Austin, Texas, 1975).

53 [63] FALCONER, THOMAS, Discovery of the Mississippi. (London, 1844 - as reprinted by Shoal Creek Publishers, Inc. Austin, Texas, 1975).

54 [63] FALCONER, THOMAS, Discovery of the Mississippi. (London, 1844 - as reprinted by Shoal Creek Publishers, Inc. Austin, Texas, 1975).

55 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

56 [63] FALCONER, THOMAS, Discovery of the Mississippi. (London, 1844 - as reprinted by Shoal Creek Publishers, Inc. Austin, Texas, 1975).

57 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

58 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

59 [83] HALLETT ROBIN, Africa to 1875. (The University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor, 1970).

60 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

61 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

62 [167] PARSON, JAMES J. AND DENEVEN, WILLIAM M., "Pre-Columbian Ridged Fields", Scientific American July, 1967, page 93.

63 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

64 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

65 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

66 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

67 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

68 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

69 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

70 [205] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Ibid. Volume II.

71 [283] NATIONS, HAMES D. AND CLARK, JOHN E., "The Bows and Arrows of the Lacandon Maya", Archaeology 36, Vol. I: 36-43, Jan./Feb. 1983.

72 [166] PARKES, HENRY BAMFORD, A History of Mexico. (Houghton Miff lin Co., Boston. The Riverside Press, Cambridge).

73 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

74 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

75 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

76 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

77 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

78 [274] BENCHLEY, PETER, "The Bahamas", National Geographic 162: 365-395, Sept. 1982.

79 [150] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, Admiral of the Ocean Sea. A Life of ChristopherColumbus. (Little, Brown & Co., Boston 1942).

80 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

81 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

82 [160] OXENSTIERNA, ERIC, "The Vikings", Scientific American, May 1967.

83 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

84 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

85 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

86 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

87 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

88 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

89 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

90.MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

91 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

92 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

93 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

94 [134] MAY, CHARLES Paul, Oceania: Polynesia, Melanesia, Micronesia. (Thomas Nelson, Inc., Nashville, Tenn. 1973).

1.  This information is found in de Tocqueville (Ref. 4), pages 337 and 338).

2.  Dobyns was a source mentioned by Wright (Ref. 19), page 24.

3.  Quotation from page 30 of de Tocqueville (Ref. 33)

4.  This is the date given by Alestair Cooke (Ref. 40), but de Tocqueville, quoting Beverley's History of Virginia, says the date was 1621. (Ref. 41), page 360

5.  La Saile differentiated "savages" from Abenakis. The latter were also called Abnakis and MicMacs, of the Algonquin group. Their apparent differences from the other natives are of interest with respect to Fell's concepts recorded on page 269.

6.  These were also lacking in colonial America. (Ref. 76)

America: A.D. 1701 to 1800

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

CANADA AND THE FAR NORTH

When Vitus Bering found the strait which bears his name he also explored the Aleutian chain of islands and the Alaska shores, living on sea otters and starting a new fur trade. By 1745 ruthless Russian hunters were established on Attu Island, where they killed all male Aleuts and took their women. Later, however, they found that they had to keep Aleut males to help them hunt the otters in their ulluxtadags (similar to Eskimo kayaks) with harpoons and they then merged and lived together with the Aleuts. In 1784 Grigorii Shelekhov established a settlement on Kodiak Island and founded what became the Russian-American Company. They obtained otter and seal pelts, using 7,200 Aleuts to hunt full-time and taking 300 others as hostages to ensure work from the first group. This broke up the Aleut families and then disease appeared, so that in the two generations at the end of the century, the Aleut population fell by nearly two-thirds. (Ref. 1, 2) Shelekhov was followed by Alexander Baranov, who greeted British ships and found English, American and even a few Spanish skippers had been trading for furs some 1,100 miles south. In 1799 he sailed along the shore with 450 two-man kayaks to establish a colony on Baranov Island, just 6 miles above a Tlingits Indian stronghold at what is now Sitka, Alaska. Those Tlingits had inhabited the lower coastal area of the Alaskan panhandle for a long period and had a high culture, living in gabled lodges housing a dozen families and producing canoes holding 60 men. One of their better known features were their 50 feet tall totem poles. North of the Tlingits were the Eskimoes along the Arctic shoreline living, as the Aleuts on the islands, by hunting chiefly seals and walruses. In central Alaska were the Athabascan Indians, bearing no cultural resemblance to the coastal people. They are linguistic cousins of the Apaches and Navajos and lived in small nomadic bands in bare simplicity, existing chiefly on the caribou. They did create the snow-shoe to facilitate getting about in deep snow. (Ref. 3)1

1 They had a relative high standard of living with art, music, medicine, some surgery and mummification. After the Russians arrived the Aleuts were essentially enslaved and their numbers dropped to 3,200. (Ref. 4) It is interesting to note that before his famous voyages to the Pacific James Cook was an officer aboard the Eagle for 2 years after war started between England and France (1758) and then as master of a ship he charted much of the east coast of Canada between the years 1762 and 1769. He helped in the battle of Louisberg and Quebec on the St. Lawrence. (Ref. 5)

By 1745 when the Russians were already well established in the Aleutians, the English had only a handful of isolated trading posts west of Hudson Bay. (Ref. 6) On the west coast of Canada, Don Juan Francisco de la Bodega sailed the "Sonora" beyond the 56th degree latitude and examined the coast belonging to Russia,- which is now the upper of British Columbia. Then in 1778 while Captain Cook was sailing up the coast to reach the Aleutians, he incidentally discovered Nootka sound on Vancouver Island. Spanish historians claim, however, that Juan Perez had discovered this sound previously in 1774.

On the Atlantic side, in 1711 Britain attempted to take French Quebec and Canada, by sending seven regiments of Marlborough's best, along with 1,500 colonials into the St. Lawrence. Ten of their ships were sunk and the expedition f ailed. The war in Europe ended 2 years later, however, and France's position in southeastern Canada was greatly weakened by the Treaty of Utrecht, which terminated the War of the Spanish Succession, or Queen Anne's war, as it was called in America. (Ref. 7) France lost Newfoundland,

Nova Scotia and the Hudson Bay area to England and Canada as a whole was impoverished.

While thousands of sturdy Germans, French, Protestant Scots, etc., were pouring into the English colonies, the government of Louis XV allowed only a mere trickle to go to Canada. The population of Canada in 1713 was only 18,119, although this had doubled by 1734. In the 30 years after 1713 the French spent $6,000,000 in gold building a fortress on Cape Breton Island, which menaced English fisheries, but was useless in war time. They also built forts on Lake Champlain, at Niagara Falls and two on the Wabash. In 1744 the War of Jenkins' Ear with Spain merged into the War of the Austrian Succession (King George's War in America) in which England and Austria were allies against France and Prussia. The French and their Indian allies raided New England and the Iroquois raided Canada. The Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle ended that war, with France retaining the Louisburg fort on Cape Breton Island. In mid-century the English settlers in Nova Scotia fought with the local French Acadians and the latter were deported in mass some 6,000 to 7 ,000 strong. Some ended up in Louisiana to became the "Cajuns". (Ref. 8)

The Seven Years War in Europe spilled over into the f inal French and Indian War in America (1755-1763) and the Peace of Paris signed the death knoll for France in America. (Ref. 9) Quebec had fallen in 1759 and Montreal in 1760. (Ref. 10) The French people in southern Canada, however, continued a self-consciousness and intolerance, with their grievances carrying on to the present time. This was in spite of the fact that the British government, by the Quebec Act of 1774 guaranteed the French settlers free exercise of their religion, language and law (Old French civil law), as well as expanding the boundaries of the new Canadian colony to the Mississippi and Ohio rivers. This, incidentally, was interpreted as harmful to Virginia and Pennsylvania and was one factor, along with the Coercive Acts, in lighting the fuse for revolution in the lower thirteen colonies. (Ref. 11) Actually the British were not overjoyed with their conquest and tried to trade Canada back to the French, soon, in exchange for the island of Guadeloupe. *** (Page 1201)

Map taken from Reference 97.

The Canadian northwest was opened by Scottish merchants in slender canoes and by the French voyageurs. The fur trade reached its zenith in the 1790s. Montreal was the chief supply center with great loads of supplies leaving in flotillas of 30 some canoes, each 40 feet long and carrying 8 to 10 voyageurs. They would travel 1,600 miles, up the Ottowa River, then down the French River into Georgian Bay and the North Channel of Lake Huron, across Sault Ste. Marie into Lake Superior, then across the Grand Portage to the Pigeon River. In the western part of the route the canoes were a little shorter, at 25 feet, but they still carried 6 to 8 men and 1 ~ tons of cargo, while drawing only 18 inches of water. These northmen were French or mixed French-Indian and were small, not over 5'5" in height. They traveled on smooth water at 4 miles per hour, sometimes for 16 hours a day. Sled dogs and Indian wives completed their necessities. (Ref. 12)

In 1791 Parliament passed the Canada Act, dividing the region into Upper and Lower Canada, this roughly corresponding to English and French areas, respectively. For a quarter of a century there was peace. The Canadian Pacific coast had been ~ailed in the 1780s and in 1792 Captain George Vancouver explored and surveyed the region now bearing his name. Alexander Mackenzie went overland to the Pacific in 1793 as the first European to cross this continent, coast to coast. His route was by canoe west from Lake Athabasca, up the Pease River, portage across the Rockies to the Parsnip, then the Fraser, Blackwater and Bella Coola rivers, in turn, to the Pacific. (Ref. 13) He used Pemmican (Cree name for "fat") as part of his food supply. This was made by drying thin-sliced, lean meat over a fire, then pounding it to shreds and mixing it with an almost equal amount of melted fat, along with some marrow and a few handfuls of wild cherries (later currants or sugar were used), after which it was packed in rawhide sacks tightly sewed and sealed with tallow. This food supplied adequate calories for survival. An additional travel food was a dried corn meal pancake called "Johnnycake". (Ref. 14) By 1800 trappers and traders had crisscrossed the continent many times. (Ref. 15)

At the last of the century Spain was at war with Great Britain and in 1789 the Spanish Captain Martinez siezed 4 British ships in Nootka sound. This started a year's dispute terminated by a convention of October, 1790 in which it was agreed that all had a right to navigating and fishing in the Pacific and of making settlements there, but the British should not do so within 10 leagues of any coastal area already occupied by Spain.

Because of the warm Japan Current, much of the Canadian western coast land (and adjacent islands) is warm, with great forests and rivers teeming with salmon. The Haida, Kwakiutl and Bella Coola Indians lived too easily there and had so much leisure time that they could create great native civilizations, with a culture expressed in wood-working, including magnificently carved totem poles, some SO feet high and lodges as large as 3,000 square feet. They had sea-gray canoes holding 50 men. (Ref. 16) (See pages 269,374 and 568)

Meanwhile in the far eastern North American region, Danish missionaries and traders had brought fabrics, implements and some new foods to the Greenland Eskimos. Although the latter kept their old customs of using kayaks and harpoons for seal hunts, they now used guns for killing caribou. They lived in communal houses of stone and turf. (Ref. 17)

THE UNITED STATES

AREA OF ORIGINAL 13 COLONIES (AND FLORIDA)

The eastern colonies had 250,000 people at the beginning of this century. By 1750, including the 100,000 Negro slaves, the colonies were almost one-third as populous as England itself. (Ref. 18) By 1776 the population had increased to about 2 1/2 million. Patterns of migration changed during the century, with Scotch, Welch, Irish, Germans and Dutch arriving in ever increasing numbers. Some Scandinavians, Swiss, Belgians and French signed terms of indenture by the thousands in order to get to America. The mixture by 1763 has been estimated at 50% English, 18% Scotch and Scotch-Irish, 18% African, 6% German and 3% Dutch, thus already a "melting pot". (Ref. 19) Europe had no need for food products from the colonies, such as grain, meat and butter so these things were sold to the Caribbean and the bills of exchange so obtained were used for purchasing manufactured items from the British Isles. It was different with tobacco and even by 1723 some 200 ships carried 30,000 kegs a year to England, where it was re-exported to northern Europe. (Ref. 20) Gradually a few other products were shipped directly across the Atlantic. Just before the American Revolution, South Carolina sent more than a million pounds of indigo to England. (Ref. 21)

By 1733 there were 13 colonies but each had its own government, currency, trade laws and religious ways, so that they were actually like 13 nations. The middle colonies produced the most flexible societies, giving birth to the first real cities, with business men and ports and trades and yet were basically agrarian. The plantar society of the south was a fluid aristocracy, open to labor and talent, while New England was controlled by a Puritan oligarchy. (Ref. 22) New colleges were built at Princeton1 and what are now known as Columbia and University of Pennsylvania. The first American newspaper was published in Boston in April, 1704. (Ref. 23) New York state was hampered in land expansion because of the Iroquois Confederacy land and it was only in 6th place in population as late as 1760. Boston ladies imitated the manners of the court of King James and all colonials were concerned with social status. Virginia society became stabilized with brave gallants, fair women, horse races and fox hunting. There was no middle class there because if one was white he was either of first family or a frontiersman. The colonies had rum distilleries, using molasses from the Indies and there was an iron industry in Virginia, in spite of English laws forbidding this, in 1750. By 1775 there were more furnaces and forges in the colonies than in England and Wales together. A most serious handicap was the English restriction on colonial use of money, forbidding the export of English coin to the colonies and prohibiting any local mint coinage. As a result the locals used Spanish milled dollars, or "pieces of eight", and paper money and bills of credit. In every colony south of Maryland, Negro slaves outnumbered white servants by 1720 and the proportion of blacks continued to increase. In Virginia in 1756 there were 120,156 Negroes out of a total population of 293,474. There were some slave insurrections, the chief one being the Cato Conspiracy in 1739. (Ref. 24)

As an American aspect of the War of the Spanish Succession at the beginning of the century, fighting developed between Carolinians and their Chickasaw allies against the Spanish in Pensacola, and locally this was called "Queen Anne's War". The Goose Creek men that we met in the last chapter continued their mischief in the l8th century. In 1704 the Barbadian, James Moore, and 50 Goose Creek men led 1,000 Creeks, Yamasees and Apalachicolas against the province of Apalachee. Missions and Franciscans alike were burned and Moore returned to Carolina boasting of having 4,000 women and children as slaves and an additional 1,300 who voluntarily joined with him. In addition, he killed or enslaved 325 men, not including the captives taken by his Indian allies. Perhaps 200 Apalachees escaped and f led westward to Mobile, where French padres put them in new missions and a few sought refuge near St. Augustine. Moore and his Creeks and Yamasees charged on into Florida, ravaging Timucuans, burning their towns, plundering livestock and taking captives. Pensacola, 500 miles south of Charleston, suffered a similar fate and even the Keys were attacked by the Indians in canoes. Unable to protect them because of involvement in Queen Anne's War, Spain shipped hundreds of the Florida Indians, including the remnants of the Calusas and Tequetas, Apalachees, Guales and Timucuans, to Cuba. (Ref. 26)

In the meantime Carolina had some Indian troubles of its own. The Tuscaroras, of Iroquoian stock, occupied much of North Carolina's Tidewater and they had been traditional enemies of the Algonquian tribes. Probably because white colonists were allying themselves with the latter, the Tuscarora suddenly turned on the whites in 1711. For 2 years full scale war raged with the Tuscarora fighting both the colonists and some of the Algonquian tribes, who were supplied by Virginia and North and South Carolina authorities. Finally some 1,000 Tuscaroras were taken captive and sold. In 19714 a still more destructive war erupted, one somewhat erroneously called "the Yamasee War". Actually there were many natives in addition to the Yamasee, including Lower Creeks, Guales, Apalachees, Savannahs, Cherokees, Yuchis, Cheraws, Catawbas, Waterees and Waccamaws who attacked the whites. Some played greater roles than others. Many of these tribes were components of the old Chiefdom of Cofitachiqui and in a way this was the native response to the commercial empire of the Goose Creek men. Losses on both sides were high - 400 colonists perished, some 6% of the white population. On the Indian side, many of the participating tribes simply became extinct. Port Royal remained deserted for years. Generally disorganized, the colonists revolted against proprietary rule in 1719 and claimed South Carolina a royal colony.

Even before their war on the colonists in 1711 the Tuscaroras were the most powerful nation in the North Carolina Tidewater and for years they had fallen on their weaker neighbors and sold captives to the Virginians and North Carolinians. Slave raids, wars and especially diseases eventually swept away almost all Timucuans, Appalachees, Tequestas and eventually even the Yamasees. Some Lower Creeks remained in Florida, destroying and mixing with aboriginal remnants of other tribes and by the latter third of the 18th century - these Indians became known as Seminoles. The Creek Chief Cowkeeper, who settled in the Gainesville region, according to some, is the progenitor of the Seminole nation. (Ref. 27) (See also page 1015)

Europeans customarily branded slaves and this was carried on in the United States. In 1716 commissioners in charge of the Carolina Indian trade sent branding irons to agents in the back country to mark deerskins and captives, alike. The latter were marked on the face, shoulder or arm. Through this 18th century tens of thousands of southern Indians were enslaved and most of these were women and children. Indians worked for whites as wage laborers, tilling fields, rounding up cattle and as domestics, hunters and artisans. pamunkey women worked as maids. Many female Indian servants murdered their offspring, either to escape a whipping, an increased period of service or perhaps just to keep their children from growing up in an alien world. The men sometimes carried peltry for 200 or even 500 miles for the Goose Creek men. In excellent physical condition, some of these Indian men impressed the colonists by keeping up with a man on horseback for 10 or 20 miles, apparently without fatigue. They learned new occupations such as serving on board oceangoing vessels and learning to care for and ride horses. Each village was apt to have a resident factor, an Englishman or more likely a Scot, but some factors were Indians, mestizos or occasionally blacks. The natives' appetite for trading goods and drink exceeded their ability to pay and they were frequently in debt. (Ref. 28)

At the beginning of the century Anglicans redoubled their efforts to send missionaries among the Indians to learn their languages and establish schools. The Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts (SPG) was founded for that purpose in 1701. The Archbishop of Canterbury was a founder and colonial governors and commissaries were members, as were laymen on both sides of the Atlantic. Inevitably there developed a close association between SPG and English imperialism. There was little distinction between extending the flag and spreading the faith. A search was made to find a lingua franca which could be comprehended by most southern Indians. An Algonquian tongue spoken by the Savannahs (Shawnees) was considered, but the Muskhogean Yamasee was better as it could be understood throughout much of the south as a second, if not a first language. Schools were established, including one in connection with William and Mary College, but there were never many in attendance and little was really accomplished. In the long run the SPG was most successful with Mohawks in upper New York, where missionaries did conduct services in the Mohawk language. We have mentioned the Yamasee rebellion in the latter half of the century, after which those Indians were implacable enemies of the British as long as any of them survived. The SPG was shocked. (Ref. 29)

After 1715 the two largest Indian tribes adjacent to South Carolina were the Creeks and Cherokees and there was some attempt to Christianize them. A German, Christian Priber, a versatile scholar and lawyer conversant in several languages, went to live among them, dressed as a native, learned their language and tried to establish a socialist community on the frontier. He educated the Indians, explaining how traders' scales, weights and measures worked so that the British colonists assumed he was a French agent trying to turn the natives against them. They sought him out and imprisoned him.

Except for the Floridas, which Britain acquired in 1763 and held for 20 years, Georgia was the last southern colony, founded in 1733, more than 60 years after the birth of Charleston. After 10 years of Trustee rule, Georgia's white population was at most 3,000, but on the eve of the Revolution, Georgia contained 18,000 free whites and almost as many slaves. The original trustees did have ideals,- however, including the prohibition of drinking, the outlawing of Negro slavery and some restriction on the size of land holdings. This did not keep the Georgians from using Indian slaves, however, and by 1750 the trustees legalized all types of slavery. James Oglethorpe was the only trustee who actually went to Georgia and he appointed Charles Wesley his secretary for Indian affairs and John Wesley as an ordained missionary of the SPG. John decided to go into the Chickasaw country to learn their language and customs, but various complications kept him from accomplishing that and his ministry was not successful. Oglethorpe persuaded the Yamacraw chief, his wife, nephew and a handful of others to return with him to England in 1734, where the Reverend Samuel Smith instructed them in the Creed, the Lord's Prayer and the Commandments. This was about the extent of the Georgia conversion.

We shall return to the traditional history of the American colonies, the problems in the "Old Northwest", the French and Indians War and finally the American Revolution at a later time, but feeling that school texts have overlooked much material about the southern Indians and their relationships with the whites and imported Africans, we shall devote a few additional paragraphs to these subjects. At times the Indians cooperated with the British, as when Creeks, Yamacraws and Cherokees helped Oglethorpe in battles with Spanish troops, who attacked St. Simons Island in 1742. Natives crewed the scout boats used for communications along the chain of sea island forts and they raided Florida, killing or capturing unwary Spaniards, Yamasees and Negroes. At other times the Indians fought the colonists, but in between there was considerable merging of red, white and black races.

In this 18th century Creeks constituted one of the largest racially heterogeneous tribes. Other more or less "pure-bred" tribes, such as the Catawbas, had existed, but now there were only a few hundred of them left and the Catawba language had been lost. Various Catawbas conversed in assorted tongues belonging to several different language families. The first mention of the term "Seminole" was in 1771 and it was probably taken from the Spanish cimarron (wild) which became simanoli in Chickasaw. Lower and then Upper Creeks drifting into Florida formed the nucleus of the Seminole "nation", with a few remnants from earlier days - Calusas and Tequestas. (See also page 1013). There never was a unified Seminole nation and those Indians then, as today, did not necessarily understand one another. The Lumbees of southeastern North Carolina offer an even more bizarre grouping. Numbering still some 40,000 today, they constitute one of the largest tribes in the United States, but actually they are an aggregation of diverse remnant tribes and also blacks and whites, having geography more than anything else in common. There is no Lumbee language.

It is thus apparent that the mixtures that developed among the southern Indians was not entirely one of intermingled tribes, as the whites mixed with the natives on a much grander scale than some care to admit. A considerable numb er of colonists married Indians and reared families and then, of course, the packhorsemen and factors, living for extended periods among the Indians, formed unions with native women. Many of the tribes had cultures which condoned premarital sex for the young Indian girls. Such a large mestizo population emerged that great numbers of 18th century "Indian" chiefs had such names as McDonald, Perryman, Colbert, Brown, etc. It wasn't long before the natives and the whites and mestizos living among them began to insist that they owned their lands outright and that in every respect they inhabited a sovereign, independent nation. Attempts were made to reestablish centralized states, yet no chief spoke for a unified Cherokee or Creek nation and colonists repeatedly took advantage of this to obtain lands. Many of the tribes were ethnic melting pots. The terms Creek and Muskhogee did not even appear until this century. Creek or Muskhogee, the primary language, in all probability was not a first language or perhaps even understood by a majority of the Creeks. Lower Creeks, a major part of the confederation, themselves composed of different ethnic groups, for the most part spoke Hitchiti, which was unintelligible to those speaking Creek proper.

At any time, in the last century or through this one, whenever whites destroyed Indian granaries and cut down their corn, the effect was devastating. Survivors fled to the woods, where many starved, as they were not as at home in the woods as their hunting and gathering ancestors had been. The Cherokee Chief Vann was driven from his village during the revolution and was forced to scratch for subsistence in the wild. All of these Indians were basically agriculturists. Although small amounts of wheat and rice were grown, maize remained the staple and was prepared as cornbread and hominy, or after being boiled with oak and hickory ashes, was drunk as a kind of soup, which the Creeks called sof kee. Late in the century sweet potatoes were developed. Fields were fenced and cattle, horses, sheep, goats, hogs and chickens were available. The Upper Creek Chief Wolf owned 200 head of black cattle and Indians in other villages had even larger herds. A few years after the Revolution, William Augustus Bowles brought a large supply of munitions and presents for the Creeks from the Bahamas, but they had to come to the coast to get them. They had no difficulty in assembling more than 100 pack horses outfitted with saddles and halters had led them nearly 400 miles overland to pick up the goods. Of course, horse stealing became as prominent as raising, buying and selling. (Ref. 30)

Although scalping was a long time custom among Indians, the usage increased after white contact and was more prevalent around the time of the American Revolution than ever. Mississippians were not true cannibals, but for ritualistic purposes at times did eat human flesh. Like the Indians, British colonists also drank yaupon tea and some was even exported to Britain and France. Europeans took over a great many Indian medicines and cures and a considerable portion of southern white and African folk medicine is of aboriginal origin. The Indians were also the source of many new words such as moccasin, matchcoat, terrapin, opossum, raccoon, chinquapin, chum, hominy, pone and tomahawk. The terms for racial hybrids have been confusing. A 1705 Virginia statute says that a mulatto is the offspring of whites and non-whites, that is - the child of an Indian and a white, or the child, grandchild or great-grandchild of a Negro and a white. A South Carolina missionary in 1715 baptized as a mulatto a girl whose mother he reported as an Indian and father as a white trader. At other times "mulatto" seemed to mean Negro-Indian mixture, but finally the term zambo was used for that hybrid. A significant percentage of the Yamasees themselves were zambos and during this 1 8th century that tribe became increasingly noted for its Negroid features. In spite of the statutes, Africans and Indians intermingled, learned each others' languages, intermarried and at times made common cause against whites. Mestizos properly may mean Indian-White, but has also been used for all kinds of combinations. (Ref. 31)

Regarding slavery, the status of white convicts arriving in Chesapeake Bay whose terms might be up to 14 years or even life did not differ greatly from that of chattel slaves. White, black and Indian slaves were all marketed and employed with little distinction, except for the one difference that most Indian slaves were female. The male Indians would run away and were difficult to manage, so most of the field hands were young, male blacks.

All the slaves were kept together in compounds and it was inevitable that much mixing took place. At times Indians owned African slaves and vice versa. The 1725 census in St. George Parish, South Carolina discloses that the Indian Nero possessed one Negro black slave and the Indian Sam Pickins owned six. In turn Negro Robin Johnson owned 9 slaves, all of whom apparently were Indians. Alexander McGillivray, a mestizo Upper Creek, died in 1793, leaving a considerable estate, including 60 Negro slaves.

In time most southern Negroes adopted, at least in a modified form, the white man's religion and the evangelical sects won more converts than the staid Anglicans. Another change occurred in the Negro culture after they came to America - they dropped the patrilineal society of Africa and became matrilineal. There were probably several factors in this, but one was certainly the matrilineal culture of the southern Indians. A handful of surviving Christian Indians abandoned Florida in 1763 when the British took over, retiring with the Spaniards to Cuba or Mexico. Although a few Catholic converts still remained among the Florida Indians when that area was restored to Spain in 1783, no effort was made to re-establish the missions and no Catholic Indians remain today. Any remnants had been absorbed by the emerging Seminoles.

THE MISSISSIPPI REGION, THE "OLD NORTHWEST, AND THE FRENCH AND INDIAN WAR

Frenchmen were at the upper end of the Mississippi watershed and Detroit was founded by Sieur Antoine de la Mothe Cadillac in 1701 as a fort to control the entrances to Lakes Huron and Erie. There were Indians all over the eastern part of what we now call the Midwest. The Shawnees, who were known in the south as Savannahs, were at various periods widely dispersed, but by 1725 most of the southern bands had rejoined their kinsmen in Pennsylvania. Pressure there from the expanding white frontier and the Iroquois slowly pushed them westward, where they established new villages in the Wyoming and Susquehanna valleys. During the second quarter of this 18th century part of the tribe again moved south, seeking refuge among the Upper Creeks in Alabama, while the majority was settled in mid-century along the Scioto River in central Ohio. They were surrounded by a great many other tribes, including the Liamis, Potawatomis, Delawares, Wyandots and Senecas. (Ref. 32) In the territory now known as the State of Illinois, there were herds of 400 to 500 buffalo seen frequently even as late as 1792, but within 5 years of that time they were all gone, driven across the Mississippi by hunters and domestic farming activities. (Ref. 33) With them went the Indians. In Minnesota, Chippewa and Sioux fought over the wild rice stands in the northern lakes in mid-century. (Ref. 34) The Sioux moved into the South Dakota area as nomadic horsemen with a far different life style than the original valley farming Indians, whom we have described there from the 10th to the 14th centuries. (Ref. 35) They had received their horses indirectly from the Spaniards in the southwest.

In the lower Mississippi region in 1713 St. Denis, from French Biloxi, settled Natchitoches as the oldest city in Louisiana. Near there were a series of small Indian states, including the famous Natchez, perhaps the last inheritors of the Mound-building tradition. There were perhaps 4,000 Natchez people left at the beginning of this century, living in 7 villages clustered near the present city of Natchez. Their social structure included a chief, the Great Sun and his relatives, known as Little Suns. A step below were nobles, then groups of Honored Men, a class achievable by anyone through distinguished action in war or religious devotion and finally the Commoners or Stinkards. Each Sun and Noble, however, had to marry a Stinkard, so there was a constant social turnover. These Indians attacked French Louisiana colonies in 1729, killing 200 and taking women, children and black slaves as prisoners. When they revolted against the French again in 1734, however, within a few years almost none remained alive. The French commanders disposed of a thousand captives in the West Indies. (Ref. 36, 37)

Throughout the century whenever England and France were threatening each other or at war in Europe, the Canadian French made sporadic raids on the frontiers of New England and vice versa. At the end of the 1740s the French took an expedition down the Ohio River and buried lead plates to mark their territorial possessions. Then in 1754 they destroyed a rude English fort at the crucial spot where the Monongahela and Allegheny rivers meet (near present Pittsburg) and built their own Fort Duquesne. At 21 years of age George Washington had his first taste of battle against the French as they moved out of that fort in 1755 at the opening of the true French and Indian War. General Braddock and his English forces were badly defeated by the French and their 1,000 Indian allies.

The victory brought almost all the Indians of the old "northwest" to the French side. This was the American aspect of the Seven Years War but it was a frontier war, strange to the British and they suffered atrociously in the mountains and forests from Indian guerrillas and in the pitched battles they were out-maneuvered. Af ter six years the English did take Quebec and Montreal and the fighting ended. In the Treaty of Paris, three years later, Canada and the whole empire of France in the interior United States were transferred to England. We have noted previously that in the same treaty Florida was taken from Spain, who had come in too late and on the wrong side. The Spanish did acquire La Salle's vast, vague region of Louisiana, however, from the French. (Ref. 38)

The Old Northwest was the territory about the Great Lakes and between the Ohio and Mississippi rivers. By 1750 the Shawnees of that area were divided into five semi-autonomous political units or bands, each occupying a special place within the tribal confederacy. The Thawegila and Chalahgawtha bands supplied the leaders for the entire tribe, but all the bands took an active part in the French and Indian Wars, most of them supporting the French. Some of them fought beside Captain Daniel de Beaujeu as they cut the British column to pieces in the battle near Fort Duquense. During the next 4 years they joined bands of Delawares to raid the English frontier in Pennsylvania and Virginia. After the fall of Quebec, however, most Shawnees withdrew from the warfare, at least for the moment. The Treaty of 1763 did not give absolute peace on the frontier. In that very year Chief Pontiac of the Ottawas along with some Wyandots, Potawatamis and Ojibwas, attacked and then besieged the fort at Detroit from May until November2. Inspired by that, the Shawnees again attacked into eastern Ohio and West Virginia, killing settlers and burning farms. They sent runners as far west as Illinois, urging the tribes of the Wabash Valley to attack British forts and traders. Actually the Shawnee anger was directed at the "Virginians" - those whites trying to occupy Kentucky. (Ref. 40)

Cumberland Gap is a 1,665 feet elevation pass through the Appalachian Mountains lying at the border of Kentucky, Tennessee and Virginia, long known to the Indians, but discovered for the Virginia Land Company by Dr. Thomas Walker in 1750 and named for the Duke of Cumberland. From the pass trails fan out to the south and west so that somewhat later a veteran of the French and Indian Wars, Daniel Boone, made this a highway to the promised land of the west. The so-called "Wilderness Road" was nearly 300 miles long, ending at the Ohio River at Louisville and within 15 years, at the end of the century, 100,000 people had traversed this trail to western Tennessee and Kentucky. Mostly unlettered, these people needed a good gun, a good horse and a good wife, along with good health, good luck, an axe and salt. Most had to carry their salt over the mountains, but at Boone County, Kentucky was a huge brine lake, which incidentally was also a great archaeological find, with a graveyard of mastodon bones. The salt licks were also used by the Indians and this immediately helped to initiate hard feelings early in the settlement of the area.

During the six years of the French-Indian War, the British got an education and became aware of the fact that they needed to overhaul their imperial system and strengthen their central authority. Previously all relation of England to the colonies was on the basis of a commercial empire, on the theory that the colonies existed solely for the benefit of the homeland and that in return the homeland owed them protection. Although the Acts of Trade and Navigation had been passed by Parliament in 1651 they had not been enforced until this century. These Acts called for exclusive navigation, in that all commerce had to involve only British or colonial ships and the "Entrepot Principle" which meant that foreign trade should normally be conducted through the mother country. After the war just discussed, England began to pass constricting laws, new taxes and new army conscriptions from the colonies themselves. This shocked the Americans. First came the Stamp Act, innocuous enough in itself, but inf uriating to the colonists and soon repealed at the insistence of William Pitt. But then came George 111 and Lord North, with still more repressive laws and taxes and a show-down became inevitable. (Ref. 41) (Go to 1140 & 1153)

FACTORS LEADING TO THE AMERICAN REVOLUTION

Enforcement of the Sugar Act3 of 1733 by William Pitt in 1760. Early Americans, like most Europeans of the day, preferred to drink almost anything in preference to water and the New Englanders made everything from poor whiskey to pumpkin beer, maple syrup and persimmons to apple-jack. But soon the main drink in the colonies was rum and the yearly consumption was 3 3/4 gallons per person, including women and children. Some believe that the Sugar Act which imposed a heavy tax on both sugar and molasses (if they came from anyplace but the British owned Caribbean Islands) was more important in the declaration of independence than the tea tax, because the rum trade was based on molasses. The rum was felt to be important, not only for the local consumption but because the New England shippers could exchange rum for slaves in Africa, then trade the slaves in the West Indies for more molasses, which was taken back to the colonies to make more rum. Alcohol was a mainstay of 18th century America. When George Washington was campaigning for the Virginia legislature in 1758, his agents doled out almost 3 3/4 gallons of beer, wine, cider or rum to every voter and Washington was afraid this would not be enough. (Ref. 42)
The Iron Act of 1750 prohibiting colonists from manufacturing iron products, but allowing them to develop their ore deposits for exchange in England for the manufactured pieces. This was the classic mercantilism of the British colonial system, using colonies to produce raw materials, which the mother country could process and sell back. This law was generally ignored by the Americans
The Garrisoning of 10,000 British troops, and this chiefly in cities, rather than on frontiers where they were needed
The Revenue Act of 1764, to raise money to defray the expense of troops "defending the colonies". This act put duties on foreign sugar, European luxuries and limited some exports
The Stamp Act of 1775. This was the first direct, internal tax levied on the colonies. Every type of legal document, even such as college diplomas, was heavily taxed and payable in sterling. Every copy of newspapers, each advertisement in papers, etc. was taxed. Riots against enforcement officials began immediately. A middle-class organization, "Sons of Liberty", sprung up in every seaport and kept the courts from acting, thus nullifying the law. It was repealed by a new administration in England in 1766
The Townshend Act of 1767. Avoiding an internal tax, which the colonists thought unconstitutional, this levied duties on certain English manufactures entering America - paper, glass, paint and the East India Company's tea. The culminating blow was a whole new customs regulation organization to enforce this, using Admiralty Courts to try cases under the Acts of Trade and Navigation, without a jury. The Townshend duties were repealed in 1770, except for tea. It was at that time that Samuel Adams, a middle class Bostonian, began to lead opposition as a Boston "radical"
Land Grievances. There were brawls in the back-country from New Hampshire to South Carolina over land boundaries, land companies and the like, with resulting grievances of frontiersmen against the establishment on the coast. All felt their problems had no attention in Parliament. The Boston Tea Party of 1773. The Sons of Liberty, dressed as Indians, boarded three, unloaded tea ships in Boston Harbor and dumped the cargo into the sea. This was a protest against the tax on tea and it had the calculated effect of irritating the British government into unwise acts of reprisal. This is what Sam Adams wanted
The Coercive Acts of 1774. The Boston Port Act virtually blockaded Boston until it paid for the dumped tea. The Administration of Justice Acts chastised Massachusetts, making councilmen, judges, sheriff s, etc. all appointees of the king. The Quartering Act empowered royal governors to commandeer houses for soldiers. It should be noted that many old Whigs and merchants in England opposed all of these Acts

One of the first skirmishes of the revolution took place in Boston in 1770, when colonists and British troops exchanged shots in the so-called "Boston Massacre". Three civilians were killed and two more died later, including a black man, Crispus Attucks. Who fired the first shot or threw the first stone? Following this episode a revolutionary conspiracy and a colonial underground was formed by James Otis, a Whig lawyer and scholar, and Samuel Adams, the genuine rabble-rouser. They formed committees of correspondence running clear down to South Carolina. In Virginia the headquarters were in a tavern and members included Patrick Henry and Thomas Jefferson. (Ref. 43)

The first Continental Congress met on September 5, 1774 at Philadelphia with 55 members chosen by revolutionary conventions in 12 continental colonies. The Congress issued the Declaration of Rights and an agreement called "The Association" - a non-importation, non-consumption agreement regarding imports from Britain unless the Coercive Acts were repealed. The first true fighting of the war occurred in April, 1775, when General Gage set out to Concord to destroy patriot munitions. The famous stories of Lexington and Concord and later Bunker Hill, etc. are sufficiently well known by all to not require repetition here. Politically, the next step was the Second Continental Congress, which met in May of 1775. At about the same time Parliament passed an act prohibiting all manner of trade and commerce with the colonies. The latter countered with the Declaration of Independence in July, 1776, worded chiefly by Thomas Jefferson.

FEATURES OF THE AMERICAN REVOLUTIONARY WAR

The war was actually not popular in America. The army was chiefly infantry regiments named after various colonies, where they had been recruited. Every line regiment had Negroes. The colonies could have provided a regular army of 100,000 but they could never have fed and clothed so many. The greatest number of men at any one time was 20,000, in 1778. Washington's army went hungry because of reluctance of farmers and merchants to exchange food and clothing for a Continental chit. The chief source of food was Connecticut, through actions of Governor Jonathan Trumbull.

Financing of the Revolution

Foreign loan. 6.4 million dollars were borrowed from France, in addition to a direct grant of 2.6 million. John Adams got an additional loan from the Dutch
Domestic loans. 20 million dollars were raised by both interest bearing bonds and certificates of indebtedness for goods received
Requisitions in money or in kind, apportioned among states in proportion to the estimated population

All loans, domestic and foreign and the states debts were later repaid at par. The local currency depreciated, but a later French loan negotiated by Robert Morris saved the day.

Alistair Cooke (Ref. 44) asks the question: "How did a rag-tag army defeat one of the crack armies of Europe?" And then he gives the following answers:

Weaponry. The British used smooth-bore muskets that allowed a lateral error of 3 feet at 100 yards and used for mass "spraying" of close order troops. In contrast the American frontiersmen used the Pennsylvania flintlock, with double the barrel length and grooves (rifling) to make the bullet spin and stay on line They could put a ball in a man's head-at 150 to 200 yards
Guerilla hit and run warfare
The choice of Washington as commander in chief, as this brought Virginia into the war
The idealism of Ben Franklin and Thomas Jefferson spread among the people

One might add a 5th factor in the American victory - the difficulty of the British in supplying an army of 90,000 soldiers an ocean away from their homeland, as after 1775 the Americans had pretty well prevented British troops from access to local supplies.

Under the circumstances the British navy did a good job, but in January 1779 the Red Coat army in New York had only 4 days rations left when a relieving fleet arrived. (Ref. 45)

The final battle of the war occurred in 1781 at Yorktown. General Cornwallis was already under siege with Washington's troops on land; then the French navy bottled him in4. In 1782 there was still occasional fighting in the west, where the British had Indian associates and this will be discussed a little more in a later paragraph. The Peace of Paris of February 3, 1783 involved Great Britain, France, Spain, the Netherlands and the new United States, with the latter winning territorial rights west to the Mississippi, north to Canada and south to the Floridas. The British did retain Newfoundland fishing rights and free navigation on the Mississippi. Spain wanted Gibraltar, but settled for the return of Florida.

After the war, there was still not a nation but a group of independent countries. Within four years the Union was close to bankruptcy and strong leaders were not in sight. About 1/3 of the people in this new "nation" were Tories, who had remained loyal to England during the war. Pennsylvania and South Carolina were generous and compassionate with these people, but other colonies reacted much differently and great numbers of Tories were exiled to Canada, the West Indies or back to England. Immediately after the termination of fighting various states started to draw up declarations of rights and constitutions. The Virginia Declaration of Rights was one of the great liberty documents of all time.

Articles of Confederation had been drawn up as early as November, 1777 by a Congress designed to preserve the independence and sovereignty of the states. There was a considerable revival of commerce between 1782 and 1789 and some literary activity, as evidenced by the publication of Webster's Dictionary by Noah Webster. But all was not completely peaceful - in Massachusetts a revolt of poor farmers against the courts, who were prosecuting debtors was called "Shay's Rebellion". The situation was alleviated when some new legislators were elected.

Besides having European nations treating it with contempt, the new nation was scarcely able to contain the Indian tribes and to pay the interest on the Revolutionary War debt. It was on the brink of collapse when Congress appealed to the people for a new constitution.  (Ref. 47) Finally delegates did meet in the so-called Constitutional Convention in 1787. The problem was not to give the states anything, but to take some existing powers from them. (Ref. 48) Sam Adams, Thomas Paine, Patrick Henry5 and others of the "Pampleteers" group were not present. As Cooke (Ref. 49) puts it - such men "love the bonfire, but find the rebuilding something of a bore". Alexander Hamilton wanted a lifetime chief executive, a lifetime senate of property owners and in effect wanted to extinguish the states altogether. His opposite was George Mason, a 62 year old, uncompromising democrat, who was about 1/2 century before his time. He called himself a radical republican and argued long and hard for individual liberties such as he had engineered previously in the Virginia Bill of Rights. Between these two extremes was James Madison, 36 years old, also from Virginia, but with a middle ground approach that led to the final constitution. The solution was compromise and at the end even Hamilton helped to publicize and get the document approved.

Some additional information concerning the Constitutional Convention can be found in "Documents illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States", published for the Library of Congress by the Government printing office in 1927. (Ref. 51) The following contains excerpts from that source:

From the notes of William Patterson of New Jersey, while preparing a speech for July 9, 1787 we find this information about the populations of the various states:

New Hampshire-- 1774 --100,000
Massachusetts -- 1774 -- 400,000
Rhode Island -- 1783 -- 48,538 Whites and 3,331 Blacks
Connecticut -- 1774 -- 192,000 Whites and nearly 6,000 Blacks
New York -- 1786 -- 219,996 Whites and 18,889 Blacks
New Jersey -- 1783 -- 129,000 Whites and about 10,000 Blacks
Maryland -- 1774 -- 350,000 (Estimated) with 3/7 Blacks - 150,000
Virginia -- 1774 -- 650,000. (This apparent4 as a total, because he writes then - Blacks as 10 to 11 - 300,0006

The Congress early wrote an Ordinance for the Government of the territory of the United States Northwest of the river Ohio and it contained, among others, the following interesting features:

"Article III --The utmost good faith shall always be observed toward the Indians; their lands and property shall never be taken from them without their consent; and in their property, rights and liberty they never shall be invaded or disturbed unless in just and lawful wars authorized by Congress
Article VI - There was to be neither slavery nor involuntary servitude in the territory, but escaped slaves were to be returned to owners in the original states

In the convention there was much discussion about slavery. Mr. John Rutledge of South Carolina said that religion and humanity had nothing to do with this question and that it was a matter of "interest". "If the northern states consult their interest, they will not oppose the increase of slaves which will increase the commodities of which they will become the carriers." Mr. Charles C. Pinkney of South Carolina added that South

Carolina could never receive the plan (Constitution) if it prohibits the slave trade. He further stated that the entire world had had slaves - Greece, Rome and other ancient states - and that slavery had been sanctioned by France, Holland and other modern states. "In all ages one-half of mankind have been slaves." (Ref. 53)

Thomas Jefferson was not present at the Constitutional Convention as he was serving as Minister to France at the time, but it will be worthwhile to consider at this time a few more details about that most remarkable man. He was a Greek and Latin scholar, geologist, musician, astronomer, meteorologist, archaeologist, anthropologist and gardener extraordinaire, as well as statesman and lawyer. (Ref. 54) His father was a Welshman with distaste for English rule, although already a third generation colonial. As a young man Thomas was accused, rightly or wrongly, of many indiscretions with married women and finally married a rich widow with a child, only to soon take a mulatto slave as his concubine7. His house slaves alone numbered 25. He loved fine wine, blooded horses and exotic orchids, all of which he kept at Monticello. He preserved a legacy of over 25,000 letters from friends and acquaintances and copies of his own letters that numbered some 18,000, all indexed. In spite of meticulous record keeping, however, when he died he owed over $100,000. He befriended the Shawnee Indians and talked against slavery, having introduced a bill in the Virginia legislature at age 24 to permit emancipation by free choice of the slave holder, but the bill was defeated. He wrote about and compared Whites, Blacks and Indians, giving certain features to all, some good, some bad, but was remarkable liberal for an 18th century Virginian, where there were 10 blacks for every 11 whites. During the war, Virginia never officially permitted slave enlistment. Nevertheless, free blacks numbering about 500 did fight as soldiers and sailors by November 1777. Thousands of other Virginia slaves, however, fled to the British side, including 22 of Jefferson's own. Other colonies lost slaves also; 4,000 from Savannah, 6,000 from Charleston, 4,000 from New York and thousands more were carried off by the French.

Jefferson was enthusiastic about the new inoculation against small-pox that became available near the end of the century, although the more religious people were upset about it, still claiming that illness was a manifestation of God's intention, if not a punishment for sin. Jefferson, himself, was a deist. John Adams and Jefferson were once great friends, but had a falling-out chiefly over the French revolution, which Jefferson supported. In addition there was a great rivalry with and finally hatred of the younger Alexander Hamilton, a bastard son of a wayward descendant of a French Huguenot in the West Indies and a Scotsman, 4th son of a Scottish laird. Although it was common knowledge that Hamilton was a womanizer, he married into a rich, Dutch patroon family along the Mohawk. He seemed to cherish a monarchy and wanted to make the childless George Washington a king, with himself as the chosen heir. (Ref. 56)

As is well known, after the Constitution was adopted the new government commenced to function in 1789 with George Washington as the first president and John Adams as vice president. John Jay was chief justice, General Knox secretary of war, Edmund Randolph attorney general and upon his return from France, Thomas Jefferson became secretary of state. Any enthusiasm for emancipation of slaves in Virginia was rapidly cooled by the news of the Santo Domingo rising of the blacks under the Jamaican voodoo priest, Boukman and Toussaint L'Ouverte. (See the next section, please). As secretary of state, Jefferson was a states' rights and southern policies advocate, who was favorable to France.

Map taken from Reference 97

His associates formed the Republican Party of that time (later to become the present day Democratic Party). The real power of the first administration, however, was the secretary of the treasury, Alexander Hamilton, who favored Britain over France and whose policies led to the establishment of the Federalist Party. The United States navy had to be rebuilt in 1794, stimulated by piracy of the Barbary corsairs and some troubles with the British navy.

As John Adams became president with Jefferson as vice-president in 1797 naval war with France loomed on the horizon. The aggressive and subversive French Directory let French privateers loose against the American merchant fleet and by June more than 300 American vessels had been captured. The Federalists felt that France was a great menace and that England was the only barrier against France's ruling of the world. An American negotiation mission arrived in Paris just after Bonaparte had beaten Austria and the Directory was at the height of power and arrogance. Talleyrand, the minister of foreign affairs, was insufferable and tried to bribe the commission. When reports of this reached home, President Adams and Congress created a navy department, navy yards were purchased and an ambitious program of naval construction was undertaken. By the close of 1798 some 14 American man-of-war ships were at sea and transatlantic shipping was being protected every place, with the help of an arrangement with the British navy. The first test battle was off Nevis Island in the Caribbean, where the U.S.S. Constellation fought for an hour and won over the crack French frigate L'Insurgente. This helped the Federalists to win a strong majority in the 1798-1799 Congressional elections. But Talleyrand changed his approach, saved face and full war did not occur. Nevertheless, there was a rebirth of the U.S. Navy and at the end of hostilities, there were 54 American warships.

As the century ended in 1800, Jefferson ran for president. It is interesting that clergymen were against him. He felt that both the Episcopalian and the Congregational churches hoped to be named as the established Church of the United States, but he had "sworn upon the Altar of God, eternal hostility against every form of tyranny over the mind of man". (Ref. 57)

We must return to events west of the Appalachians during and after the American Revolution. Shawnee hatred of the Virginians virtually assured that the former remaining in Ohio would oppose the colonists during the war. In January 1778 a war party from the Chalahgawtha (Chillicothe) village captured Daniel Boone and some companions at the Blue Licks on the Licking River. Boone later escaped, but all through the summer of 1778 Shawnee warriors fell upon Kentucky settlements, burning, capturing horses and taking scalps. Such raids and counter attacks by such as Colonel John Bowman's 200 mounted volunteers continued through 1779. Although few Indians were killed, the Americans captured many horses and much Indian property. Somewhat demoralized, many Shawnee tribesmen retreated down the Ohio and eventually crossed the Mississippi, establishing new villages in what is now Missouri.

White settlers crowded into Indian lands in southern Ohio and the remaining Shawnees turned to British Indian agents, who assured them that they still owned their lands. Hoping to forestall more bloodshed, the United States negotiated a series of treaties with the Iroquois, Wyandots and other tribes during 1784 and 1785 and assembled a delegation of Shawnees at Fort Finney in January of 1786. American agents told these Shawnees that they must give up their land claims east of the Miami and acknowledge the sovereignty of the United States over all their villages. The Indians were astonished, but under threats of destruction of their women and children, Kekewepellethe and other Shawnee leaders, signed the documents, but they soon lashed out again at white settlers in southern Ohio. Two federal expeditions were sent out against the Shawnees - the first under General Josiah Harmar and the next under Governor St. Clair, who had almost 2,000 regulars, militia and volunteers. The Shawnees with Miamis, Potawatomis, Delawares and other allies, killed over 630 Americans and the latter had to admit disaster. During the spring of 1794 the British built a new Fort Miamis at modern Toledo8 Thinking that was a sure indication of British military assistance, the Shawnees dared the American to come again and more warfare seemed inevitable. The new leader of the American forces, "Mad Anthony" Wayne, however, had spent two years training an army and on August 20, 1794 this army swept through Shawnee barricades at Fallen Timbers, Ohio and crushed the Indians. They had no choice but to make peace and on August 3, 1795 signed the Treaty of Greenville, in which they exchanged most of their former homeland for a few trade goods and an annuity of $1,000. The only land they retained was the northwest quadrant of Ohio. (Go to 1140 & 1153)

THE SOUTHWEST AND FAR WEST

West of the Mississippi whites and Indians alike were little affected by the American Revolution or the events leading up to it. The spread of horsemanship from the Spanish contact had worked a rapid transformation in the Great Plains, but this was only the beginning of a radical cultural adjustment to a nomadic life. (Ref. 58) Between 1720 and 1722 Mexican Spaniards occupied Texas, fearing loss of the territory to France. A mission was founded at San Antonio in 1718. Around 1700, using the horse, Comanches came out of Wyoming and fought against the Apaches first and then kept the Texas settlements in a permanent state of siege, after a big battle on the Red River in 1759. Spanish Governor Domingo Cabello listed the population of Texas in 1783 as 2,819 Spanish people. In the adjacent area of Louisiana, by 1797, American squatters made up nearly 1/2 of the population of 50,000. (Ref. 59) New Orleans had been founded about 1720 by Le Moyne de Bienville to control river traffic. After 1763, however, Spain controlled this area until the French Consulate forced its return to France in 1800.

Besides Texas and New Mexico, most of Colorado and Arizona, with slices of Utah, Wyoming, Kansas and Oklahoma, all belonged to Spain in an area called the Kingdom of New Mexico, by Madrid. White settlements were made chiefly along the Rio Grande River. Albuquerque was established in 1706, with Taos soon after and there were Spaniards about Pueblo, Colorado by 1750. There was extensive trade between that area and Chihuahua in old Mexico, some 600 miles south. In some years as many as 500,000 sheep were sent there. It is unfortunate that even the Franciscan priests treated the Indians as servants and serfs. In the 1770s almost 1700 Spaniards were killed by Apaches and Comanches, now teaming up against the white invaders. But the area continued to be populated, particularly after Governor de Anza persuaded the Comanches and Apaches to fight each other again instead of the Spaniards. The Utes joined forces with the Apaches. By 1799 the Spanish population in that area was 18,826. (Ref. 60, 61) The Pima Indians9 of southern Arizona fought the Apaches, but continued friendly to the Spaniards. In 1775 they numbered about 2,500, living as sedentary farmers, raising corn, squash, beans, cotton and Spanish wheat by means of irrigation. (Ref. 62)

In the far west, Spain was also active both by land and by sea. The land between Mexico and California was mapped by Father Kino, who went overland to San Diego in 1769 and established missions in the Baja peninsula. The last great military expedition of the Spaniards came about in the 1750s when there were rumors that the Russians were going to take upper California (the state of California, today) and the Spanish considered this a part of New Spain. Actually the Russians were only chasing the sea otter, but King Carlos, of Spain, ordered out expeditions by land and sea to build a chain of forts and hold the California coast. With the military went priests and in particular one Father Serra, who built 21 missions, the main architectural legacy of Spain in California. He personally walked between 4,000 and 5,000 miles up and down the coast line, over mountains and deserts. The Spanish did bring oats, wheat, barley and oranges to America and refined the culture of maize. (Ref. 64) The earliest California missions were in San Diego, San Gabriel and San Luis Obispo, all established by 1773. In 1775 Don Bruno Heceta, sailing the "Santiago" found the Columbia River mouth, naming the river "Rio St. Roc". Spain had a settlement at Cape Medocino, about 130 miles north of San Francisco. (Ref. 65 The Presidio of San Francisco was founded by Bautista de Anza, subsequently the governor of New Mexico, in 1776. All overland routes from Mexico to California were interrupted in 1781, however, by bloody Yuma Indian rebellions. At the very end of the century (1792-1794) George Vancouver made three sea visits to California for Great Britain. (Ref. 66)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THE CARIBBEAN

In Mexico Spanish rule continued in a stagnant civilization. The object of Spanish colonization was to enrich the Spanish king, without thought to the effect on the population and progress of the colonized country. There were 5,000 to 6,000 priests, with 6,000 to 8,000 other members of the religious orders and they were owners of tremendous properties. By the end of the century there were perhaps a 1,000,000 creoles and the mestizos were becoming more numerous. In the army, the privates were mestizos and the officers, creoles. The 3,000,000 or 4,000,000 Indians lived very little differently from their ancestors. As the century progressed and after wide-spread administrative reforms by the new Bourbon monarch, Philipe, King of Spain and grandson of Louis XIV, - especially liberalization of trade regulation - there was a general economic upsurge and the growth of a large middle class population gave new intellectual and cultural life to the colony. A very rapid population increase was apparent by the close of the century, apparently as a result of the development of immunity to the various European diseases. Spanish America became much more Europeanized, although racial plurality, prevalence of large estates and the widespread compulsory labor (both debt peonage and outright slavery) and the extraordinary economic and cultural importance of the Church, distinguished it from the most of Europe. Mexico City had 112,926 people in 1793 and was larger than any city in France or England except Paris and London. There were more people in Mexico than in all of the thirteen colonies of North America. (Ref . 139). Silver mines in the northern part of the country allowed the Mexicans to purchase large quantities of European goods. When the maize supply, which originated in the south, was interrupted in 1785-86, however, famine developed in the northern mine area and there was an endless flight of workers to the south and Mexico City. (Ref. 67)

Guatemala City was founded in 1776, after the old capital was destroyed by an earth- quake. (Ref. 68) After about 1720 Britain's largest supply of American Indian slaves for the West Indies came, not from the U.S.A. south, but from Central America, primarily the Gulf of Honduras, the Mosquito Coast and Panama. Mosquito Indians and some Darien warriors in Panama raided Spanish settlements and Catholic Indian villages in the interior, returning to the coast with slaves. Two thousand such individuals were sold by the Mosquitos in the decade following 1712. (Ref. 69)

In the Caribbean, the first coffee plants were started on Martinique by a French naval officer in 1723 and the Caribbean would eventually supply 90% of the world's coffee. (Ref. 70) Jamaica continued its sugar production and Saint Domingue produced as much or more. Jamaica, as a very large island, had gigantic estates developed there, especially after 1740, when the island's sugar economy was expanded. A typical estate would have a master's house and 9 or 10 black slaves for every white man. The colonial pound had a lower value than the pound sterling (1 pound sterling = 1.4 Jamaican pounds). Piracy and pillage by French privateers was common. (Ref. 71) By 1763 the British had taken previously Spanish Havana and all the French islands except St. Dominque, but all was restored by the Treaty of Paris of that year. (Ref 8) Britain did gain permanent control of Belize and protectorates over Honduras and Nicaragua. (Ref. 72)

Late in the century revolt of slaves in Sainte Domingue (Haiti), led by black leaders Boukman and Louverte, ruined the French colony there and changed this island from the richest colony in the world, with sugar and coffee exports, to the poorest republic. (Ref. 73) This revolt must be considered a by-product of the French Revolution. (Ref. 74) Slave trouble occurred on Jamaica, also and resulted in 1739 in the governor's signing of a fifteen point treaty with the maroon leader, Captain Cudjoe. The maroons rebelled against both Cudjoe and the settlement, however, and intermittent con licts continued throughout the century. Actually Cudjoe's maroons numbered only some thousands, while the total slave population of Jamaica was about 100,000, with fewer than 10,000 whites. (Ref. 75) Even with all their troubles, the planters made at most 8 to 10% profit, the real wealth being accumulated by capitalists in England. (Ref. 76)

When the British took over the tiny island of St. Eustatius in the Leeward group, in 1781, Admiral Rodney found that Jews comprised at least 1/5 of the merchant population. A fine brick synagogue and a large mikve (bath house) were scheduled to be fully excavated in the summer of 1982. (Ref. 77, 78)2

2 Vincent and went to the Bay Islands off the coast of Honduras and then to the mainland coast, where many still live in isolated villages. (Ref. 79)

SOUTH AMERICA (See map on page 945)

It has been said that in this century South America was powered by 2,000,000 mules, although in the Argentine, ox carts were used. In 1776 Peru had 500,000 mules for trade or drawing coaches on the coast and in the Andes. 50,000 a year were imported from the Argentine pampas. (Ref. 80) The human population was about 15,000,000 of which about 20% were Caucasian. (Ref. 81)

WESTERN AND NORTHERN COASTS OF SOUTH AMERICA

European expeditionary forces continued intermittent fighting over American ports. With 100 ships and 27,000 men, Britain's Admiral Vernon attacked the Spanish fortress at Cartagena, Columbia in 1741, but the Spanish, with the help of malaria and yellow fever, held them off and the British retired to Jamaica, having lost 4,500 soldiers, at least as far as effectiveness was concerned. Cayenne, in French Guinea, was actually a French penal colony. Cocoa plantations in Venezuela were created by the Caracas Company in 1728. Southern Venezuela, however, was a_ wild country with huge flocks of sheep shepherded by Indians and Spanish-Indian half-breeds. (Ref. 82)

In the Spanish part of South America a relatively small number of Europeans ruled over a large native population, but as the races and skills were gradually mingled some industry developed, so that by 1700 Spanish America was nearly self sufficient. There were only rare, minor uprisings, the most important of these occurring in Peru in 1780 and 81, led by a man claiming royal Inca descent. Earthquakes were frequent, with Lima virtually destroyed in 1746.

With the new liberalization of trade and transport decreed from the new Bourbon monarchy of Spain, the colonies were allowed for the first time to trade freely among themselves. Gradually wider circles of Spanish-Americans began to interest themselves in the new knowledge from Europe. (Ref. 83) In the third quarter of the century, under the enlightened Spanish reign of Carlos III, the area had even begun to make preparations for self-government, but then the French Revolution spoiled everything. (Ref. 84)

The great silver mines of Bolivia continued to operate during the century. The greatest mining camp was Potosi, 4,000 meters high in the Andes, where more than 100,000 people lived under most expensive conditions. A hen could cost 8 reals, an egg 2. Only the merchants made money. (Ref. 85) The Atacamanian Indians allowed a permanent contact between the populations of southern Peru and the tribes of central Chile - the Diaguites and Araucanians. They kept their own language until late in this century and had a population of about 10,000. One of the foods used by South American Indians on long journeys was prepared by taking 1/4 inch strips of lean game meat (later beef), dipping them in strong brine or rubbing them with salt, then rolling them in animal hide for 10 to 12 hours to allow re-absorption of the salt and release of some juices, then hanging the strips in the sun to dry and finally tying them in bundles. The Indians called this charqui which was later corrupted in the United States West to "jerked" beef or "jerky". (Ref. 86)

EASTERN COAST AND CENTRAL SOUTH AMERICA

The alliance of Portugal with England during the war of the Spanish succession led to French attacks on Brazilian ports, Rio de Janeiro being sacked in 1711. There was continued trouble between the Portuguese and the converted Indians (the Paulistas), with some open warfare finally resulting in the pushing of the line of Portuguese territory farther westward into the jungles. In addition there was war (1710-11) between the native Brazilians of Olinda, capital of Pernambuco, and the Portuguese town of Recife. Again the latter won and made Recife the capital of Brazil until 1763 when it was moved to Rio de Janeiro because of the development of nearby gold mines. Actually the peak gold production was between the years of 1750 and 1755, when over 15 tons a year were mined. (Ref. 87, 88) Throughout all this Brazil continued to provide Europe with sugar, coffee, cacao, rice and cotton, in addition to the gold, but since the Indian labor population had been almost obliterated by conquest and disease, they had been replaced by Africans.

By 1775 some 5 1/2 million slaves had been brought to America, although only 1 1/2 million had survived. (Ref. 89) By mid-century the minister the Marquis de Pombal introduced colonial reforms, including the removal of certain restrictions and taxes and the organization of trading companies. Actually some native Brazilians were appointed to important governmental posts, racial equality was advocated and defenses were improved, but the masters of Brazil were still the merchants of Portugal. The discovery of the rich gold and diamond finds early in the century had helped the economy considerably.

The Jesuits were expelled from their "reductions" in land-locked Paraguay among the Guarani Indians. The "reductions" were compounds with two priests, an Indian supervisor and many Indian farmers and laborers, ostensibly designed to acquaint the natives with Spanish religion and ways, but which really became commercial enterprises competing with other private businesses. The Guarani were language-related to the Tubi groups of Brazil. (Ref. 90, 91) There were some serious clashes between Spain and Portugal over the area of Uruguay (then called "Banda Oriental") and although Spain created the Viceroyalty of La Plata in 1776 as a defensive as well as administrative measure, the final disposition of the territory was not finally decided until the next century. (Ref. 92)

The fierce Araucanian Indians, some of whom had escaped the Spaniards in the 16th century by taking refuge with their stolen Spanish horses on the eastern slopes of the Andes, subsequently invaded the pampas and occasionally still threatened Buenos Aires in this century. (Ref. 93) The sale of thousands of mules a year to Peru and Brazil gave primitive Argentina a chance to share in the silver and gold of those countries. Some 2,000,000 mules may have been used in Central and South America for saddle or carrying (rarely for hauling). European oxen were used for - drawing heavy carts in the pampas and the gauchos were already riding great horses at the end of the century. Even so, whether traveling by horseback, mule or ox-cart, travelers across the Argentine deserts had to be sure of elaborate arrangements to find food and water. (Ref. 94)

1 [234] WHEELER, KEITH, The Alaskans. (Time-Life Books, Alexandria, Va. 1977).

2 [199] STARR, S. FREDERICK, "Why did Russia let Seward's folly go on the cheap?" Smithsonian, Dec. 1979, page 129.

3 [234] WHEELER, KEITH, The Alaskans. (Time-Life Books, Alexandria, Va. 1977).

4 [310] MORGAN LAEL, "Alaska's Far Out Islands: The Aleutians", National Geographic 164, No. 3: 336-363, Sept. 1983.

5 [302] WARNER, OLIVER (with DR. J.C. BEAGLEHOLE), Captain Cook and the South Pacific. (Cassell, London. American Heritage Publ. Co., Inc., New York, 1963).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

8 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

9 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

10 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

11 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

12 [212] TANNER, OGDEN, The Canadians. (Time-Life Books Inc., Alexandria, Va. 1977).

13 [212] TANNER, OGDEN, The Canadians. (Time-Life Books Inc., Alexandria, Va. 1977).

14 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

15 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

16 [212] TANNER, OGDEN, The Canadians. (Time-Life Books Inc., Alexandria, Va. 1977).

17 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

18 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

19 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

20 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

21 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

22 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

23 [218] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEX15, Ibid. Volume II. (Original publication in 1840).

24 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

25 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

26 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

27 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

28 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

29 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

30 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

31 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

32 [293] EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

33 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

34 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

35 [241] ZIMMERMAN, LARRY J. AND WHITTEN, RICHARD G., "Prehistoric bones tell a grim tale of Indian vs. Indian", Smithsonian, Sept. 1980, page 100.

36 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

37 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

38 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

39 [293] EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

40 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

41 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

42 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

43 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

44 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

45 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

46 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

47 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

48 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

49 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

50 [20] BRODIE, FAWN M., Thomas Jefferson, An Intimate History", (W.W. Norton & Co., Inc., New York).

51 [123]  LIBRARY OF CONGRESS, "Documents Illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States, Government Printing Office, Washington D.C. 1927.

52 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

53 [123]  LIBRARY OF CONGRESS, "Documents Illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States, Government Printing Office, Washington D.C. 1927.

54 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

55 [20] BRODIE, FAWN M., Thomas Jefferson, An Intimate History", (W.W. Norton & Co., Inc., New York).

56 [20] BRODIE, FAWN M., Thomas Jefferson, An Intimate History", (W.W. Norton & Co., Inc., New York).

57 [20] BRODIE, FAWN M., Thomas Jefferson, An Intimate History", (W.W. Norton & Co., Inc., New York).

58 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

59 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

60 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

61 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

62 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

63 [289] TUCKER, WILLIAM, "Thrifty Diabetes", Science 83, Apr. 1983, pp. 92-93.

64 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

65 [63] FALCONER, THOMAS, Discovery of the Mississippi. (London, 1844 - as reprinted by Shoal Creek Publishers, Inc. Austin, Texas, 1975).

66 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

67 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

68 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

69 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

70 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

71 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

72 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

73 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

74 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

75 [249] FINLEY, M.I., Ancient Slavery & Modern Ideology. (The Viking Press, New York, 1980).

76 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

77 [245] DETHLEFSEN, EDWIN, ET AL, "Archeology on St. Eustatius: The Pompeii of the New World", Archeology 35: 8-15, Mar./Apr. 1982.

78 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

79 [308] EDWARDS, MIKE, "Honduras: The Eye of the Storm", National Geographic 164: No.5: 608-637, Nov. 1983.

80 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

81 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

82 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

83 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

84 [68] GARRATY, JOHN A. and GAY, PETER, (Editors), The Columbia History of the World. (Harper & Row, New York, 1972).

85 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

86 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

87 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

88 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

89 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

90 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

91 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

92 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

93 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

94 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

1.  This college was originally at Newark under Presbyterian auspices and was moved to Princeton in 1756. (Ref. 25)

2.  This was to be known as Pontiac's Rebellion or Pontiac's Conspiracy. (Ref. 41)

3.  Sometimes called the "Molasses Act"

4.  An interesting sidelight is that the French fleet under the Comte de Grasse had re-fueled in the Caribbean and made for the Chesapeake, while his English counterpart, Admiral Rodney, was attacking the Dutch Island of St. Eustatius, just north of St. Kitts, because the islanders had been trading illicitly with the rebel colonies. (Ref. 46)

5.  When Patrick Henry gave his famous "give me liberty or give me death" speech, his wife was a hopeless psychotic in a strait-jacket, confined to a basement room. Tom Paine had had a break-up with his second wife, whom he simply left in England. (Ref. 50)

6.  Trager (Ref. 52) writes that as of 1775 there were 450,000 slaves below the Mason Dixon line

7.  When the French savant and refugee, the Comte de Volney, visited Monticello in 1796, he noted in his journal great astonishment at seeing slave children as white as himself! (Ref. 55)

8.  This was on land ceded by Great Britain by the treaty of 1783 (see map on page 10Z9) but it is obvious that the British in Canada and the Old Northwest did not pay a great deal of attention to that

9.  Today about 1/2 of the adults on Pima farm reservations have diabetes mellitus. William Tucker  (Ref.63) believes that they are representative of certain groups of Polynesians and American Indians who, in their past history, have gone through periods of infrequent meals. As an adaptation to those large, infrequent meals, their bodies developed low insulin production, allowing the blood sugar to rise and stay high longer and with slower use, carry the individual over the starvation periods. This genetic diabetic trait results in obesity and diabetes in a setting of adequate food and regular meals

America: A.D. 1801 to 1900

AMERICA

NORTH AMERICA

THE FAR NORTH AND CANADA

ALASKA

The century opened with bloody warfare for the small Russian settlement at Fort St. Michael on Baranov Island, when the Tlingits Indians massacred the men and carried off the women to their village at the site of present day Sitka, in 1802. Two years later Baranov's men, regrouped in kayaks and supported by a Russian warship, bombarded Sitka and finally forced an Indian withdrawal. The Russians then built a new fort and in the years that followed the missionary Father Ivan Veniaminov built a cathedral, started a seminary, saved the Tlingits from a small-pox epidemic by vaccination, taught the Aleuts carpentry, blacksmithing and brickmaking, created an Aleut alphabet and with that translated the Gospels. Baranov was followed by 13 Russian governors, chiefly naval officers, but there was one prince and one baron. Commerce with San Francisco was brisk, particularly during the latter's gold-rush days. Among other things, 20,000 tons of Alaskan ice, packed in sawdust, was sold in San Francisco at $35 a ton. The zenith of Russian culture at Sitka was about 1820

The Kiksadi clan of Tlingits dominated the hinterland and thus the principal source of Russian food supply. Frequently these clans mounted crippling raids against the Russian mainland settlements, some as late as 1866. Supply ships from Russia had to go around the Cape of Good Hope and in some years none arrived. Many Russians died of scurvy before they learned that potatoes and other vegetables could be grown in the far north. At one point, the Russians attempted to solve their grain problem by establishing Fort Ross, only 90 miles north of the Spanish mission of San Francisco, but the area was not very fertile and they sold out to John Sutter in 1841.

We mentioned in the last chapter that the Russians virtually enslaved the Aleuts, forcing 1/2 of all males between the ages of 18 and 50 to work for very meager compensation. By this policy, along with disease and the use of the white man's firearms, the Aleut population had been reduced to about 1/10 of the original and the Eskimos on the mainland had been cut to about 1/2 by 1857. A massive seal fur industry resulted when a machine was developed which removed the outer layer of bristly guard hairs from the animal. A Moscow journal of 1835 boasted that between 1786 and 1832 there had been 3,178,561 Pribilof fur seals killed. Soon the yield decreased and both European and American fur markets declined so that the fur based economy ceased to be very profitable. The worst losses were in the 1820s.

When Russia was defeated in the Crimean War in 1856 she was desperate for money, and that, along with an increasing interest in China rather than America, was the big f actor leading to the sale of Alaska's 375,000,000 acres to the United States in 1867 for $7,200,000.

That purchase, arranged by Secretary of State William Henry Seward of the Andrew Johnson administration, resulted in the name "Seward's Folly" for that region for many years.

All was forgiven at the end of the century when the great Klondike and Nome gold rushes developed. (Ref. 1, 2)

Alaska's northwest contained some 24 Eskimo groups, all speaking related tongues.

Unlike their European and Siberian counterparts these Americans relied more on sea mammals than on the new world reindeer (caribou). Seals, walruses and sea-lions supplied food, clothes, boats, tents and oil for lamps. Tendons were used for sewing and bones took the place of wood. The Eskimos introduced umiaks (large, open, skin boats) and the toggle-headed harpoon to the world. (Ref. 3)

GREENLAND

Central Greenland remained the most inhospitable of all Arctic areas, but Eskimos did live all along the southern coasts, both east and west, with a hybrid Eskimo-Danish culture. Due to an oversight at the Congress of Vienna in 1815, when Norway was taken away from Denmark, this colony was overlooked and remained in Danish hands. Administration was poor, however, and among other troubles the natives had a high incidence of tuberculosis. In far northwest Greenland a group known simply as Polar Eskimos lived in complete isolation, using sea-mammal bones for sled runners and using nets to catch cliff-dwelling birds. There were about 150 people there when Europeans discovered them in 1818. (Ref. 4, 5)

CANADA

Arctic Canada had a mixture of Inuit (Eskimo) people living chiefly north of the tree-line and Arctic Indians living just south of that region. Among the latter were the Kutchins, who walked hundreds of miles each summer after the caribou herds. In winter they used snow-shoes and lived in domed caribou-skin tents or log and moss houses. They traded with the Eskimos. Koyukon, Tchin and Chipwyan tribes were all part of those Kutchin people. Inuit Eskimos lived on the Arctic Ocean coast line from Beaufort Sea to the Baff in Bay and Davis Strait as well as on the northern shores of Hudson Bay. (Ref. 6)

In 1825 British North America consisted of 2 major areas: First, there were the six settled provinces of Newfoundland, Prince Edward Island, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and Lower and Upper Canadas; and second there was all the remaining territory from Hudson's Bay on west to the Pacific. The first 4 named were known as the Maritime provinces; Lower Canada was later to become Quebec and had 625,000 chief Iy French people in 1841, while upper Canada later became Ontario and had 455,700 population in the same year. The western territory was owned by the Hudson's Bay Company and the Northwest Company with the British government keeping some authority. Each province was ruled by a local Tory oligarchy which supported the governor.

Occasionally an attempt to gain independence sprouted, such as the revolt promoted by Louis Joseph Papineau1, an assemblyman, John Neilson, a Scots and Edmund O'Callaghan, an Irishman - in Quebec. Papineau's fatal error was in alienating priests by anticlerical outbursts and when the bishop came out against him, few French Canadians would follow him. In Ontario an uprising of 1836 came nearer success. This was led by William Lyon MacKenzie of Toronto and Marchall Bidwell, a fugitive from the United States. The rebels marched on Toronto, but were dispersed by one volley from some militia. In May of 1838 Queen Victoria sent the young Earl of Durham to be commissioner of British North America and he adopted a course of clemency to the rebels. Through his recommendations Canada was given responsible government with a ministry responsible to an elective assembly. Nova Scotia obtained creditable government in 1848 without a rebellion through the statesmanship of Joseph Howe, son of a Bostonian. The governments of New Brunswick and Prince Edward Island underwent similar peaceful evolution.

In the 1850s Tsimshian Indians2 of coastal British Columbia were savage fighters engaging in ritual cannibalism and they were finally "tamed" by a preacher, William Duncan, by 1862. He was later made governor of Vancouver. The gold rush of Vancouver Island and the Fraser River area occurred in 1858. In the Great Plains were large numbers of Catholic French Indians called "Metis". For 50 years they made yearly excursions in the plains to hunt buffalo and in the middle of the century they were confronted by the Hudson Bay whites, who set up various rules and regulations, which included the prohibiting of those people to trade with the Americans in St. Paul, Minnesota. This prairie land (Rupert's Land) was sold by the Hudson's Bay Company for 300,000 to the New Dominion of Canada in 1869, just 2 years after that Dominion was established by the British North American Act. The sale remained unknown to the 6,000 French-speaking and 4,000 English-speaking mixed bloods and 1600 white settlers in the plains areas.

Louis Riel the Younger, 1/8 Chippewa, but educated in Montreal on a Catholic scholar- ship, became the Metis leader. He rebuffed the government's attempts to survey and reclaim the land, working out of his headquarters in Fort Garry, which was later to become Winnepeg. Riel was hung as a traitor to the Dominion in 1885, 15 years after Manitoba had become a province. Canadian Mounted Police had been formed and after the Metis were controlled, the great nations of the Sioux had to be tamed and that included Sitting Bull, himself, who had gone to Canada after the famous Custer massacre in the United States. The end result for these displaced Indians, however, was gradual starvation, as civilization came west with the Canadian Pacific Railroad in the 1880s. We shall hear much more about earlier Indian problems in the vicinity of the Great Lakes in later paragraphs. (Ref. 9, 10, 11)

The formation of the Dominion resulted from three forces, the rise of Canadian nationalism, a desire of British liberals to slough off colonial responsibilities and the ambition of some elements in the United States to annex Canada. The constitution granted to the Dominion reserved the powers of government in the Parliament at Ottawa, but it failed to quench provincialism, particularly among the French population, which considered itself a nation apart, and still does.

Like the United States, Canada had a depression in 1873, which lasted at least 20 years and slowed the growth of that country considerably. It recovered only after the completion of the transcontinental Canadian Pacific Railway in 1885, after years of financial and engineering difficulties. The election of 1896 brought Sir Wilfrid, a French-Canadian lawyer, to head the government as premier and his long administration saw a wave of prosperity as the prairie provinces developed with their new railroad transportation system. Still, at the end of the century great expanses of land in Canada were essentially uninhabited. Lands occupied by 1900 included a narrow strip along the St. Lawrence River, Montreal and the eastern Great Lakes, then southern Manitoba, Saskatchewan and southeastern Alberta, with Winnipeg as a wheat center being the only city of over 100,000 west of Toronto. (Ref. 12, 13)

We cannot leave the discussion of British Canada without reverting back to activities connected to the War of 1812 with the United States. As early as 1811 British Canadian officials believed that war was imminent and began to warn Indians who were friendly to them. Chief among those were the Shawnees, who were led at that time by the mystic Prophet Tenskwatawa and the latter mobilized many Ottawas, Potawatomis and Chippewas in the Lake Michigan region. After some preliminary maneuvering actual land warfare began with the British and Indian forces defeating the Americans at the battles of Brownstown, Monguagon and Fort Michilimackinac. On August 16th Governor William Hull surrendered the American Fort Dearborn, just 24 hours after Potawatomis had killed most of the garrison. That winter the Prophet had trouble feeding his people in the Indiana area, however, and as another American expedition approached, he and most of his followers fled to Canada.

Knowing that the American Governor Harrison was preparing to recapture Detroit, the British commander Brigadier General Henry Proctor launched offensive operations. While ships transported the British regular militia and artillery across Lake Erie, the Prophet and his brother, Chief Tecumseh, led almost 1,200 Indians overland to the mouth of the Maumee. The attack failed and a similar one launched July 21, 1813 also failed. Meanwhile on Lake Erie, Capt. Oliver Perry's fleet took on the British under Capt. Robert Barclay and destroyed them in a 3 hour battle at Put-in-Bay. On land, Proctor talkea his Indians into withdrawing and preparing for new battle on the Thames River. In a great battle about 2 miles west of Moraviantown almost all the British soldiers were killed or captured and the Indians scattered through the forests. Tecumseh was shot down and the Indian remnant had only 374 warriors, with about 650 women and children. The natives spent a miserable winter of 1813-1814 camped at the western end of Lake Ontario and the British gave them just enough supplies to keep them from starving.

The war scene then seemed to shift to the Niagra frontier where the Iroquois were British allies. The Shawnees agreed to join with the Iroquois, but they arrived a full day after the decisive Battle of Chippewa had ended. For 2 years the British Indian Department had been hard pressed to feed all the exiles in Canada and they wanted them back in the United States. It was not until the white immigration into upper Canada occurred in the decade after the Treaty of Ghent, however, that the embittered Tenskwatawa severed his ties with the British Indian Department and returned to the United States where, by 1819, he no longer seemed a threat. (Ref. 14)

THE UNITED STATES

It is not a simple matter to scan the history of the United States in the 19th century in an outline form. The War between the States seems to make a natural break-point, with the situations before and after the war quite different. With this in mind we shall divide this section accordingly.

THE UNITED STATES BEFORE THE CIVIL WAR

THE EAST

Presidential candidates for the election of 1800 were selected by party caucuses in Congress, with no public electioneering and no speeches or statements by the candidates. Even so, the politicians managed to make it a scurrilous campaign with the Republican winner, Jefferson, being accused of being a Jacobin, an atheist and a French agent. Jefferson himself believed that his election saved the country from militarism and monarchy. As for "monarchy", it was Jefferson who founded the "Virginia Dynasty" consisting of 4 presidents, who reigned for almost a third of a century. Each of these administrations will be briefly discussed.

THOMAS JEFFERSON ADMINISTRATION (1801-1808) 3rd President

By 1803 a doctor in backwoods Kentucky had vaccinated 500 people for small-pox. Through the Napoleonic Wars, the United States attempted a neutrality policy, but she could not avoid some combat with the pirates of Tripoli between 1801 and 1804, as we noted on page 1051. Meanwhile, the boundary of the nation went west to the Rocky Mountains through the purchase of the Louisiana territory from Napoleon for $16,000,000, since the little emperor was afraid Britain would soon pluck it from him anyway. But we shall discuss this more in a later paragraph when we outline the Mississippi valley region. (Ref. 15, 16) Jefferson himself was a most complex man and we have noted many of his characteristics on page 1028. A few additional remarks may be of interest here. The existence of his mulatto children was made public by the journalist James Thomas Callender in 1802 and again by the New England Palladium in 1805. In the field of religion, he re-wrote the New Testament, leaving out all mysticism, Virgin Birth, miracles, etc., entitling the work The Philosophy of Jesus of Nazareth. It was not published until after his death. As this man and his party gained power, the New England Federalists and their clergy worried about terror, atheism and free-love resulting from all this triumph of democracy. Alexander Hamilton, rising in stature on the political scene, truly expected Jefferson's regime to end in anarchy like the French Republic and he was ready to step in as the United States Bonaparte. He was killed in a duel by Aaron Burr, the vice-president, who was politically dead, himself, after that duel. Burr, 1806, tried to hatch a conspiracy against the United States from the region of New Orleans and that lead to a treason charge, from which he was finally freed by the work of his attorney, John Marshall. Burr left for Europe, there to try still more conspiracies unsuccessfully and finally returned to the United States in disguise in 1812. (Ref. 17, 18)

To go back a few years, Jefferson, concerned with the European situation which saw Napoleon still strong and the British navy supreme, built up the federal government to cope. But high wages in the United States navy and merchant marine began to attract deserters from the Royal Navy, so that the latter soon began to use that as an excuse to stop neutral U.S. ships and search them for deserters. Such an episode in June 1807, involving the U.S.S. Chesapeake, brought the new country and Britain to the brink of war. (Ref. 19)

JAMES MADISON ADMINISTRATION(1809-1815) 4th President

In 1808 Congress had passed a law against the importation of slaves, but it was not strictly enforced because Eli Whitney's cotton gin initially made slave labor in the fields seem even more needed. In addition the invention of the gin introduced the principle of mass production to America, a feature which led to the Colt revolver, the sewing machine and the flour mill, revolutionizing the status of human labor, particularly in the western world and still more especially in the northern states. The north welcomed the Industrial Revolution while the south rejected it. After Jean Etienne Bore had demonstrated how to make granulated sugar from cane, a great sugar empire began to stretch along the Gulf. With the development of a steamboat which could go upstream against the Mississippi current, the sugar was sent to St. Louis, Louisville and Cincinnati for refining. (Ref. 20)

Although a great statesman, Madison was a poor politician and as a result of his ineptitude and Napoleon's maneuverings, difficulties with England increased. Both French and English navies were seizing and even scuttling American vessels. In 1811 Madison forbade all intercourse with England and as Napoleon had closed all Europe to Britain at the same time, it made for a very bad winter in England. By 1812 the United States and England were at war.

In the meantime, as the Spanish Empire appeared to be breaking up, the inhabitants of "West Florida" elected for the United States and were soon incorporated as the Territory of Orleans (later part of the state of Louisiana. We must also discuss the Indian situation in the Ohio and Indiana regions at this time. By 1800 many Indians were ready to try the white man's ways. Late in 1801 a delegation of chiefs from the Potawatomis, Miamis, Delawares, Shawnees, Kickapoos and Kaskaskias visited the east and two of the chief s asked for government assistance. As a result, during that first decade of the century the federal government and various religious organizations sent funds, farming implements and advisors to those tribes. Yet most of the programs were mismanaged and unscrupulous agents even sold the farm implements to white settlers. But primarily the Indians themselves could not become adjusted to the new ways. The Shawnees, early known as the "Southerners" by other Algonquian-speaking peoples shared the same problems. Branches of this tribe were scattered across the south, the Gulf Coast, the Delaware Valley, Georgia and South Carolina at various periods. In this century many were settled in Ohio and Indiana when the white citizens there declared an "open season" on Shawnee property. That, along with Shawnee excessive drinking, economic difficulties and various injustices led to deterioration of relationships. Some of these Shawnees, including a young prince, Tecumseh, had fought against the Americans under "Mad Anthony" Wayne at the end of the last century. Now Tecumseh's brother Tenskwatawa, a Shawnee holy man, sought to save his people with a new mystic religion. Claiming that he had been appointed by the Great Spirit he established Prophetstown near where the Tippecanoe joins the Wabash River, denounced alcohol and polygamy and set up certain rituals. The future president William Henry Harrison kept pushing his land acquisitions and further antagonizing various tribes, all of which soon began to accept the new Shawnee religion and join the groups at Prophetstown. The Kickapoos, Potawatomis, Ottawas, Chippewas, Crees, Winnebagos, Sacs, Miamis and Assiniboins were all converts. By 1807 Prophetstown had over 60 cabins and wigwams clustered around a frame council-house measuring about 150 by 34 feet. William Wells, the Indian agent at Fort Wayne, warned both then Governor Harrison and the Secretary of War that the Prophet constituted a serious threat and it was certainly true that most of these Indians had begun to sympathize more with the British in Canada than with the "Long Knives" Americans. Only the Shawnee clan led by Chief Black Hoof remained loyal to the United States. (Ref. 21)

But the Prophet began to have trouble feeding his hordes at his "holy city" and when the Ottawas and Chippewas near Lake Michigan defected, Harrison thought that the Shawnee leader was slipping and he made plans for further land encroachment. In September 1809 he signed a Treaty of Fort Wayne with Miamis, Delawares and some Potawatomis, obtaining over 3,000,000 acres of land in Indiana and Illinois. The Shawnees were incensed and Tecumseh set out south to try to gather more of his scattered kinsmen for a final confrontation. He also visited the British at Malden and, as we noted on page 1139, the British, foreseeing possible war with the United States, began to court these Indians, sending them food, arms and ammunition. Finally in the fall of 1811, after several unsuccessful conferences, Harrison started north from Vincennes with an army to put an end to Prophetstown. The famous Battle of Tippecanoe began in the early morning of November 7, 1811.

"Harrison described the battle as a 'complete and decisive' American victory, and three decades later he would gain the presidency as 'Old Tippecanoe', a military hero who had soundly beaten the Indians on the Wabash. But a closer examination of the battle and its outcome indicates that Harrison's claims were exaggerated. Both white and Indian losses were much the same. The American force numbered close to 1,000 officers and men. They suffered 188 casualties, of which at least 62 were fatal. The number of Indians engaged in the contest is much more difficult to ascertain, but there were probably between 600 and 700 warriors. Reports of Indian casualties also vary widely, but probably at least fifty were killed and seventy were wounded.''3

THE WAR OF 1812

War was declared on the basis of the impressment of American seamen, repeated violations of American territorial rights and alleged blockading of the American coast. Although New England, where 3/4 of the American shipping was owned and which supplied most of the seamen, wanted no part of the war4, the war-hawks thought the fight, if successful, would result in the conquering of Canada, end the Indian menace and throw more western land open. Many politicians, including William Henry Harrison, had already grabbed land in the amount of about 48,000,000 acres between 1795 and 1809. The belief of many that Britain was behind the Shawnee Confederacy just described above, helped force the declaration of war on June 18th. Greatly outnumbered, the one saving fact for the United States navy vessels was that the Royal Navy was so deeply engaged in war at the same time with France and could spare only 1 ship of the line, 7 frigates and a number of smaller ships to operate off the American coast. The British did blockade much of the east coast and there was action, as we have seen (pages 1139-40) on and around the Great Lakes. The war was unpopular everywhere, perhaps due to poor leadership from Madison. After Napoleon's abdication in April, 1814, Britain was able to provide Canada with an adequate army and things changed rapidly, with the British war office planning a three pronged invasion attack - at Niagara, Lake Champlain and New Orleans - as well as raiding at Chesapeake. A British raiding party did enter Washington, ate at the White House (which Madison had evacuated) and burned all public buildings of the capitol. Otherwise execution was poor, however, and the final New Orleans attack was thwarted by General Andrew Jackson, although unknown to those participants, the peace had already been signed in Ghent.

After the war there was a great stimulus to manufacturing and by 1815 there were 500,000 spindles in operation. The Federalist New Englanders were actually talking about secession at that time, but the Republicans of the same area kept the activity under control. Those two parties continued to struggle for a quarter of a century. (Ref. 24) In 1814 General Andrew Jackson had defeated the Creeks at Horseshoe Bend near the border of Georgia and Alabama and so, after his defeat of the British at-New Orleans in the following year, the United States was well in control of the old "southwest". (Ref. 25, 26)

JAMES MONROE ADMINISTRATION (1817-1824) 4th President

Except for the Monroe Doctrine, the Supreme Court decisions of Chief Justice Marshall were the only enduring feature of the new nationalism of 1815 and after. The decisions included the defense of the constitutionality of the new Bank of the U.S., the right of the Supreme Court to review state court decisions concerning treaties or laws affecting the nation and finally the denial of the states to withhold militia from national service when demanded by the president. Henry Clay and John Calhoun were nationalist leaders in Congress at that time and both feared sectionalism. A post-war depression appeared in 1819 and in the recovery period, the question of slavery arose, with both sides threatening secession. In fear, Congress passed the Missouri Compromise, in which Missouri was admitted to the union as a slave state, but slavery was prohibited thereafter in any area north of Missouri's southern border, latitude 36~ 30". At the same time, Maine, which had just detached itself from Massachusetts, was admitted, thus making 12 free and 12 slave states.

It is appropriate here to return momentarily to the Indian situation in the southeast United States. In spite of all contact with Christianity the Southern Indians clung to many of their ancient rituals, especially the "bush" or annual Green Corn Festival, which lasted for several days after the new corn ripened and homage was paid to the Sun, Corn and similar Indian deities. However, many of the Indians and mestizos lived among the colonists, merged into the white culture and in time forgot their language and traditions. Genetically they had considerable impact, far more than is generally realized. After their many troubles more than 500 Creek survivors congregated in southern Alabama near Atmore, where for decades they lived near whites and Negroes. Each had its own school system, although the whites were dominant and discriminated against both ~he other groups. But mixing was considerable and today many of the "whites" in this area are in part Creek. All Indians were not exterminated by disease, warfare or-the later transfer west. In part they remained in the south, partly absorbed and helping to create 1 9th century "Negroes". Even Alex Haley, author of Roots, has Indian forebears. In the 1920s the anthropologist Melvill Herskovits made a random anthropometric survey of students at Howard University in Washington D.C. and of a selected groups of Negroes living in Harlem. One-third of each group displayed physical characteristics of Indian ancestry. In 1947 the historian August Meier made a genealogical survey of Negro college students in the southern heartland of Mississippi and adjoining states. On a large sample, 70% had Indian ancestors5. Thus right (Ref. 27) feels that the American black is not an African black but actually a new race. It is difficult to determine the extent of Indian blood in the American Negro because one does not have any of the Timucuans, Stonos, Occaneechees and other extinct tribes to study and present day Powhatans and Cherokees are not the same as those found at the time of first white contact.

In the United States early the word "slave" became synonymous with "black", "African" or "nigger" and since there were many Indian slaves, they were of ten subject to the same names and, in fact, considered the same. Actually genetically the southern Negro was a product of Africans, whites and Indians. After slave importation from Africa was outlawed and Indian slave raids in the South had become relatively insignificant, the percentage of males among those races of the south changed. The male Africans decreased in percentage while the male Indians increased. The famed Seminole Chief Osceola's spouse, or at least one of them, in all probability was a Negro and his father in all likelihood was white. A physical anthropologist who has examined Osceloa's bones has speculated that he had African forebears as well. Many modern Negroes are doubtless correct in claiming direct descent from that great Seminole warrior. As the Cherokees became increasingly cultured, they adopted white attitudes toward Negroes, but it was different among the Seminoles. Both slave and free Africans lived among them and indeed were a part of the Seminoles and their presence became more conspicuous during the 19th century Seminole wars. In 1818 General Andrew Jackson stormed into Spanish Florida and his major objective was Bowlegs Town, a sizable Negro settlement on the Suwannee River. (Ref. 29)

As Monroe's Secretary of State, in December, 1823, John Quincy Adams insisted that the president issue what became known as the Monroe Doctrine. As a warning to European pawers who might have designs on any of the new central and south American governments and to Russia, who was claiming new territory on the Canadian coast, the doctrine may be summarized as follows:

The American continent was not to be considered as subject for future colonization by European powers
The U.S. would not interfere with any existing European colonies

JOHN QUINCY ADAMS (1825-29) A minority president

Adams was a great patriot and wanted to use federal revenue to increase the navy, build national roads and canals, send out scientific expeditions and establish institutions of learning and research, but most of these things were not to materialize for some years to come.

ANDREW JACKSON (OLD HICKORY) (1829-37) 6th President and MARTIN VAN BUREN (1837-41) 7th President

This was the era of the great political figures - Adams, Clay, Webster, Van Buren and Calhoun, and it marked the beginning of the modern Democratic political party. The Adams - Jackson political campaign of 1828 was the most degrading experience of an election that the United States had experienced. Jackson was ill-educated, intolerant and rough, yet professing the principles of the Declaration of Independence and devoted to the union. Jacksonian democracy was the upsurge of a new generation of recently enfranchised voters against a somewhat ossified Jefferson Republican party. (Ref. 30) Jackson Democrats believed in equality only for white men and they introduced the spoils system into federal government, catered to mediocrity and diluted politics with the incompetent and the corrupt. The jackass as a symbol of the Democratic party was first used by the opposing Whigs as a satire on the supposed ignorance of "Old Hickory". Two vital issues of that time were:

Nullification. First set forth in the Exposition of 1828 by the legislature of South Carolina, this stated that each state had the right to judge when its "agent", the federal government, exceeded its powers and then to take measures to prevent enforcement within state limits. Calhoun was the secret author. Jackson threatened the use of army and navy in a showdown in 1833 and South Carolina backed down
The Bank of the United States. Jackson forced the demise of the previously well run U.S. Bank by denying it government funds. Local banks, released from control, increased paper credit for speculation in western lands and shortly there- after the financial panic of 1837 burst upon the country. Van Buren, a shrewd, able and dignified president spent the whole of his administration developing a substitute for the Bank of the United States. He was also the principal architect of the modern American political party

Andrew Jackson hated the British and all Indians, due to several unfortunate incidents in his childhood. It was an almost foregone conclusion, therefore, that when the whites wanted more land for cotton in the south that Jackson should outlaw the tribal kingdoms of the Choctaws, Creeks, Chickasaws and Cherokees in Mississippi, Alabama and Georgia. The Indians appealed to the Supreme Court and Chief Justice John Marshall upheld their claim, but Jackson paid no attention and ordered the army "to get them out". 30,000 of those Indians were driven, one way or another on the "Trail of Tears" to Oklahoma and one quarter of them died on the trip. (Ref. 31, 32) The common impression that after the 1830s all Southern Indians had been either killed or removed to Oklahoma is misleading, however, because some 74,000 are still present in the South today, living in loose, ill-defined clusters, such as the Creeks around Poarch, Alabama and the Lumbees south of Fayetteville, North Carolina or on reservations. It was during Jackson's administration that the Second Seminole War was fought in 1835. Abolitionists charged that this was really not an Indian but a Negro war, resulting from southern white determination to capture and enslave Negro-Seminoles. Many parallels exist between the maroon wars in Jamaica (see page 1035) and the several Seminole wars fought in Florida, Georgia and Alabama. (Ref. 33)1

1 The Chickasaw, Creek and Choctaw were all advanced civilized peoples, but the Cherokees were astounding. Spread over northwest Georgia into Alabama and part of Tennessee, the Cherokees had a printed language, which had been developed by George Gist, also known as Sequoyah, a Cherokee half-breed. Bibles, other books and even a weekly newspaper, "The Cherokee Phoenix", were printed. They welcomed Christian missionaries, built roads, houses and churches. In 1826 a Cherokee reported that his people possessed 22,000 cattle, 7,600 houses, 46,000 swine, 2,500 sheep, 762 looms, 1,488 spinning wheels, 2,948 plows 10 saw mills, 31 grist mills, 62 blacksmith shops and 18 schools. They were more civilized than the Georgia "crackers", who coveted their lands. The independence of that Cherokee nation had been guaranteed by the U.S. in a treaty of 1791, but the state of Georgia had been chopping away at their lands for 30 years and the discovery of gold in the area in 1828 was the last straw. The Indians had to be moved to Oklahoma Territory. The journey cost them 25% of their numbers but they retained their identity, government, language and alphabet to this day. (Ref. 34)  There were several important landmarks in the approach to the American Civil War. Among these was the Dred Scott Decision. Dred Scott, a slave, having been taken temporarily into a free state, sued for his freedom and the Supreme Court decided against him on these grounds: (1) A Negro could not be a U.S. citizen and therefore could not sue. (2) As a resident of Missouri, the laws of Illinois (where he had been taken) did not apply. (3) In any event, Congress could not deprive citizens of their property - in this case a slave. This was in 1857. Another stepping stone toward war was John Brown's raid: John Brown, a long avid abolitionist, seized the federal arsenal at Harpers’ Ferry in October, 1859, as the first step in establishing a planned Negro Republic. He was later hanged. In the meantime, Lincoln, as a member of the new Republican Party, appeared on the scene. His party won the Congressional elections of 1860, combining solid policies of Hamiltonian Federalism with the hopeful, humanitarian outlook of the old party of Jefferson. Minnesota and Oregon were admitted as new states in 1858 and 1859, making 18 free and still only 15 slave states. Lincoln won the new presidential election as the Democrats fought and split over Douglas and Buchanan. (Ref. 35)  The Navaho Indians have withstood the white onslaught better than most and this may be because they are cultural "borrowers" - learning agriculture, weaving and pottery from their early, settled, Pueblo neighbors, stealing horses from the Spanish and many social and religious ideas from the Mexicans. In 1863 Colonel Kit Carson subjugated the Navaho and imprisoned 8,500 of them in Fort Sumner. After three years they were released to a 16 million acre reservation in the southwest. While in prison some learned silver working and with this and their other skills they have survived as traders in the American market. (Ref. 36, 37, 38)  Up to 1868 nearly 450 treaties had been signed by the U.S. government with various Indian groups and scarcely a one remained unbroken. With the end of the Indian wars an economic recession hit the West, for up to 1870 the federal administrations had been spending about $1,000,000 for every Indian killed.  (Ref. 39)

WILLIAM HENRY HARRISON & JOHN TYLER (1841-1845) Whig party

We have previously noted that Harrison was elected, in great part, on the basis of his questionable victory over the Indians at Tippecanoe. (See pages 1143-44). Upon Harrison's early death, his vice-president, John Tyler, succeeded to the presidency, both of them representing those old Jefferson Republicans who would not follow Jackson. They were helped by a few remnants of the old Federalists.

The next several presidents of the eastern establishment contributed few major policies or advancements to the nation. JAMES K. POLK (1845-49), a Democrat, did bait Mexico in order to win California. This will be discussed in a later section on "Texas and Mexican War". He was followed by GENERAL ZACHARY TAYLOR, (1849-50), a Whig whose chief fame was that he was president during the period of the California gold rush, which will also be described later. MILLARD FILMORE, (1850-53) was a Whig who became president upon Taylor's death and signed the compromise bill admitting California and Texas as states and the organization of New Mexico and Utah as territories free to enter the Union without reference to slavery. His administration was the last of the Whig party, as FRANKLIN PIERCE (1853-57) was then elected as a Democrat. During his administration, Daniel Webster was Secretary of State and it was the time of the Kansas-Nebraska Bill, which will be mentioned in a later paragraph. JAMES BUCHANAN was elected for one term as a Democrat in 1857 and slavery was the real issue of that campaign as the slave trade continued, even though it had been illegal since Fillmore's administration. Between 1840 and 1847 some 440,000 slaves were illicitly exported to the United States, Cuba and Brazil. In 18 months of 1859 and 1860 some 85 slave ships were fitted out in New York City, alone. (Ref. 40)

We have very briefly covered the political and governmental situation up to the time approaching the Civil War, but we need to find out more about how people lived in that time. Cholera ravaged the entire country three times in this century and yellow fever hit the northeast early and then the southern and Gulf of Mexico ports, with a peak in 1860. (Ref. 41) Northern U.S. society experienced the industrial revolution, cheap transportation, educational and migratory movements and those things influenced the border states somewhat, but the lower south was entirely apart, as was the far west and the southwest. Thus we shall now discuss the various parts of the country separately.

First the north. This was a busy age, with every northern community a human ant-hill of activity. Most white workers still worked 63 hours a week and 18% of all children were still employed. Everything was business, there were no public parks or pleasure resorts, few games or sports. Sculling in the eastern harbors was the only competitive sport, trotting horse races about the only entertainment. As early as 1856 there were 38 trotting courses of national repute in the northern area. Medicine was bad and anyone wanting a good medical education had to go to Austria or France. Tuberculosis, cholera, typhus and yellow fever killed thousands. Dr. Oliver Wendell Holmes did write on puerperal fever in 1842, antedating Semmelweis by 4 years, but few believed him. Dr. William W. Gerhard of Philadelphia did a fine study of cerebral meningitis in 1834 and later distinguished typhus and typhoid fevers. Dr. Crawford W. Long of Georgia, in 1842 and Dr. W.T.C. Morton of Massachusetts, in 1846 successfully used ether for anesthesia. Dr. Philip Physick of Philadelphia established surgery as a specialty and the American Medical Association was founded in 1847.

City water systems and sanitation were crude or absent. Philadelphia pioneered with pumping water from the Schuylkill River and by 1830 could deliver 6,000,000 gallons of water daily. But Chicago, owing to difficulty of drainage, had practically no plumbing until 1861. Boston, with a population of 165,000 in 1857 had only 6,500 toilets, of which 8, in the basement of the Tremont House, served 200 to 300 guests. Illuminating gas was fairly common by 1860 and 337 cities had it piped in from central plants using coal. Although the district of Michigan only had 31639 people in 1832, there were 940 miles of post roads. (Ref. 42, 43)

Immigr2tion from Europe accelerated. In the 1830s there were 540,000 newcomers with 44% Irish, 30% German and 15% English, but by 1840 the number rose to 2,814,554 in the following decade. Almost all arrived and stayed in the north and almost all became Jackson Democrats through the planned manipulations of the party hacks. Irish immigrants comprised 34% of all voters in New York City in 1855, but they contributed little to American economic or intellectual life. Ugly racial and religious riots arose in the eastern cities at least once every decade.

The factory system for cotton spinning and weaving became well established in New England, so that by 1840 there were 1,200 cotton factories, operating 2,250,000 spindles in the United States, 2/3 of these in New England. By 1850 there were over 1,500 woolen mills. These and other mills were operated largely by water power. In 1860 manufacturing produced $1,000,000,000. The iron industry developed very slowly. It has been written that the Atlantic towns heated their houses with coal brought 3,000 miles from England rather than by wood from their own forests 30 miles away, because sea transportation was that much cheaper than overland. Steam-ships were not in use at the time of those comments. (Ref. 44, 45) Still there were hard times between 1837 and 1841 and westward migration accelerated. Canal and railroad construction created a demand for cheap labor and made it easier for people to reach the west. The-states built their own canals, roads and railroads. Ohio linked the Great Lakes with the Mississippi valley; the Erie canal connected Buffalo to New York City.

By 1820 New York State's population of 1,372,812 was in first place and the increase in inhabitants of New York City was phenomenal. By 1850 there were 515,547 people in the city proper plus 96,838 in Brooklyn. Fortunes were accumulated there, but culture was deficient. Columbia University, the only college present until 1831, graduated only about 24 a year. New York University and Fordham added a very few more after 1841. Upstate New York, however, was well provided with denominational colleges. The most original contribution to higher education was Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, founded at Troy in 1824, the precursor of all the subsequent engineering and technical universities. An interesting aside is the final disposition of the great Dutch estates along the Hudson. Their lands had been rented out in an old feudal type system that involved peculiar considerations. With the death of Stephen Van Rensselaer, "the last patroon" in 1839, a rebellion broke out among his renters, when his sons tried to collect thousands of dollars of back rent. This forced New York legislation modifying the rent and lease laws and systems. Intellectuals of New York State were plentiful, including Clement C. Moore, Professor of Hebrew and Greek, who wrote "The Night Before Christmas"; William Cullen Bryant, America's greatest poet; Edgar Allen Poe; Henry W. Longfellow and Nathaniel Hawthorne. The artist Colonel John Trumbull of Connecticut painted the "Declaration of Independence" and "Battle of Bunker Hill". John Lloyd Stephens founded American archeology after trips to the old Maya scenes in Central America and Yucatan.

In other fields, Abbe Sicard established the first American school for the deaf at Hartford and Samuel Howe and Michael Anagnos founded the Perkins Institute for the blind. Women's suffrage movements were initiated as early as 1848. Many "isms" appeared, not the least of which was Joseph Smith's Mormon faith. In 1836 Emerson published "Essay on Nature", opening the period of transcendentalism, a belief in the divinity of human nature. In the same generation there were Hawthorne, Thoreau and the Alcotts.

By 1850 there had been formulated three basic principles of education:

Free primary and secondary schools should be available for all children
teachers should have professional training
all children should be required to attend some school- up to a certain age

By 1840 over 150 small denominational colleges were in existence in the country. American science soon became specialized. Joseph Henry discovered the electromagnet and many other features of electricity and Samuel F.B. Morse used the former to develop the telegraph. Charles Goodyear had patented the vulcanization of rubber by 1844. The Smithsonian Institute was started in 1846 with Joseph Henry as its first director. Only astronomy lagged and this was due to the effect of organized religion, which considered probing the heavens with a telescope as mildly blasphemous.

And now we must consider life in the American south. We have already discussed the Indian-Negro situation at some length on pages 1115 and 1116. "Cotton was king in the south from 1815 to 1861, and the principle bulwark of his throne was Negro slavery"6. By 1860 the crop was almost 2,300,000,000 pounds, accounting for 2/3 of the total exports of the United States and 5/6 of the world's production. In that harvest 4,000,000 slaves were used. A prime field hand 18 to 25 years old was worth $500 in 1832 and $1.300 just before the panic of 1837, although their yearly maintenance cost only $15 to $60. Morison (Ref. 46) says that 13% of all Negroes in the U.S. in 1860 were mulattoes, but as we have seen, later writers might put this much higher, especially if one adds in Indian blood. The south was ruled by a few but strong classical southern gentlemen, of which only a few descended from the colonial aristocracy. The great mass of wealthy planters by 1860 were self-made men like Jefferson Davis, whose parents had lived in log cabins. There were probably fewer than 15,000 families of the southern white gentry and most of the white southerners were small farm owners. The latter were actually the governing class in Alabama, Mississippi and Arkansas. About half the cotton crop was made by those who owned from 1 to 6 slaves. Whites were forbidden to teach slaves to read and write in every southern state except Maryland, Kentucky and Tennessee. (Ref. 47) In contrast to this slavery in America we should recall that although slavery was almost universal in more ancient times, the slaves then were of the same race as their masters, of ten the better educated and usually could work or buy their way out of slavery eventually. In the U.S., slavery was fatally united with the permanent, physical fact of color. (Ref. 48) A slave rebellion led by Nat Turner in Virginia in 1831 resulted in the deaths of 57 whites and perhaps up to 100 Negroes before it could be put down by regular troops and navy personnel. Elsewhere in America slaves were being freed, in the British colonies in 1833, the French Antilles in 1848 and the Spanish republics in turn between 1813 and 1854. Only in a few Spanish and Dutch islands, the United States and Brazil did slavery continue after 1854. Some effort had been made to return blacks to Africa by the American Colonization Society, but by 1855 only 3,600 had been sent. This did help the Republic of Liberia to form a constitution patterned on the U. S. model, however, in 1857.

There was little literary, scientific or artistic production from the prewar south, with the exception of some outstanding "firsts" in medicine. Ephraim McDowell (trained at the University of Edinburgh) developed an international reputation in abdominal surgery, while J. Marion Sims, practicing in Alabama, laid the basis for the specialty of gynecology. As noted previously, Dr. Crawford Long of Georgia used ether for anesthesia in 1842, but he did not publicize his discovery for several years. The first dental school in the world was established in Baltimore in 1839. (Ref. 49) The south's one scientific achievement was Commander Matthew Fontaine Maury's Physical Geography of the Sea (1855), which marked him as the world's greatest oceanographer. Most of the south's energy, however, seemed to be devoted to backing up John Calhoun's ridiculous pro-slavery doctrines. Even in religion the southerners were different. Both the southern divisions of the Methodist and Baptist churches defended slavery. There were many reasons for the great resistance to the emancipation of the slaves. We have already noted that the invention of the cotton gin, which made cultivation of upland cotton by slaves profitable, was one factor. Jacksonian Democracy was another great influence, because of the rise of provincial, ill-educated politicians, who catered to the prejudices of the middle class and poor whites. Instead of preparing the south for the inevitable emancipation, those men flattered people into the fatal belief in the righteousness of slavery.

THE MIDDLE WEST AND THE LOUISIANA PURCHASE REGION

In this section we shall be concerned primarily with the territory gained through the "Louisiana Purchase" and what we currently consider the Middle West. We have infringed somewhat on this by discussing pre-war features in Ohio, Indiana and Illinois, but in this 1 9th century it seemed that those regions were more closely linked with the traditional EAST.

There were many reasons for Napoleon's sale of the Louisiana Territory - his need for money, his fear that Britain would otherwise soon take it from him, and his General Leclerc's recent loss of 24,000 men over a 9 month period to disease and the arms of 500,000 black Haitians, who would not be enslaved. The legality of the sale was questionable, however, as the area was still in the hands of Spain, even though the French claimed that Spain had ceded the area to Napoleon in a secret treaty of 1801. At the time the contested region was an unmanned, undefended empire with the whole watershed of the Mississippi and comprising the present states of Louisiana, Arkansas, Oklahoma, both the Dakotas. Iowa, Nebraska, Kansas, Minnesota, Colorado, Wyoming and Montana, - that is, one-third of North America. The sale price of $16,000,000 actually amounted to 4 cents an acre. After the purchase, President Jefferson then appointed Meriwether Lewis and William Clark, along with a 16 year old Shoshone Indian girl and her French-Canadian husband as guides and interpreters, to survey the new purchase. They left St. Louis in May of 1804. (Ref. 50, 51, 52)

The boundaries of the Louisiana territory were actually very poorly defined except in the east and south, where the Mississippi and Red rivers respectively served as "natural barriers". On the west the border was the Rocky Mountains, whatever line that might indicate, and on the north there was even less definition, with mention of a border in the vicinity of the origin of the Mississippi and Missouri rivers. By this century, the Sioux

Indians, who had been in the Michigan region in the early 1 7th century, then in Minnesota late in that century, had gone on to the Black Hills of South Dakota in the 18th century, driving out the Cheyenne and the Kiowa. In this 19th century they inhabited large areas of the north Great Plains and western prairies of Wisconsin, Iowa, Minnesota, North and South Dakota, as well as some regions in Canada. There were 7 tribes with a total of about 30,000 people. Like the Shawnees, most of them supported the British in the War of 1812. Treaties of one sort and another were signed with the United States in 1815, 1825, and 1851. (Ref. 53)

Even after the United States acquired Missouri in the Louisiana Purchase, French influence remained dominant in that region. But Americans began to filter in, particularly in the regions of the lead mines at Ste. Genevieve and Potosi. By the time of the Lewis and Clark expedition St. Louis was already notable as the gateway to the Far West. Later St. Joseph, Missouri was the supply center for the gold rush "49ers" and over 50,000 emigrants went through that city of only 3,000 permanent people. (Ref. 54, 55) On his return from Canada the Shawnee Prophet, Tenskwatawa, led his people into Missouri, but they met some resistance from local tribes and the whites and late in 1827 they left St. Louis, en route for Kansas. (Ref. 56) We have mentioned the admission of Missouri as a state of the Union and the politics involved in the "Missouri Compromise" on page 1145. Settlement quickened after the 1820s and many German immigrants arrived in the 1840s and 1850s.

In the early century part of the mid-west was not very enticing. De Tocqueville (Ref. 57) describes all the land which is now Oklahoma, Kansas, southern Nebraska, the panhandle of Texas and eastern Colorado and New Mexico as a desert, generally covered with sand incapable of cultivation' In the decade following 1821 some 271 steamboats were launched on the Mississippi and its tributaries. (Ref. 58) The treeless prairies were not well settled down to 1850, but then new machinery such as McCormick's mechanical reaper, Marsh's harvester, the steel-toothed cultivator, etC., along with the rising price of wheat up to $2.50 a bushel in 1855 and the building of railroads into the prairie country, stimulated a great proliferation of farmers. Politics was involved in the building of the railroads as well as the bill for the organization of the Great Plains as the "Territory of Nebraska" in 1854 and Stephen Douglas of Illinois was a promoter of both. The political issue was again slavery and its relation to the new Territory and the old Missouri Compromise (see page 1145). The old "Northwest" seethed with indignation over the Kansas-Nebraska Act which nullified the Missouri Compromise and was ripe to form a new anti-slavery party - a new "Republican" one. In Kansas itself, slavery and anti-slavery immigrants actually came to war, anticipating the Civil War and federal troops had to restore order. The two contending groups then each held conventions asking for statehood. The anti-slavery Topeka convention was rejected by the Senate in 1856 and the Le Compton Constitution was accepted.

Some of the Creeks, Cherokees and other southern Indians had migrated on their own to Oklahoma as early as 1818, and then, of course, Andrew Jackson moved hundreds there during his administration. After the Creeks had relocated in Oklahoma, supposedly not 1% could prove that they had no mixed blood. In many instances, this eventually resulted in a reversal of the old Indian matrilineal society and that created much tension. As early as 1819 the Cherokee Council had specifically prohibited white men from disposing of their Indian wives' property. (Ref. 59) Settling on the hills and meadow lands in the eastern section of Oklahoma territory, the so-called "Five Civilized Tribes"7 formed organized states and communities. They clashed some with the Plains Indians, particularly the Osage, but they were pretty well free of white interference before the Civil War.

THE SOUTHWEST (TEXAS, NEW MEXICO & THE MEXICAN WAR)

In 1805 a "neutral ground" was established as a buffer zone between the United States and Mexico in the area between the Sabine River in the west and the Arroyo Hondo, a tributary of the Red River in the east. This soon became a haven for outlaws. In 1820 New Mexico, which then included Arizona and Texas, was a frontier province of Mexico and the latter country encouraged emigration from the United States. In 1821 Stephen F. Austin, taking over a grant which had been given to his father, settled 300 U.S. families in the most fertile region of Texas and by 1834 his colony comprised some 20,000 whites and 2,000 slaves, outnumbering the native Mexicans in Texas by 4 to 1. By the following year there were 28,000 North Americans and to these were soon added swashbucklers like Sam Houston, David Burnet, Branch Archer, Davy Crockett and the Bowie brothers of long knife fame. When Mexican President Santa Anna proclaimed the constitution of 1835, sweeping away state rights within the Mexican domain, the North Americans in Texas, led by Austin, expelled the Mexican garrison from San Antonio de Bexar and seceded, declaring Texas' independence. Santa Anna responded by crossing the Rio Grande with 3,000 men, besieging the 200 Texans at the Alamo fortress, killing them all. Already the colonists had proclaimed an independent Republic of Texas, elected David Gouverneur Burnet president ad interim and put Generalissimo Sam Houston in charge of troops. The latter defeated Santa Anna near the present day city of Houston and after quarreling with Burnet, he became the next president of the Lone Star Republic, which was recognized by President Jackson of the U.S. in 1837. The white population was barely 50,000 and the finances were poor.

Annexation to the United States was a solution to the Texas problems, but such occurred only after much bickering. It was finally hastily arranged after influential southern editors and politicians feared that the Republic of Texas would abolish slavery and they wanted Texas for a slave state, to balance the northern abolitionist ones. President Tyler arranged the annexation in 1845. The Mexican War, which broke out shortly thereafter may have resulted because President James Polk goaded Mexico into war in order to win California for the U.S. He had tried to buy California, unsuccessfully, so he took advantage of some debt repudiations by Mexico to put further pressure on the Mexican government, for collection. At the same time another Mexican revolution occurred and the new government there was spoiling for a fight. Polk ordered troops across the Rio-Grande on January 13, 1846 and the war was on. It had little support in the east but was popular in the Mississippi Valley, where the army received 49,000 volunteers. In March of 1847 General Winfield Scott landed 3 miles from Vera Cruz with an army, then marched to Mexico City along the old Spanish invasion trail and by September Mexico had surrendered. By the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo (1848) New Mexico (including most of Arizona8) was ceded along with Upper California (including San Diego) to the United States and the border of Texas was acknowledged at the Rio Grande. The U.S. assumed the previously disputed, unpaid claims and paid an additional $15,000,000. (Ref. 61, 62) (See also page 1160 for New Mex.)

THE WEST

The original Oregon Territory included the present day states of Oregon, Washington and Idaho and the province of British Columbia. The final border settlement with Great Britain was made in June 1846 under Polk's administration. Backwoodsmen from Iowa, Missouri, Illinois and Kentucky made up most of the early white settlers and they were originally led there by the Rocky Mountain beaver hunters known as "Mountainy men". Indian troubles occurred from time to time, including the Cayuse War of 1847. The Cayuse Indians9, closely associated with the Nez Perce, but separate, blamed some missionaries for an outbreak of small-pox and killed those in the mission. The white settlers than declared war and subdued the Indians, who were placed on a reservation in 1855.

The Church of Jesus Christ of the Latter-day Saints, commonly called the Mormon Church, was responsible for settling Utah. Brigham Young, heir to Joseph Smith, who was murdered in Illinois in 1844, reached Utah with his followers in 1847. Included were some 4,000 English converts. By 1848 over 5,000 people had arrived and the Utah Territory was organized in 1850 with Young as territorial governor.

The development of Wyoming was closely allied with the fur trade and the great westward migrations. When John Colter, a trapper in the Wyoming Mountains, first returned to St. Louis with tales of the great canyons and steaming geysers of Yellowstone, he was ridiculed. Soon, however, the "Mountainy men" entered the country and helped establish the western route to Oregon through South Pass. The trail has hundreds of graves of those who died in blizzards, from starvation, disease and Indian attacks. In the first half of the century Colorado, part of the Spanish territory, was occupied chiefly by Indians, with only the occasional white hunter. The Comanches, Cheyennes, Arapahos and the Kiowas combined forces in 1840 to combat the invasion of their grounds and the settlement of Colorado by whites was accompanied by massacres, lootings and subsequent reprisals.

In Arizona the Pima Indians, whose language was of the Uto-Aztecan linguistic family, were joined early in the century by the Maricopa of the Hokan-Siouan linguistic stock, along the Gila River. That new alliance allowed them to severely defeat their old enemy, the Yumas, by 1857. (Ref. 65)

We have mentioned in another connection that the Russians visited San Francisco in 1806 and that they established a short-lived Fort Ross some 100 miles north of the Golden Gate in 1812. In 1826 Yankees arrived overland in the persons of Jedediah Smith and his fellow fur trappers, but colonization remained chiefly Mexican until the 1840s. In 1834 Governor Figueroa removed the San Francisco Solano mission from Franciscan monk control and put Mariano Vallejo in charge. Some 250,000 acres of land thus soon fell to his personal ownership and eventually he had 50,000 cattle, 24,000 sheep and 8,000 horses of which 1,000 were broken to saddle. He later supported the United States take-over, although he was put in prison for awhile and lost most of his land.

In 1839 the Swiss John Sutter arrived and established a "kingdom" of New Helvetia on a large area in the Sacramento valley. In 1836 a group calling themselves the "Californios" briefly asserted the independence of California and by 1845 had driven out the last Mexican governor. Led by John C. Fremont, Americans set up a republic at Sonoma under the Bear Flag. As news of the U.S.-Mexico war reached there soon afterwards, Commodore John D. Sloat captured Monterey, the capital, and claimed California for the United States. As we have seen above, by the Treaty of Hidalgo, this annexation was made permanent. Even in 1845 almost nothing was known in the United States about California, except for R.H. Dana's Two Years before the Mast and J.E. Fremont's Report of the Exploring Expedition to Oregon and North California. Barely 6,000 whites lived there and the Indians were weak. In January of the same year of the Hidalgo Treaty, a workman in the Sacramento Valley discovered gold in Sutter's millrace and soon the gold rush to the state was on. San Francisco rose in a few months to a city of 20,000, where eggs sold for $10.00 per dozen. Two years after the gold discovery, California became a non-slave owning state in a package deal, which also admitted Texas and formed territories in New Mexico and Utah. The gold fever was augmented as W.S. Bodie found gold high in the Sierras at "Bodie" in 1859 and struck it really rich in 1876. By 1880 the town of Bodie was roaring with life and death, with 56 saloons, 12,000 people and 1 killing a day. When gold ran out in 1883, Bodie was almost abandoned. (Ref. 66, 67, 68)

Before leaving this section on life in the United States west of the Mississippi before the War between the states, we should give a little additional information about progress in New Mexico, which was the chief center of the Mexican-Spanish civilization north of the Rio Grande. Early in this 19th century, some "North Americans" began to invade the area, including Lt. Zebulon Pike, who subsequently wrote a book which stimulated many Missourians to trek to Sante Fe for trade. Between 1824 and 1825 some 25 wagons left Missouri with about $35,000 worth of merchandise, which was sold in Sante Fe for $190,000,000 in gold. Later hundreds of wagons made the journey and on the return trip many brought mules, which later became identified with the state of Missouri. In 1841 Mirabeau Lamar, the second fully accredited president of the nation of Texas, invited the New Mexicans to join Texas and then raised an army with which to force the union, but the venture failed. (Ref. 69)

ABRAHAM LINCOLN AND THE WAR BETWEEN THE STATES *** (Page 1202)

Because there were 4 candidates in the election of 1860, Lincoln won only 39% of the popular vote and carried only 2 counties in the south. (Ref. 70) As soon as he was elected the south rapidly fell prey to its dreamers with their visions of a great Southern Confederacy expanding around the whole Gulf and spreading from sea to sea, teeming with culture and trade and based on slavery. South Carolina declared its independence on the day before Christmas, 1860 and quickly Alabama, Florida and Mississippi followed, with Louisiana and Texas joining by February 1, 1861. Those states formed the Confederate States of America on February 8th, with the southern Congress electing Jefferson Davis president and Alexander H. Stephens as vice-president. The Confederacy was based on the two contentions of states rights and slavery, the former dooming their ability to wage war successfully and the latter preventing all possibilities of-a foreign ally. All of this occurred before President-elect Lincoln had even taken off ice and nothing was done in Washington until 6 weeks into Lincoln's term. Then multiple attempts at compromise and conciliation were attempted, but failed. Lincoln renewed his party's pledge to respect slavery in those states which had it, but would not acquiesce in secession.

The first gun of the Civil War was fired April 12, 1861 as the Confederate officers started to take Fort Sumter at Charleston, North Carolina. That firing on the flag was enough to arouse patriotism in the north and then events moved swiftly. To win, the north had to completely crush the south and most European experts thought this impossible.

Lincoln's paramount object was to save the Union, not to destroy slavery, but in the fall of 1862 after General Lee's army had been exhausted and depleted at Antietam, he did announce his Emancipation Proclamation to officially free the slaves in the rebel states. The loyal slave states (Delaware, Maryland, Kentucky, West Virginia and Missouri) only later freed their slaves by state action.

Mostly boys fought the Civil War, it being almost certain that the majority on both sides were under 21, many as young as 15. Even the officers were young, some major generals being in their 20s. At least 540,000 Americans (population in 1860 was over 31,000,000) lost their lives in or as a result of that war. The average soldier was sick enough 2 or 3 times each year to be sent to a hospital, which was of ten a more dangerous place than the battlefield. Antisepsis was unknown, anesthetics not always available and abdominal wounds and major amputations meant probable death. The south had the best medical corps as a result of the work of their capable surgeon-general, Dr. Samuel Preston Moore, but neither side had an effective transportation system early and the south never developed one. In the last 2 years of the war the use of anesthetics finally became routine in the northern armies only. (Ref. 71) The commander of the Confederate Navy had a son killed in the Union Navy and Mrs. Lincoln's three brothers died fighting for the south.

In this outline we shall not attempt to record the campaigns and battles of this war. In spite of a series of costly land campaigns over two years, the Union won only after the South had been starved by a Union blockade and split by the Mississippi. The best officers on both sides were West Point graduates, but Lincoln may have been the best strategist of them all. He offered command of the Union forces at the beginning to General Robert E. Lee and Lee was against slavery, but he was a fifth generation Virginian and felt that he had to stay with his state. Most of the fighting was done in rough, forested country. Antietam, Gettysburg and Fredericksburg were the only important battles in open country. General Lee persistently underestimated the effect of rifle fire over open ground and that is why his attacks failed at Antietam and Gettysburg. The Union's .58 caliber rifle, 4' 8" long, fired by a percussion cap, could be fired at 3 rounds per minute and could kill at over 1/2 mile. Mines and submarines were used for defense in shoal waters. A new innovation was air observation from balloons. 50uthern hopes of a quick victory were based on the expectation that the North would not f ight and that England, needing cotton, would go to war to help the South. Both assumptions were in error, although warships for the Confederacy were built in both British and French ports.

During this war, Lincoln wielded a greater power than any president up to the time of Franklin D. Roosevelt and in actuality he was a dictator, from the standpoint of constitutional law. Under one of his proclamations, over 13,000 persons were arrested and confined by military authority for offenses ranging from theft of government property to treason. Lincoln had many enemies in the north, ranging from the religious Osgoodites, who considered him the Beast of the Book of Revelations, to the defeatists "Copperheads", who only wanted to negotiate and finally the "barnburning" Knights of the Golden Circle in the middle west. Lincoln also enraged the Congress by arbitrary acts that went of ten beyond the Constitution or the authority which Congress felt that he had. Until his death he was never wildly popular.

Every school child knows of General Lee's surrender to General Ulysses Grant at Appomattox on April 12, 1865 and of Lincoln's assassination at Ford's theater on the night of April 1 4th at the hand of an actor, John Wilkes Booth, declared to be insane. Some southern armies and vessels surrendered at various times subsequently, the last on November 6th, when the C.S.S. Shenandoah surrendered to British authorities. (Ref. 72, 73)

Map taken from Ref. 97

THE IMMEDIATE EFFECTS OF THE CIVIL WAR

In the North

Production was stimulated in the north and in Philadelphia alone some 180 factories were built within 3 years. Immigration from Europe increased with 800,000 people coming within 5 years. Labor saving devices invented at that time, or in general use, included the Howe sewing machine, the Gordon McKay shoe machine and the mechanical reaper. Pennsylvania oil production went up to 128,000,000 gallons in 3 years. Ref ining methods allowed kerosene glass lamps to light American and English farmhouses. The Homestead Act in 1862 stimulated westward migration and opened up new prairie farmlands. Great fortunes were started - Armour (meatpacking), Havemeyer (sugar), Remington (guns), Carnegie (iron and steel), Borden (milk) and Marshall Field (merchandise). 40,000,000 bushels of wheat and flour were exported in 1861. New states were added during and after the civil conflict. (See map on previous page). Some 15 new colleges were established, including Vassar, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, La Salle, Cornell and Swarthmore. At the end of the war, after the Confederate General Early had raided up to within sight of the capitol, there was inflation and paper dollars fell 2/3 in value-and the cost of living soared.

In the South

The war effort absorbed all. Transportation was wanting so that food and supply distribution was very bad, both during and af ter the war. Some areas starved, while others still had plenty. Texas was geographically removed from it all and uninvaded (except by Comanches) until 1865. Luxuries were imported from Mexico.

THE RECONSTRUCTION PERIOD. 1865 - 1877

There was an extremely rapid demobilization of Union forces and, amazingly, generalized acceptance of the war 's result by the south. Of several thousand southerners who refused to return to allegiance to the nation, a large part went to Texas, with a few to Europe, Brazil and Mexico. Reconstruction is still a controversial subject in American history, of ten distorted by emotion. Still it was a deplorable and tragic period. For up to three years no compulsion was put on the southern states to enfranchise the Negro, but during that time nothing was done to prepare him for citizenship either and much was done to humiliate him and keep him "down". In spite of the stereotype picture of the northern Republicans beating and robbing the south, in actuality millions of dollars of northern money poured into the south for food, education and various charities. Congress, too performed wonders in relief, but not in racial adjustments. President ANDREW JOHNSON appointed provisional civil governors in every former Confederate state where Lincoln had not already done so. The South replaced slavery with the "Black Codes", which everywhere kept the Negro a second class citizen.

In March, 1867, by Act of Congress, military rule replaced the civil administrations of the rebel states. The Union military enrolled a new electorate and proceeded to set up reconstructed state governments. This was accomplished by 1870. Those radical governments persisted in some states for up to 8 years - Louisiana, Florida and Texas - and while they were infamous for some types of corruption, they also accomplished some good legislation that resulted in rebuilding schools, roads, railroads, etc. But overall, those governments were bad and in the end neither the freed Negroes nor the Republican party profited.

More disgraceful activities followed - the impeachment of President Johnson10 and the rise of the Ku Klux Klan.

The election of the war hero, GENERAL ULYSSES S. GRANT to the presidency started a dynasty of Republicans, which lasted almost to the end of the century. Unfortunately, below the presidency the corruption of the party was abominable. The Civil War, like every other war, had broken down morals and everyone was out to "make a fast buck". In addition stock speculation, over-rapid expansion of the agricultural west and a world-wide drop in prices brought on the panic of 1873 and a depression which lasted 3 years. Corruption and boss rule continued throughout the century. (Ref. 74)

EXPANSION, DEVELOPMENT, AND SOCIAL CHANGES IN THE LAST 30 YEARS OF THE 19TH CENTURY

An interesting feature of the last half of the century was the development of the Mormon culture in Utah. When Brigham Young had arrived in that area in 1841 it was the northern-most province of Mexico. The Mormons found a desert and made it over into one of the most fertile areas of the west and for many years they kept to themselves and practiced their religion, which included polygamy. When PRESIDENT GROVER CLEVELAND signed the act which made Utah the 45th state in the 1890s, however, polygamy had to stop. Some of the Mormons migrated to northern Mexico, rather than live under the Union's laws. (Ref. 75)

During the period from 1850 to 1870 the high plains states and the Rocky Mountain areas enjoyed a very moist period, but that was followed by decades of drought, with a great reduction of grass. That had a serious effect on the cattle herds, with a drastic reduction in numbers and it would have been the same for the buffalo herds, reducing them by 50 to 70%, even if they hadn't been over hunted. The Sioux Indians of the Dakotas, who were originally farmers, only became buffalo hunters shortly before their extermination late in this century. The buffalo herds were cut in two by the railroad as it went west in the late 1860s. Up to the time of the Civil War, the eastern (Union Pacific) railroad went only to Council Bluffs, Iowa and there was a Central Pacific RR running north and southwest of the Sierras. In 1866 Congress allowed the two commercial companies to build, one from each direction, and meet wherever they chanced. For a single mile of track they needed 40 cars to carry 400 tons of rail and timber (for- ties, bridges, etc.), fuel and food. The Central Pacific had to get its materials, except for timber, by sea - some 12,000 miles around Cape Horn. Eastern work gangs were chiefly new immigrants, mainly Irish, using plenty of whiskey, while the western crews were primarily Chinese, needing tea.

The United States government gave the companies a subsidy of $16,000 per mile of track on the prairie and $48,000 per mile in the mountains. The two tracks met at Promontory Point, Utah on May 10, 1869. In the first 2 decades of operation, freight rates were lowered 500% and travel time reduced by 900%. By 1890 the rail network was larger than in all Europe, including the British Isles and Russia. (Ref. 76, 77, 78, 79)

In 1867 at the end of a spur railroad line, Joseph McCoy bought the town of Abilene, Kansas for $5 an acre and then spent $5,000 for various kinds of promotions to get cattle there from Texas for shipment east. The result was the Chisholm Trail, beginning in south Texas near the Gulf and going through Oklahoma to Abilene. At the end of the Civil War, herds of 2,000 to 3,000 head of long-horned cattle moved regularly up this trail, from the matrix of some 3,000,000 of those cattle in Texas. Their ancestors had been brought over in the second voyage of Columbus. A good drive to Kansas was completed in three months. In the first 4 years McCoy shipped over 2,000,000 cattle out of his stock yards, greatly exceeding even his own boasts and it is probable that this was the origin of the expression "the real McCoy". In the 1860s and 1870s there were multiple cowtowns with cowboys, claim jumpers, fugitives, prostitutes and the natural enemies - cattlemen and sheep men. The death rate in those cow towns was proportionately 10 or 20 times as high as New York City today. Some of the mining towns were even worse. But the Great Plains, finally cleared of Indians and buffalo, were open for cattle. Between 1860 and 1880 even Kansas increased its cattle herds 16 fold and Nebraska by 30 times. In 1886 Wyoming had 9,000,000 cattle, although many owners went broke in the financial panic of 1885-87) (Ref. 80, 81)

In 1840 it took 233 man-hours of work to grow 100 bushels of wheat, but in 1920 it took only 80 man-hours. Part of that was due to the great increase in the number of draft horses, rising from 6,200,000 in 1850 to over 15,500,000 by 1900. American grain sent to Europe was cheaper than that grown locally and European agriculture was disrupted.

One result of that was Norwegian emigration to America. Social changes were in part related to various immigration patterns. The proportion of British Isle immigrants fell from 45% in 1861-1870 to 18% in 1891-1900 while that of - Russians and southern Europeans rose from 0.1% to 50% in the same period. Most of the newcomers went to the northeast so that in 1900 86% of the foreign-born were in states north of the Ohio River and east of the Mississippi.

The first significant labor organization was the "Knights of Labor", founded in 1869 and winning the first railroad strike in 1884. Marxists and anarchists started other unions, with the latter fanning the infamous Haymarket Square riot in 1886, as part of a Chicago strike. In 1886 Samuel Gompers founded the American Federation of Labor, which gradually succeeded the Knights as the spearhead of the American Labor movement. (Ref. 82, 83)

We have previously mentioned the Homestead Law of 1862 by which anyone could obtain 160 acres of western land by agreeing to work it and produce a crop within 5 years. This was made possible by three agricultural advancements, the windmill, a special plow11 for caked prairie soil invented by John Deere and barbed wire, which would keep cattle out. Of course the latter, in itself, provoked seemingly endless atrocities and battles between the farmers and the scandalized cattlemen. But in the final analysis, transportation was the key to the development of the west. By the end of the century more than 175,000 miles of railroad track had been laid, the Pullman sleeping car had been invented, along with the Westinghouse brake and refrigerator car. The Union Pacific, Central Pacific, Northern Pacific, Southern Pacific and the Santa Fe railroads were all aided by government grants and were well established in this period. The terminals of these lines - Omaha. Kansas City, Oakland, Portland, Seattle and Tacoma - all became metropolitan cities within 30 years, while the populations of all the western states increased by 5 to 10 fold. Of course Chicago, a terminal not only for railroads but also for river and lake traffic from the Great Lakes region, became one of the busiest trade centers of the world.

Alexander Graham Bell invented the telephone in 1876 and Thomas A. Edison the incandescent light bulb in 1879. By 1885 the Bell Telephone Company had over 134,000 subscribers in the United States. Shipping tonnage on the Great Lakes increased from 100,000 in 1865 to 25,000,000 in 1901, with wheat and iron forming the chief cargoes. Pittsburgh became the center of the northern Appalachian coal fields and Birmingham, Alabama the hub of the southern Appalachian fields. Steel production reached 10,000,000 tons by 1900, outstripping the British output, yet farm products still greatly exceeded those of industry.

But over-production of goods and raw materials, over-capitalization of railroads and feverish speculation in securities brought financial panics in 1873 and 1893. After the latter, particularly, there were labor strikes with terrible violence. Trusts were formed, including the railroads and there were some very questionable business practices. The Interstate Commerce Act of 1887 was the federal government's first attempt to regulate the railroads and break up the trusts. The first ready-made plates for use in photography were developed in the 1880s and Henry Ford made his first twin-cylinder, water-cooled, 25 mile an hour car in 1896, although mass production did not materialize until after the turn of the century. (Ref. 84)

In spite of the financial panic of 1873, factories tripled their output between 1877 and 1892 so that the United States became the leading industrial power of the world. The panic of 1893 occurred when the Democratic Party was in power, and it subsequently became stigmatized as the party of depression. Born as the son of a poor weaver in Scot- land, Andrew Carnegie went from oil to building to buying up iron and steel mills and then to railroads and steamship lines. His monopoly of steel helped him to weather the 1892-3 depression and 9 years later he sold his steel interests out to the United States Steel Corporation for $250,000,000, after which he started his career of fabulous philanthropy. (Ref. 85, 86)

A major step in medicine occurred with the establishment in 1893 of the Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, with a remarkable faculty, which included the pathologist William H. Welch who was among the first to introduce microscopy and bacteriology into the country, the great clinician William Osler and surgeon William S. Halsted. Within a few years Hopkins' former students and professors carried the Hopkins' system to all parts of the United States. (Ref. 87)

On the political scene, RUTHERFORD B. HAYES was announced president in a disputed election by action of the National Electoral Commission by a strict party vote. Hayes refused to run again in 1880 and a "dark horse" GENERAL JAMES A. GARFIELD ran away with the nomination and finally the election. On his death by assassination 4 months later, his vice-president, CHESTER ARTHUR assumed office. Reform in the civil service commission regulation was made by law in 1883. Overall, some believe Arthur's was the best Republican administration between Lincoln and Theodore Roosevelt, but in the 1884 election, the Democrat GROVER CLEVELAND won the office. But Cleveland made many enemies, being rude to the press, offending Union veterans, vetoing hundreds of pension bills and trying to stop the "free coinage" of silver under the Bland-Allison Act. Cleveland lost the next election (1888) to the Republican BENJAMIN HARRISON, who made a dignified but ineffective president and his Congress wanted no legislation other than raids on the treasury and hold-ups of the consumer. As a result, Cleveland was returned for a second term in the elections of 1892. There followed the worst industrial depression since the 1870s. It was a period of soup kitchens, ragged armies of unemployed and desperate strikes. The party in power is always blamed for all hard times, so in 1894 the Republicans won again, with WILLIAM McKINLEY defeating the "boy orator of the Platte", William Jennings Bryan.

THE SPANISH-AMERICAN WAR

In 1897 Cuba was in revolt against Spain's inept rule and American journalists, such as William Randolph Hearst and Joseph Pulitzer, in a race for circulation, played up some atrocities and Cuban concentration camps in the American press. Soon there was a cry to "do something" about Cuba. Just as a new Spanish premiere did promise Cuba a measure of home rule and reform, however, the U.S.S. Maine battleship was mysteriously blown up in Havana harbor, with heavy loss of life. The clamor for war with Spain then became more than the weak President McKinley could stand and in place of accepting a peacef ul solution already offered by Spain, which even included ceding Cuba to the U.S., McKinley allowed Congress to declare war in April of 1898. The American fleets immediately went to work, with one Atlantic squadron blockading Havana and another protecting the U.S. coast. Commodore Dewey took the Pacific fleet into Manila Bay in the Philippines and without losing a single man reduced the Spanish fleet there to junk. The obsolete Spanish vessels there were no match for the newer American ships. Even so, the United States Naval bombardments in both Manila and the later Santiago Bay of Cuba, proved embarrassingly inaccurate, leading to a world-wide effort to improve long-range gunnery. (Ref. 88) After 10 weeks of fighting the U.S. had wrested an American empire from Spain. The ground war to "save Cuba" was a popular one, but sad because of lack of preparedness of the continental forces. For every one of the 289 men killed in battle, 13 men died of disease. If the Spanish forces had been in any way organized and reasonably led, the ragged U.S. forces could never have invaded the island, but they did. Then when the Spanish navy sailed out of Santiago Bay to be destroyed by the guns of Admiral Sampson's Atlantic squadron in July of 1898 the war was over. At the formal Treaty of Paris in the fall of that year, both Cuba and Porto Rico, as well as the Philippines, became U.S. possessions. For the latter, this country did give Spain $2,000,000.

THE INDIAN PROBLEM IN THE LAST HALF OF THE CENTURY

By way of recapitulation we should mention that many Indian problems began after the United States acquired Florida through the treaty ratified in 1821. Then Monroe's bowing to the demands of land craving "westerners" and Jackson's follow-up policies resulted in the attempt to remove all Indians to regions west of the Mississippi. This began in the old "Northwest" and the lower South. We have seen that the Seminoles of Florida refused to move and under the leadership of Osceola, retreated to the fastness of the everglades, where they remain in some 200,000 acres of swampland today. The only "western" statesman to denounce these shabby activities was Henry Clay. From 1853 to 1856 there were 52 treaties signed, mostly with Indian nations west of the Mississippi, resulting in the addition of 174,000,000 acres to the national domain. There were 200,000 Indians between the Mississippi and the Rocky Mountains at the beginning of the century.

The Indian story of the second half of the century, however, is that of the Great Plains tribes and their attempts to prevent white settlements. The Sioux, Blackfoot, Crow, Cheyenne, Arapaho, Nez Perce12, Comanche, Apache, Ute and Kiowa were all well armed and had swift horses. The universal Indian sign language only became manifest at that time on the Great Plains, when tribes speaking different languages had to communicate and collaborate, although it had actually originated at an earlier date among the Westos, Shawnees and other Southern Indians. (Ref. 89) The wanton destruction of the buffalo, the Colt six-shooter and the white man's diseases were all fatal to the plains Indians. United, these Indians might have been invincible, but they were themselves divided and were defeated piecemeal, although at times the Indians seemed to be winning. When 60,000 Texans went to the Confederate army, it left scarcely 27,000 men behind to defend the entire state and the Comanches and Kiowas, among others, turned central Texas into a disaster area. This occurred even after prospectors in the 1849 gold rush had brought cholera to those tribes as they poured through their territories. Some of the tribes lost 50% of their people. The Comanches, who had gone south from Wyoming about 1700, were excellent horsemen, led by Quanah Parker in the late 1860s. Parker was never actually defeated in battle, but in 1875 he gave up his wars and accepted reservation life, leading the last of his Kwahadie clan and their 1,500 horses to Fort Sill, Oklahoma. He later became a business man, leasing land to Burk Burnett, Dan Waggoner and others in north Texas. But he also proselytized the peyote cult, which became known as the focus of the native American church. (Ref. 90)

The various tribes occupied and roamed over large territories at times and it will be easier to discuss them by tribes, rather than narrowly by regions. The Shoshones of Wyoming territory were linguistically and culturally related to the Utes and Paiutes and were actually great warriors against their Indian enemies (Sioux, Crows, Blackfoot, Cheyenne and Arapahos), but they made friends with the whites of the Lewis and Clark Expedition and later helped the Mormons to make safe passage. Fort Washakie was named after the great Shoshone chief. The Blackfoot occupied part of Wyoming and Montana territory, while the Nes Percel were primarily in Idaho. The Utes, some of whom were also friendly to whites, were primarily in Colorado, where there were no U.S. forts.

The Cheyenne and Sioux were more widely distributed, with the later especially spread from the Dakota territory through Montana, Wyoming and Nebraska. The U.S. had many forts in those areas, including Forts Buford, Abraham Lincoln, Yates, Meade and Randall in the Dakota Territory, Fort Kearney in Nebraska and Fort Ellis in Montana. Chief Sitting Bull was a Hunkpapa Sioux band warrior and Crazy Horse was an Oglala Sioux. In the 1 ,860s Washington gave the Hunkpapas a large reservation (along with some Cheyenne and Arapaho clans) encompassing the entire western 1/2 of South Dakota and the Powder River country to west of the Big Horn Mountains to be unceded Indian Territory, off limits to all white people. This was the Treaty of Laramie. But the Northern Pacific Railroad went through then and Lt. Col. George Armstrong Custer was sent with reconnaissance guards. He reported that there was gold in the Black Hills, sacred to the Sioux. By 1875 there were over 1,000 prospectors there and Washington took away the unceded land. But Chief Sitting Bull ignored orders to go to a reservation. Consequently in 1876 three columns of army were sent out to "get" Sitting Bull. He did-a "scarlet blanket" ceremony to his god, which involved SO cuts of skin off each arm and then 24 hours of dancing. The now General Custer led one of the three forces of the U.S. and came across the trail of the Indians as they were moving. Recklessly and against orders, he attacked them. In the battle Custer was killed and the core of the 7th Cavalry was destroyed. Later the Sioux were defeated by Colonel Nelson Miles and Sitting Bull was taken prisoner. Still later, of course, he was famous with Bill Cody's Wild West Show, only to be killed in 1896 by Indian policemen, who had come to arrest him as a high priest of a ghost dance movement. After the capture of Sitting Bull, the Sioux Chief Big Foot, with 300 followers, escaped to the Badlands of South Dakota. They, too, were captured and taken to Wounded Knee Creek. When the soldiers were attempting to disarm the Indians gun fire broke out, the Indians were massacred and the bodies left on the ground to freeze. This is yet today a source of much Indian grievance and discontent. (Ref. 92)

In the meantime, by 1870 a new tanning process developed in 1870, made buffalo hides commercially workable and therefore buffalo hunting a year around business. At the same time there appeared the high powered Sharps' rifle that could kill a full grown buffalo at 500 yards. A top marksman might kill 200 a day in the Texas panhandle. This marked the end of the buffalo and of the remaining Indians. Buffalo slaughter at more than a million a year meant that by 1886 only about 1,000 remained on the plains. (Ref. 93)

Next we must turn our attention to the great southwest, where in the middle of the century some 7,000 Apaches lived in Arizona, New and Old Mexico. There were several bands - the White Mountain group, the Aravaipa Apache, the Mimbres and the Chiricahuas being the most numerous. The latter group was perhaps the most formidable and was led by Chief Cochise. In Mexico in 1837 and after, the states of Chihuahua and Sonora paid bounty of 100 pesos for a male Apache scalp, 50 for a woman's and 25 for a child. The Apache bows were lethal at 100 yards and they used slings which could hurl stones 150 yards, as well as war clubs and lances. Trained as long distance runners, they could cover 70 miles a day on foot in tough terrain. Chief Geronimo was made most vicious by a massacre of many of his people by the Mexican General Carrasco at Janos, Mexico. By the 1870s there were 10,000 white miners, ranchers and townsmen in Arizona and by 1880 the number had risen to 37,000, about 10 times the Indian population. In the 1880s 5,000 Apaches were forced on to the San Carlos reservation in southern Arizona where they were supposed to farm, but they didn't know how. Geronimo repeatedly escaped to Mexico and returned to raid. In 1886 General Nelson Miles took 5,000 troops to hunt him down and Geronimo finally gave himself up, after his family had been sent to Florida. In 1894 he and the remaining Chiricahuas were taken to Ft. Sill, where most of them soon died of disease. (Ref. 94)

The Zunis of the Southwest were very intractable and had repelled the Spaniards in earlier years, time and time again. Palmer (Ref. 95) says that they derived originally from two parental stocks, one from the north and one from the southwest, but their language is distinct and intelligible to no other Indian tribe. They have succeeded in preserving their myths and traditions in a "series of sacred epics, a sort of inchoate Bible"13. These facts are particularly interesting in view of Barry Fell's hypothesis discussed on page 210, concerning the possible relationship of the Zuni and their language with Libyan sailors. Information about some of the southwestern Indians has been slow in coming to light. In Rose Palmer's book, The North American Indians, (Ref. 96) written under the Smithsonian auspices as late as 1949, she does not even mention the Hohokam and Anasazi. She does mention "Basket Makers", stating that some cave-like dwellings in deep recesses of cliffs had been abandoned long before the Spaniards came. *** (Page 1202)

The Ute, Comanche, Hopi and Pima Shoshonean languages are related to the Nahautl group of languages of Mexico, which includes Aztec. Some of these Shoshonean Athapascan groups had early been isolated by mountains and deserts. The Mohave, who tattooed their bodies and wore practically no clothes, along with the Yuma, formed a connecting link with the southwest tribes. They had rafts and planked canoes sealed with asphalt.

In the far west, the Yuroks and Hupa (also Hoopa) of northern California, like the northwest coastal Indians, were highly civilized, using bows and arrows, body armor of thick elk hide and dugout canoes with 6 to 8- paddles that could even be used in the ocean. They ate salmon, mussels, seaweed (for salt), whale meat and acorns. The latter were dried, pounded into meal, treated with hot water to remove the tannic acid and then cooked in closely woven baskets, with stirring, until a tasteless gruel resulted. They grew and smoked tobacco. Although those two California tribes spoke- entirely different languages, they were friendly and cooperative with each other. The Hupa, living along the Trinity River, did not even know of white men until the gold rush days of 1850. (Ref. 98)

MEXICO, CENTRAL AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN

The Mexican Revolution actually began in 1810 when Miguel Hidalgo, a priest, called on his Indian followers to rise against their local rulers. Spanish rule had already deteriorated as Napoleon had subdued Spain. But Mexico City was even then a rich capital, with caravans of mules with noisy bells, carrying merchandise and maize flour daily to the city. (Ref. 99) Various governors appeared and disappeared in Mexico in that time of struggle between classes and among ambitious, selfish, military men. The Mexicans copied the United States constitution in 1824 almost exactly, but they could not make it function properly because of constant collisions of state and national sovereignties, with the result that by the 1830s they had alternated between anarchy and military despotism. (Ref. 100) War with Texas in 1835 and with the United States in 1845-48 resulted in the loss of much land. (See pages 1157 and 1158). Mexico had 30 presidents in its first 50 years. (Ref. 101) Benito Juarez, a Zapotec Indian, finally came into power and tried to improve his country's economic situation and lessen the political power of the Church, but that era was interrupted by Napoleon III's placing the Austrian Maximilian as Emperor of Mexico, supported by French troops, in opposition to Juarez. By 1867, however, Juarez had run the French out and subordinated church and state to a secular administration. As the French deserted, Maximilian was captured and shot. The last third of the century saw Porfirio Diaz as dictator of Mexico, when the liberals had been unable to give Mexico prosperity. Diaz allowed spectacular economic progress, but with foreign capital and leaving the populace poorer than ever. (Ref. 102)

Elsewhere in Central America there was much confusion. For awhile there was a Confederation of Central America including Guatemala, Honduras, Nicaragua, Costa Rica, San Salvador and Quezaltango, although the first four soon declared themselves independent of the federal government. In the first half of the century the main road to Guatemala City was almost impassable even with mules. The people, even the whites, went about essentially naked, living on tortillas, corn, dark beans and cigars. Polygamy was common, even among nominal Catholics. There were many gigantic Catholic churches desolate and deteriorating in the jungle, evidence of an expiring people. When a cholera epidemic struck in 1838 the priests told the Indians that foreigners in San Salvador had caused it, leading to further political confusion. (Ref. 103) Stephens (Ref. 104) described the bull-fights in Yucatan about 1840 as "brutal".

Nicaragua was the seat of multiple incidents, involving British, U.S. and local revolutionaries and Latin America has been suspicious of U.S. activities ever since. President Polk obtained the right of transit across Panama by treaty with Colombia in 1840 and the Panama Railway was completed in 1855, with American capital. The old Mayan ruins in both Yucatan and what is now Honduras were investigated and publicized by John Stephens from the United States. Belize had 6,000 people, 4,000 of which were black, mahogany cutters, but there was complete integration of the races in that British settlement. The old Indian 40 feet long canoes with cabins still plied the rivers, but were now manned by Negroes. The previously fierce, cannibalistic Caribs of the coast were now civilized and most were Catholics, although they had not mixed with the Spanish conquerors. (Ref. 105) There were three main political parties in Central America, one lead by Morazan, former president of the Republic of San Salvador, a second by the mulatto Ferrara in Honduras and finally Carrera, an Indian of Guatemala. The latter's country, although dominated by dictators through most of the century did manage to supply the Spanish with sugar, cocoa and indigo.

Early in the century European introduced disease took a high toll throughout Mexico and Central America in general. The native population of Mexico had been seriously depleted and in some areas, such as Veracruz in particular, there was a human vacuum which was resettled by French and Italian farmers. A big step in the control of tropical disease was made in 1881 by the Cuban physician, Carlos Finlay, as he defined the Aedes aegypti mosquito as the insect vector in yellow fever. More complete details were then developed by a United States commission working in Cuba under Walter Reed, at about the turn of the century. (Ref. 106)

In the Caribbean, Cuba remained under the control of Spain, even as most of the remainder of the Spanish Empire broke away. - This is not to say that there were not uprisings. A Ten Years War was initiated by Carlos Manuel de Despedes, but it was a revolt which was finally crushed. Cuba had 55 steam engines by 1860. It was the largest exporter of sugar and the richest colony in the world. (Ref. 107) But still the people were not happy and there was much bitterness which finally resulted in- 1895 with the brilliant poet Mose Marti becoming the chief spokesman for a new and stronger revolt. We have seen in a special segment above how the United States became involved in this uprising which terminated in the Spanish American War. Jamaica continued to have intermittent revolts against the white colonials. When slavery was abolished in 1833 the sugar industry declined. Overpopulation and the economic and social situations generated tension and unrest, leading to more severe riots. About 95% of the population was Negro or part-Negro and many left the island to seek employment elsewhere in the Caribbean or the United States.

The story of Haiti is somewhat involved. At the end of the last century Spain had ceded its part of the island, Santo Domingo, to France, but in 1801 the remarkable Negro leader, Toussaint L 'Ouverture conquered it. Although an expedition sent by Napoleon in

1802 failed to retake the island, Touissant was captured by trickery and died in a French prison. But Haiti remained independent and the remaining whites were expelled. Santo Domingo was brought under Haitian control by J.P. Boyer in the 1840s, but actually anarchy persisted, with mulattos fighting against Negroes. The eastern, originally Spanish part of the island never was fully assimilated and eventually out of the turmoil there emerged the Dominican Republic. (Ref. 108)

SOUTH AMERICA

From 1815 to 1822 there was an amazing eruption of new nations in South America. In Argentina, after first having to fight off French, Portuguese and Dutch, a revolutionary movement of 1810 gave liberals an opportunity to reform the country socially and economically, but they failed. Jose de San Martin kept the revolutionary flame alive in a remote province and in 1817 led a famous march across the Andes with 3,500 men, to set up a new government in Chile. They then went on by sea to attack Lima, Peru. Back home in Argentina, in mid-century a bloody dictator, Juan Manuel de Rosas, took control, giving enormous ranches to his army veterans. Because of his great horsemanship, he him self was a respected gaucho14 Rosas was overthrown by Jose de Urequiza of the army in the Battle of Caseros in 1852 and the winner became chief executive, with a federal constitution. Immigration accounted for about 1/2 the population growth in this century. 30 % of the inhabitants lived in Buenos Aires and that city would not join the Argentine federation and there were intermittent civil wars between that city and province with the rest of Argentina through 1880, when the problems were finally solved under the presidency of Julio Roca. In the meantime, alliances had been concluded with Uruguay and Brazil and there had been a w ar with Paraguay between 1865 and 1870. During the administrations of Domingo Sarmiento (1868-74) and Nicolas Avellaneda (1874-80) education, commerce and immigration were encouraged and the census of 1869 showed over 1,700,000 people. English sheep were introduced to the country in 1840 and short-horn bulls in 1848. (Ref. 109, 110, 111)

Chile organized as a republic under the son of an Irish officer, Bernardo O'Higgins, in 1818. The principal result of the Chilean revolution was the transfer of economic and social control fro m a Spanish-led society to one dominated by conservative Creoles, as the people would not give up religious processions, cockfighting and gambling and the aristocracy kept their privileged positions and large estates. As with the other South A m erican nations, civil war occurred in 1829 and 1830 and wars with neighbors developed throughout the century. The greatest of those was the War of the Pacific with Chile fighting against Peru and Bolivia from 1879 to 1884. Chilean troops were everywhere successful and Chile gained possession of the Bolivian littoral and southern Peruvian coast, with rich nitrate territories of great economic importance. This region ran all along the Pacific coast and essentially blocked Bolivia fro m the sea. (Ref. 112) The last civil war occurred in 1891 and as the century ended war with Argentina was narrowly averted.

To go back in time to the early century, having established their own independence from Spain, Argentina and Chile went to the aid of Peru in 1821, with San Martin leading the army and Admiral Cochrane cooperating with the Chilean navy. In 1822 San Martin and Simon Bolivar met in Guayaquil at a time when only one Spanish army was left in the field. That army surrendered at Ayacucho in 1824. Simon Bolivar had dreamed of one great state of Colombia, but it was not to be and Ecuador, Colombia and Venezuela went their separate ways. Bolivia became independent under Bolivar in 1825 as a country some 21/2 times its present size. It was the rich nitrate and copper deposits along the coast that tempted Chile to seize that portion in the War of the Pacific (see paragraph above). In the 20th century other neighbors were to further chew up the borders of hapless Bolivia. Things were not a whole lot better in Colombia. In the seventy years just prior to 1903 that country had 17 civil wars, with conservatives, liberals, Catholics and separatists all involved from time to time. (Ref. 113) Originally a part of Colombia, Panama was given a federal status by Colombian constitutional amendment in 1855, although Panama did not declare its complete independence until after the turn of the century. Large oil reserves were found in Venezuela in 1870 and in the 20th century this has greatly increased that nation's importance in the world. (Ref. 114)

Portugal acted differently from Spain and met the demands of local autonomy. (Ref. 115) When Prince Regent Dom Joao, fleeing from Napoleon, landed in Rio in 1808 that city became capital of an empire including, besides Brazil itself, various Atlantic Islands, Angola and Mozambique in Africa and scattered areas in China, India and Oceania. Brazilian ports were opened; manufacture of iron and textiles undertaken; a bank, naval college, medical faculty, library and printing press were established. European artists and scientists arrived. Even so, as late as 1820 Brazil, in spite of gold and diamond mines and the Portuguese empire, was a poor, oppressed country, thinly populated and with little or no intellectual potential. (Ref. 116) Dom Joao returned to Portugal in 1821 with most of the cash from the Bank of Brazil, leaving Crown Prince Pedro to govern. On October 12, 1822 the Senate proclaimed him as constitutional Emperor of Brazil as Pedro I. Opposition to his autocratic ways and his obvious primary interest in the mother country finally forced his abdication in favor of his 5 year old son, Pedro II. Between 1840 and 1889 provincial revolts were gradually brought to a close and a period of order and progress was initiated. Commerce and industry expanded, 6,000 miles of railways were constructed by 1889, gold mines were further developed and sugar and rubber production were promoted. In 1872 the population was over 10,000,000, including 1,500,000 slaves. These were emancipated in 1888. Things changed in November of 1889 when the army, headed by General Manoel Deodoro da Fonseca, revolted and deposed the emperor and proclaimed a republic. Fonseca was elected president in 1891.

Map taken from Reference 97

After Peru was liberated from Spain by Bolivar, there was still no real political stability and civil strife continued until 1845 when Rarnon Castilla emerged as one of the strong men supported by the military. Even another small war with Spain occurred between 1863 and 1871 over some small off-shore islands. Before the war's end Jose Balta had become president and had begun some material expansion of Peru. Unfortunately Peru joined the wrong side in the War of the Pacific, mentioned above, and at the end lost the province of Tarapaca and after long haggling, the coastal portions of two more provinces.

In 1816 Jose Rodriquez de Francia made himself perpetual dictator of Paraguay as well as head of the Paraguayan Church and sealed that country off from the rest of the world until his death in 1840. He was succeeded by another dictator, Carlos Antonio Lopez, who held absolute power until 1862. His son, Francisco Solano Lopez succeeded him and attempted to increase the power of the country by vigorous means. The population had increased to over 1,000,000 and the first railway was constructed about that time. Lopez's ambitions for additional territory, however, brought about war with Brazil, Argentina and Uruguay (The War of the Triple Alliance) between 1865 and 1870 and the Paraguayan nation was virtually annihilated, with only about 28,000 men and some 200,000 women surviving. A long period of instability followed, with the economy slow in recovering.

In general we may say that the penchant for alternating dictatorships with various odd types of democracy has continued throughout Latin America even through the 20th century.

1 [234] WHEELER, KEITH, The Alaskans. (Time-Life Books, Alexandria, Va. 1977).

2 [199] STARR, S. FREDERICK, "Why did Russia let Seward's folly go on the cheap?" Smithsonian, Dec. 1979, page 129.

3 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

4 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

5 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

6 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

7 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

8 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

9 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

10 [212] TANNER, OGDEN, The Canadians. (Time-Life Books Inc., Alexandria, Va. 1977).

11 [32] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, Ibid., Volume IV - The Great Democracies.

12 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

13 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

14 [293] EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

15 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

16 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

17 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

18 [123]  LIBRARY OF CONGRESS, "Documents Illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States, Government Printing Office, Washington D.C. 1927.

19 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

20 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

21 [293] EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

22 [293] EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

23 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

24 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

25 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

26 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

27 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

28 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

29 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

30 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

31 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

32 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

33 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

34 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

35 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

36 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

37 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

38 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

39 [64] FARB, PETER, Man's Rise to Civilization. (E.P. Dutton & Co., New York, 1968).

40 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

41 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

42 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

43 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

44 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

45 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

46 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

47 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

48 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

49 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

50 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

51 [123]  LIBRARY OF CONGRESS, "Documents Illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States, Government Printing Office, Washington D.C. 1927.

52 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

53 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

54 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

55 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

56 [293] EDMUNDS, R. DAVID, The Shawnee Prophet. (University of Nebraska Press, Lincoln and London, 1938).

57 [218] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEX15, Ibid. Volume II. (Original publication in 1840).

58 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

59 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

60 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

61 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

62 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

63 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

64 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

65 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

66 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

67 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

68 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

69 [198] (The) SPANISH WEST, by Editors of Time-life Books. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1976).

70 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

71 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

72 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

73 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

74 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

75 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

76 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

77 [62] ENGEL, FREDERIC ANDRE, An Ancient World Preserved. (Translated by Rachel Kendall Gordon). (Crown Publishers, Inc., N.Y., 1976).

78 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

79 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

80 [39] COOKE, ALESTAIR, America. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1977).

81 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

82 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

83 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

84 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

85 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

86 [151] MORRISON, SAMUEL ELLIOT, The Oxford History of the American People, Oxford Press, N.Y., 1965.

87 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

88 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

89 [267] WRIGHT, J. LEITCH, JR., The Only Land they Knew. (The Free Press, New York, 1981).

90 [294] CAPPS, BENJAMIN, The Great Chiefs. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1975).

91 [294] CAPPS, BENJAMIN, The Great Chiefs. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1975).

92 [294] CAPPS, BENJAMIN, The Great Chiefs. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1975).

93 [294] CAPPS, BENJAMIN, The Great Chiefs. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1975).

94 [294] CAPPS, BENJAMIN, The Great Chiefs. (Time-Life Books, New York, 1975).

95 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

96 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

97 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

98 [165] PALMER, ROSE A., The North American Indians. (Vol. IV Smithsonian Instruction Series, The Series Publishers, Inc., New York 1949).

99 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

100 [217] DE TOCQUEVILLE, ALEXIS, Democracy in America. Volume I, Phillips Bradley Edition, correcting original Henry Reeve Translation of 1835. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York 1980).

101 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

102 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

103 [203] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Incidents of Travel in Central America, Chiapas and Yucatan. (Dover Publ., Inc., New York, 1969 - Re-publication of original published in 1841 by Harper and Brothers).

104 [204] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Incidents of Travel in Yucatan, Volume I. (Dover Publ., Inc. New York, 1963 - unabridged re-publication of 1843 work by Harper & Bros.).

105 [203] STEPHENS, JOHN L., Incidents of Travel in Central America, Chiapas and Yucatan. (Dover Publ., Inc., New York, 1969 - Re-publication of original published in 1841 by Harper and Brothers).

106 [125]  LYONS, ALBERT S., M.D. AND PETRUCELLI, R. JOSEPH, M.D., Medicine - An Illustrated History. (Harry N. Abrams, Inc. New York 1978).

107 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

108 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

109 [119] LANGER,WM. L. (Editor), Encylopedia of World History. (Houghton Mifflin Co., Boston, 1952.

110 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

111 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

112 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

113 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

114 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

115 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

116 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

1.  Strangely enough, Papineau took no part in the actual uprisings, as he first fled to the United States for help and thwarted there, went on to France. (Ref. 7)

2.  Tsimshian culture was typical of Northwest Coast Indians and similar to that of the Haida and the Tlingit. (Ref. 8)

3.  Quotation from Edmunds (Ref. 22), page 115)

4.  When the president ordered the militia of the northern states to the frontiers, Connecticut and Massachusetts refused to obey. (Ref. 23)

5.  These remarks are taken from Wright (Ref. 28), pages 250 and 251)

6.  Quotation from Reference 151, page 500

7.  The Cherokees particularly had a highly Europeanized culture, with a written language, invented by their great leader Sequoyah, before their western travels. (Ref. 60) See also pages 1201-1202

8.  The Hidalgo Treaty described some of the U.S.-Mexico border vaguely, and in 1853 President Franklin Pierce had James Gadsden purchase an extra 30,000 square miles along southern New Mexico and Arizona south of the Gila River, for $10,000,000. That area was considered the most practical route for a southern railroad to the Pacific. This was the "Gadsden Purchase". (Ref. 63)

9.  The Cayuse bred a small horse and gave the name cayuse to all Indian ponies. (Ref. 64)

10.  Fortunately the Senate, organized as a court under the Chief Justice, failed to convict Johnson and he remained in office

11.  This plow had a revolving blade, which turned the very hard soil

12.  The French-Canadians named these Indians Nez Perce because they pierced their noses for wearing shell ornaments. (Ref. 91)

13.  Quotation from Frank H. Cushing, who lived with the Zuni from 1879 to 1883, as given by Palmer (Ref. 97), page 128

14.  The gauchos were a mixture of Spanish Creoles and Indians

Central and Northern Asia: Beginning to 8000 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

It is of interest that some geologists have written that during much of the Triassic and Jurassic periods some 200 million years ago, southern Tibet was largely submerged below the tropical sea of Tethys - water separating the continents of Eurasia and Gondwanaland. During the Cretaceous period 65 million years ago, the Indian subcontinent separated, moved across the Tethys and collided with Eurasia with a terrific impact which formed the Himalayan range and the Tibetan plateau. The collision zone folded the earth's crusts to almost a right angle. Then only a few million years ago further uplift of the Himalayans occurred, incident to glaciation and other factors, and these mountains are still rising at the rate of 1/2 centimeter a year. (Ref. 1, 2)

Skeletal remains have been found of the cave dwelling Neanderthal hunters all about the area from the Caspian to the Aral seas. As the last Ice Age retreated, Siberian reindeer hunters progressively worked northward. Men of truly modern type were pressing into this far north land some 35,000 years ago, where they hunted mammoths within a hundred miles of the Arctic Circle, along the Pechora River. An early wave of men spread from the Ural Mountains across central Asia to southern Siberia and Mongolia and their relics have come to be known as the Mal'ta - Afontova Culture. A second wave penetrated eastern Siberia along the Aldan River and Soviet excavations there have shown these people of the Diuktai Culture to have hunted mammoths, muskoxen, bison and giant woolly rhinoceroses about 35,000 years ago. These people may have been some of the first adventurers across the land bridge into Alaska. Certain Siberian tribes existing today (Nganasans, Eutsis, Dogan Chukchi, etc.) have a complex time-factored mythology and ceremonials, including lunar calendar notations, bear and reindeer ceremonies, etc. that are related to Upper Paleolithic cultures of 15,000 to 35,000 years ago.

Around Lake Baikal and the upper Yenissei River well preserved artifacts dating to 20,000 years ago have been excavated. These include huts and small art objects, such as carved geese figurines and tiny female statuettes. From the latter it is apparent that these Mongoloid people wore skin suits, parka hoods and moccasins sewed on trousers. The bow and arrow may have been invented in central Asia by 13,000 B.C. About 11,000 B.C. the Asiatic wolf probably was under human control, but only by getting animals under six weeks of age. This was not true dog domestication. (Ref. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7)

Dr. Ales Hrdlicka has found on the southern slopes of the Himalayas among the Tibetan tribes a yellow-brown stock which "in physique, in behavior, in dress, and even in intonations of language"(1) [link] appear identical with American Indians. Could this be their original homeland?

1 [182] RIPLEY, S. DILLON, "Tibet: the high & fragile land behind the ranges", Smithsonian Jan. 1981, pp. 97-105.

2 [100] HSU, KENNETH J., "When the Black Sea was Drained," Scientific American, 238: 53-63, May, 1978.

3 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

4 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

5 [226] WAECHTER, JOHN, Prehistoric Man. (Octopus Books Limited, London and Mandarin Publishers Limited, Hong Kong, 1977).

6 [182] RIPLEY, S. DILLON, "Tibet: the high & fragile land behind the ranges", Smithsonian Jan. 1981, pp. 97-105.

7 [130] MARSHACK, ALEXANDER, The Roots of Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1972).

Central and Northern Asia: 3000 to 1500 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

Throughout the fifteen hundred years covered in this chapter, the Iranian (Indo-European) tribes slowly expanded in all directions, including various salients across southern Asia both east and north. By 2,500 B.C. the hunting economies had begun to give way to herding and agriculture in Kazakhistan and central Siberia. Horse drawn carts were in use in Turkistan by the same date. The pottery of all these people showed affinities to the Middle East. It was the domestication of the horse which allowed them to spread and penetrate in all directions.

In the far northeast of Asia, the Mongol peoples continued their own development, probably more closely related to the Chinese culture than to the Indo-European development. In the area which now comprises the western Chinese provinces of Kansu and Sinkiang, but which geographically are more a part of central Asia, the Pan-Chan phase of the Yang-shao Culture appeared about 2,500 B.C. with large urns painted in spirals with purple, brown, red and black. By 1,500 B.C. this gave way to the Hsien-tien Culture which included farming and the use of hand-made pottery and copper tools. Farther northwest, in the Yenisei Valley, the Afanasieve Culture with stock breeders and hunters, stamped pottery, and copper ornaments have been dated to this 3rd millennium. By 1,500 B.C. the Androvonovo Culture existed between the Don and the Yenisei rivers, with small settlements of up to ten semi-subterranean houses. These individuals, who were the ancestors of the later nomads of the central Asiatic steppes, grew wheat and millet and bred live-stock at that time. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4).

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

4 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

Central and Northern Asia: 1500 to 1000 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

Iranian (Indo-European) tribes occupied all of the area of south central Asia from the Aral Sea to the Tarim Basin, and gradually extended their territories on east toward China and southeast into the Indian peninsula. At about 1,000 B.C. Iranians of Transoxia found that a rider could manage his horse on a battlefield, initiating a weapon that ultimately outmoded the chariot. It is assumed that the Mongolian and the Hunnish-Turkish peoples were multiplying in the farther north and northeastern reaches of Asia, but little actual information is available. In the 13th century B.C. in south Siberia, the Karasuk Culture developed from the Androvonova, and there was a change from settled communities to seasonal nomadism. Small curved knives similar to those at An-Yang in China have been found. (Ref. 1, 2)

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

Central and Northern Asia: 1000 to 700 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

South central Asia was now occupied by various migrating Indo-European tribes, some moving gradually south between the Aral and Caspian seas and others moving west toward the southern Russian steppe. Ordos, the region of Mongolia lying inside the loop of the Yellow River where it turns north, was inhabited by nomadic tribes, including the Hsiung-nu, an Altaic-speaking Mongoloid people.1 Broad daggers, curved knives, harness ornaments and belt plaques with animal profiles have been among the remnants found. Rock carvings in Tibet along the upper Indus River valley in Ladakh on the Tibetian-Kashmir border dating 2,000 to 3,000 years ago indicate Stone Age hunters with bows and arrows. Due to a gradual continued rise of the Himalayan arc and the resulting lessening of the effective rainfall through the centuries much of this area is now desert. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

3 [182] RIPLEY, S. DILLON, "Tibet: the high & fragile land behind the ranges", Smithsonian Jan. 1981, pp. 97-105.

1.  Some authorities deny that the Hsiung-nu can be identified as a separate people on the borders of China until the 2nd century B.C.  See references 45 and 127 and this manuscript under 4th century B.C., CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA.

Central and Northern Asia: 700 to 601 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

The Hsiung-nu of the Mongolian region had horses of various breeds, among them one with an upright mane. They, like the Huns of probable later descent, were expert horsemen. East of Mongolia excavations have revealed the Tagar Culture, dating back to 700 B.C. and continuing for about 600 years. This included a semi-settled people who designed animals on small knives, belt and harness plaques and broad daggers. The latter have also been found in South Russia and on the northern borders of China.

The Iranians of Tranoxiana were a mixed group of tribes. Some, who moved on into southern Russia were known as Scythians while their kinsmen who remained behind became known as Sakas. The Medes had pretty well left this area to settle in Iran south of the Caspian, but behind them came their cousins, the Persians. Zoraster was born along the Oxus River in this century and did much of his teaching in Khurasan. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

4 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

Central and Northern Asia: 500 to 401 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

There were people in the Altai Mountains of southern Siberia and an advanced people lived near Minusinsk, some 800 miles northeast of Lake Balkash and some 200 miles north of the northwestern corner of Mongolia in the Ordos region of Siberia. The Rockefeller Collection contains a bronze reindeer mounted on a marble base representing a known Tagar Period of art from that location. As mentioned in previous chapters this same Tagar Culture has been found in more southern areas of Asia, also. The Persian Empire extended well up into central Asia from the Aral Sea to the edge of the Tarim Basin and north of this the unconquered Sakas roamed at will. Just north of the Aral Sea, at Issik near Alma Alta, one thousand gold objects dating to this 5th century B.C. have been excavated, indicating that this had been an important trade route. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

1 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

2 [183] ROCKEFELLER (NELSON) COLLECTION. (The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc., New York, 1978).

3 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

Central and Northern Asia: 400 to 301 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

At Pasyryk in the Altai Mountains of southern Siberia eight burials, dated from the 4th to the 2nd centuries B.C., have been excavated. These contained wooden chariots, textiles and furniture as well as men with skin tattoos, all well preseved by the perpetual frost. The Tagar Culture continued throughout much of the rest of Siberia. South central Asia was overrun by Alexander as he went from Afghanistan through the Hindu Kush to Bukhara and Tashkent. At the very end of the century, however, the Mauryan Dynasty of India took over a large part of Afghanistan.

As we shall see in the section on CHINA, below, the non-Chinese people of Mongolia and the adjacent part of Siberia had now about completed their slow transition into full horse nomadism and they began to attack the Chinese perimeter, as well as even taking to the sea toward Japan. Skulls from the Lake Baikal region of northern Mongolia, dated to this era, are low faced skulls of the pre-Hsuing-nu population, and were different from the later high-faced skulls of the true Hsuing-nu. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

1 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

4 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

Central and Northern Asia: 300 to 201 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

The homeland of the Parthians was on the eastern shore of the Caspian Sea and about 247 B.C. they moved south, taking territory away from the Seleucids, under their leader, Arsaces. Bactria became independent at 250 B.C. as a Greco-Bactrian kingdom under Diodotus, and it became the center of a web of caravan routes linking Siberia and China with India, Persia and the Mediterranean cities. (Ref. 1) Farther north in Siberia, Tagar Culture groups continued as in recent centuries. In Inner Mongolia, the Hsiung-nu was just forming as the first great confederation of Altaic-speaking nomads. (Ref. 2) Afghanistan was ruled by the Maurya Dynasty of India, until this entire area was reclaimed by the Syrian Antiochus III at the end of the century.

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

Central and Northern Asia: 200 to 101 B.C.

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

Bactria, astride the Hindu Kush and making up the northern part of present day Afghanistan, was ruled by Greek kings as remnants of Alexander's empire, and the country allowed Indian, Chinese, Iranian and Greek cultures to meet and intertwine. For the next two or three hundred years this was the hub of the east-west Ecumene, even though the Yue-chi destroyed the political unity of the Kingdom of Bactria. (Ref. 1) This take-over was part of a new turmoil which arose in central Asia about 130 B.C. as Huns from far eastern central Asia (perhaps Mongolia) started to push the Yue-chi (Tocharians) westward and they in turn chased a few remaining Scythians beyond the Jaxartes River1. The Scythians, in turn, headed southward and destroyed the Greco-Bactrian kingdom just mentioned, on their way to the Punjab of India, with the Yue-chi following later in about 100 B.C. via northern Afghanistan.

The Huns just mentioned were chiefly the Hsuing-nu, under Chief Modok, and they soon dominated not only Mongolia but the Indo-European oasis statelets of Chinese Turkestan as well. Armor called "chia" was worn at least by the nobles in the Hsuing-nu army.

The word may mean "hide armor" but in graves at Noin Ula, Mongolia and Tuva, Siberia armor made of iron scales attached to fabric has been found dating to this century. Bronze, iron and leather were probably all used. After the conquest of Tuva, the Hsuing-nu population, which was already racially mixed, became even more Europoid2. (Ref. 3)

The Chinese ruler, Wu-Ti, spent the resources and energies of China for eighteen years in great campaigns against the Hsuing-nu and they were finally driven out of Inner Mongolia, Kansu and Chinese Turkestan. Ferghana, west of the Tarim Basin was the homeland of "heavenly horses" which the Chinese felt they had to have in their cavalry to counteract the agile ponies of the Hsuing-nu and other raiding - nomads. At the end of the century Wu-Ti sent armies to subdue the nomads of Sinkiang and go through this area to get the horses. A Chinese explorer had reached this Ferghana Valley in 128 B.C. and a military garrison had been established by 101 B.C. The western edge of the arid Tarim Basin was the source of jade for the Chinese carvers. Farther west, the Parthians had extended their empire south and east to take in part of Khurasan and the edge of the Hindu Kush. The Bactrian camel, in this and adjacent centuries, served all the barbarians from the Great Wall of China to the Crimea as pack and riding animals. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7)

1 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

2 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

3 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

4 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

1.  This classical view of one people "chasing" or "driving" another ahead of them is not accepted by the scholarly Maenchen-Helfen (Ref. 2) who believes the migrations took place for other reasons

2.  "Europoid" is a term used by Soviet anthropologists to indicate "non-Mongoloid"

Central and Northern Asia: 100 B.C. to 0

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

In the north China, under Emperor Wu-ti, again took the offensive against the Hsiung-nu and rebuilt the old Ch'in wall, then opened up the route to central Asia, extending control over the oasis states of the Tarim Basin. In 44 B.C. Wu-ti defeated the Hsiung-nu along the border and pushed them west where they fled to the Lake Bakal region already occupied by the Yue-chi. The latter were then pushed west and south to take over Bactria and confront the Parthian Empire of Persia. The last defeat of the Huns (Hsiung-nu) by the Chinese military forces came in 36 B.C. when an expeditionary force completely broke up the Asiatic's power. (Ref. 1, 2)

At the beginning of the century two Greek principalities remained just south of the central Asian Massive and south of them, extending into present day Pakistan were the Iranian Sakas in the east and the related Iranian Suren Kingdom to the west. About the middle of the century the latter invaded the Indus Valley, breaking the power of the Sakas and deposing the last of the Indo-Greek princes. At about the same time the Huns also recovered and began to more south again against the Greater Yue-chi (Kushans), then occupying the entire region between the Oxus and the Jaxartes rivers, and soon extending through their Suren cousins, their control down the Indus in present day Pakistan. In this era Tibet was closer to India, culturally, than to China or other Asian centers. (Ref. 3, 4)

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

Central and Northern Asia: 0 to A.D. 100

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

The Silk Road trade reached its peak in this century, sustaining a string of states extending along the caravan roads from Roman Syria to the northwest border of China. In Bactria, a union of five Yue-chi tribes took the Kabut Valley, driving out the Pahlavas and soon establishing an empire which comprised all of Afghanistan as well as northwestern India. The Kushans were apparently one clan of the Yue-chi which included or was synonymous with the Tocharians, but they were dominant in this expansionist drive and the entire empire soon bore their name only. These Kushans even sent an embassy across the Caspian Sea and into Armenia to meet with the Romans in A.D. 58. The empire was a melting pot, with Indian, Chinese, central Asian and Helleno-Roman culture and their coins showed a wide range of deities, some Hellenistic (Heliols, Hephaistos), Iranian (Mithra, Nana) and Indian (Siva, Buddha). (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

The Kushans pushed their administration on into India subjugating the Surens and Sakas. They then reversed their armies and turned northward toward China, but were defeated by the great Chinese General Pan Ch'ao who was on a campaign to control Sinkiang (Tarim Basin) in A.D. 90. Pan Ch'ao then led his army across the Pamir Mountains to reach the Caspian Sea.

In the meantime, the Tibetians had attacked northwest China without much success. In the far north, the northern Hsuing-nu (Huns) were defeated by the southern Hsuing-nu in A.D. 85 and then were further beaten by the Mongol Sien-pi in 87 and by the Chinese General Tou Hsien in 89. It is no wonder that although part of them submitted to overlords, a great part of the survivors migrated westward, leaving their lands to the Mongols. This westward migration of the Huns was furthered by famine and anthrax among their cattle and horses. Along the steppe adjacent to China they were joined by Iranian herdsmen, Mongols from the forests of Siberia and even Chinese renegades and captive Europoids of various tribes, all of them subsequently called "Huns" as they gradually headed toward Europe. A great part of the Hsuing-nu confederacy, however, consisted of Mongoloids of the Baikal type, but this does not mean that all Mongoloids of this type were Hsuing-nu. (Ref. 4) The fiery, black-browed horsemen of the steppe, normally well nourished on animal protein foods, could easily overcome their more slated, carbohydrate fed Chinese neighbors, except when strong dynasties were in power such as the Han, in control at that time. (Ref. 5)

1 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

4 [127] MAENCHEN-HELFEN, OTTO J., The World of the Huns. (Edited by Max Knight and background by Paul Alexander), University of California Press, Berkeley 1973).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 101 to 200

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

In far eastern and northern Asia Mongolian nomads, perhaps with some admixture of Turkish, Europoid elements, all of which are traditionally considered as ancestors of the Huns, lived as harsh, bow-legged men with large heads and massive chests which apparently helped them to withstand the blazing days and freezing nights of the Gobi desert. Their chief meat was mutton, but occasionally they ate beef, horse or camel and the humps of the latter were considered a great delicacy. In general, in the wilder areas the cattle did not adapt well and camels were not sufficiently productive, having only a single foal every three years. The yak was used for milk, rather than fundamentally for meat. (Ref. 1)

As pack animals the horse and Bactrian camel were the means of opening the great commercial routes across the central Asian steppe, with many change-over points along the way. Stone Tower, somewhere north of the Pamirs, was the great meeting place where exquisite Chinese silks and exotic spices were bartered for Roman glassware, pottery, asbestos cloth, coral beads, gems, grape wine for the emperor of China, silver and gold.

The drain of gold from the West was fantastic in amount. In the desert at the north of the Tarim Basin at present day Turpan (or Turfan) about 950 underground canals called "Karez" were constructed to bring irrigation water from the Tian Shan (Celestial Mountains) to the desert, where a melon and grape growing oasis was thus developed. The Han Chinese ruled Turpan at this time, but through the centuries it was controlled by numerous Central Asian peoples. The "blue-print" for such an underground water system was brought along the silk route from Persia, where the canals were called "Qanats". (Ref. 2, 3)

As noted in the last chapter, the Tocharians and other Yue-chi tribes had combined to create the vast Kushan Empire which in this century covered almost the entire central Asian land mass in its southern portion. Their greatest king, Kanishka, ruled this empire from India, and more details will be written in that section of this chapter. On the Turkistan frontier with China, Mongol Hsiung-nu, Tibetans and other tribesmen lived side by side with the Chinese, who still ruled at least the most eastern portion of this area, although their protectorate over the Tarim Basin had lapsed in A.D. 106. (Ref. 4)

1 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

2 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

3 [73] GORE, RICK, "Journey to China's Far West", National Geographic 157: 292, March 1980.

4 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 201 to 300

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

In the regions of Afghanistan and western Turkestan the Kushan Empire split into several principalities and the Persian Sassanids appear to have rapidly established some dominance over the nearest of these, but their claim to have made the Oxus and the Indus their frontiers seems over-stated. The Kushan states certainly continued to exist as political entities until the 5th century. With the fall of the Han Dynasty in A.D. 220, China lost control of eastern Turkestan, and the Kushans, with some Persian influence, once again gained control. Still farther north the Hunnish tribes were flourishing.

By the opening of this century all parts of the 2,500 mile trade route from Syria to the Tarim Basin were under pressure by barbarians and a great deal of the trade had already shifted to sea lanes in the Indian Ocean. Along the silk route, however, art flourished from this century for the next 700 years as a remarkable combination of stylistic elements drawn from India, Persia and China. Stone was scarce, but decorated wood pieces and tempera painting on wood was common. (Ref. 1, 2, 3)

1 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 301 to 400

CENTRAL ASIA

In this century the Persians continued to rule and populate both Afghanistan and Turkistan, introducing Zorastrianism to the area. In 371 the Ephthalites (White Huns1) invaded the upper Oxus (ancient Bactria) but the Persian Shapur II came to an understanding with them and subsequently these people actually guarded this part of the Persian domain.

It was apparently a sharpening of the climate in this part of the world which forced the nomadic tribes to other pastures toward the end of this 4th century. Rather than go east against strong China, even after the fall of the Han Dynasty, many of the Huns turned west, riding bony, rough haired, small headed horses with short, strong legs, needing little water and covering over 60 miles a day. (See footnote on previous page). As we have seen in the paragraphs above, other peoples were ahead of them, in the greatest mass migrations known, before or since. (Ref. 1)

Up through this century Tibet was divided into 13 principalities with war continually raging between them. (Ref. 2)

1 [33] CLARK, KENNETH, Civilization. (Harper & Row, New York & Evanston, 1969).

2 [272] TONG, ENZHENG; LENG, JIAN AND WANGDUI, SUOLANG, "Unraveling Tibetan Prehistory at Karuo", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 62, Sept./Oct. 1982.

1.  See footnote under IRAN, 5th century C.E.

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 501 to 600

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

In eastern Asia the successors of the Hsiung-nu were the Kok Turuk, also called the Blue or Celestial Turks and these were the people who by 550 were driving the Juan-Juan out of Mongolia. (See also CHINA, this chapter). Their successors in Mongolia were the Turks, proper, called T'u-Chu~eh by the Chinese. This Turkish Empire was an exceptional one which could bear on western China and the Europe-Near East areas all at the same time. It now advanced rapidly and crushed the Ephthalites in 553, allowing the Persians to again occupy the lands south of the Oxus. The amalgamated remnants of the Juan-Juan and the Ephthalites were known in the West as the Avars. Previous to this the latter of the two peoples had lived in Bactria and had continuously raided Persia. In this century the Avars had already reached the Balkans and Hungary. Some place in this mass of migrating, nomadic peoples the stirrup was developed and this made it possible for horsemen to ride fast and meet a shock, as with a lance, and still survive. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

3 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 601 to 700

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

The Great Turkish Confederation controlled most of central Asia and particularly Turkistan, at the beginning of the century. Chinese diplomacy started to break up this Turkish control by 630 and then the Chinese military reconquered the Tarim Basin in 648 and West Turkistan in 656 at the peak of their expansion into Central Asia. The break-up of the Turkish Confederation thus allowed the Moslems to take the Oxus region just after the middle of the century with very little resistance.

The Chinese of the T'ang Dynasty were supported by the Turkic speaking Uigurs (also Uighurs), who were called "Yee-che" by the Chinese. Actually the Turks of Mongolia had made the Chinese T'ang ruler, T'ai-tsung, their Grand Khan in 630' Near the oasis of Dunhuang, just west of the Great Wall of China and now a part of China, and northeast of the Tarim Basin, lie the caves of the Thousand Buddhas, constructed chiefly during the T'ang Dynasty (A.D. 618-906). In subsequent centuries pilgrims from all over central Asia traveled to visit this labyrinth of sculptures and frescoes painted by Buddhist monks.

(Ref. 1, 2, 3)

Tibet was unified early in the century when rival fiefdoms began to be consolidated by King Sontsan Ganbo (or Ganbu), who incidentally married two foreign queens, one from the T'ang Dynasty of China and one a princess of Nepal. An embassy was sent to China in 641. Although the Tibetans became Buddhists, they maintained a war ethos and continued at intervals to fight the Chinese over a period of two centuries. Xenophobic policies prohibiting foreigners, along with the world's highest and most difficult terrain, was then sufficient to keep Tibet isolated from the rest of the world for hundreds of years. The Tibetans remained independent in essence until the 20th century, even though the Chinese have long claimed sovereignty (even back to this 7th century). Tibetans retained a separate language, culture, borders, money and religion. The holiest shrine still standing in the center of Lhasa is the Jokhang, built around A.D. 650 and serving as the Buddhist "Mecca" to the Tibetan faithful. (Ref. 4, 5, 6)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

3 [73] GORE, RICK, "Journey to China's Far West", National Geographic 157: 292, March 1980.

4 [272] TONG, ENZHENG; LENG, JIAN AND WANGDUI, SUOLANG, "Unraveling Tibetan Prehistory at Karuo", Archaeology Vol. 35, No. 5: 62, Sept./Oct. 1982.

5 [228] WARD, FRED, "In Long-Forbidden Tibet", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

6 [182] RIPLEY, S. DILLON, "Tibet: the high & fragile land behind the ranges", Smithsonian Jan. 1981, pp. 97-105.

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 701 to 800

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

In the northern portions of Central Asia, from the Aral Sea and the Syr Darya Valley east to Manchuria, the rulers were the Blue or Celestial Turks (See page 421). They appear to have driven other Turkish tribes westward, including the Ogur and also their former rulers, the Juan-Juan of Mongolia. In the most northeastern part of Mongolia the Uigurs seized control in 744, establishing a capital on the Orkhon River near the site of later Karakorum. The most far flung eastward group of Indo-European (Europoid) tribes were those who reached Chinese Turkistan and were called Tocharians. Their language was written down in this century. The western region of Central Asia, Kashgar, was overtaken by the advance of Islam and due to the energy of the local emir (governor), considerable advance was made against the Turks. The Arabs controlled all of western Turkistan and Afghanistan and the Moslem religion has persisted there until this day.

The Arabs were helped in driving the Chinese out of west Turkistan by the Karluk Turks, who attacked the Chinese from the rear. This Chinese army was finally completely defeated at the Talas River just south and west of Lake Balkhash in A.D. 751 in one of those decisive battles of history. China was not to be influential in Central Asia for six centuries and Buddhism gave way to Islam. Of some importance, too, is the fact that some of the captured Chinese soldiers brought the art of making paper with them to the West. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

Padma Sambhava, an Indian guru, brought Buddhism to Tibet, heretofore rife with spirits, demigods and demons. Called to the country by King Trisong Detsan, the guru brought writing to the country and blended native beliefs with the Hindu and Buddhist cults of Tantrism, so that Tibet was under Indian influence after A.D. 750. (Ref. 5)

1 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

2 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

3 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

4 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

5 [157] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Demons and Lamas in the High Himalayas", Great Religions of the World, National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition.

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 801 to 900

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

Islam and China each dominated large portions of Central Asia at this time. Chinese porcelain has been found, dating to this period, in Tarsus and Cairo, apparently carried from T'ang China through the Tarim Basin and the Pamirs to the mideast trade routes. (Ref. 1, 2) In an area east of a line drawn from the Aral Sea to the south end of the Caspian, then designated as "eastern Persia", the separate Tahirid Dynasty ruled in the early century. Near the end of the era the northern part was ruled by the Samanid Emirate and the southern by the Saffarid Emirate (874) from Persia, proper. By A.D. 900, however, the Samanids had taken over the entire area. At that time Bokhara and Samarkand rivaled Baghdad as centers of art and learning and the Persian language was used throughout. (Ref. 3)1

1 Its Samanid rulers began to mint vast quantities of large coins, many of which went to Russia, chiefly through the Bulgars on the middle Volga. (Ref. 4)

The Uigurs were chased out of Mongolia in A.D. 840 by the Kirghis Turks and the former moved to Turf an in the desert, which is now part of Sinkiang, China, where they reigned for the next 400 years. Those people eventually converted to Islam and later transmitted their script to the Mongols. (Ref. 5) The Kirghiz Turks moved on down to take part of Turkistan and developed almost a Persian culture as they adopted the Manichean religion. North of western China were the "Western Turks" and the most western group of these were called "Ghuzz". (Ref. 6, 7)

In southern Siberia in the mountainous border area between Mongolia and Manchuria, just south of Lake Baikal, were forest hunters who claimed descent from the Hsiung-nu, but who were more apt to have been related to the Juan-Juan tribes that were in Mongolia in the 5th century. At any rate, these are the Mongols that later were to be the warriors of Genghis Khan and at the end of this 9th century they started to migrate into the Siberian plain around the Onon River. Some remained hunters and fishermen while others became pastoral nomads. The latter became the true Mongols, proper. (Ref. 8)

1 [58] EDWARDS, MIKE, "Tunisia: Sea, Sand, Success", National Geographic 157: 184, Feb. 1980.

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

4 [301] SAWYER P.H., Kings & Vikings A.D, 700-1100. (Methuen, London & New York, 1982).

5 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

8 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1001 to 1100

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

Early in the century Mahmud the Turk, ruler of Afghanistan, moved out of his base at Ghazni to conquer most of Persia and the Punjab of India, along with most of central Asia, establishing the greatest empire of this period. Ghazni equaled Baghdad as a cultural center of Islam. Khwaja Abdallah Ansari (1006-1088), who was to become the patron saint of Herat in eastern Afghanistan, lived among the mullahs and doctors of law, preaching his religious philosophy in the center of this Moslem area. (Ref. 1) Mahmud's empire was short-lived, however, as the Seljuq Turks descended from Transoxiana to take Asiatic Islam piece by piece. The great Seljuq sultan, Malik-Shah, had as his general a still more famous Suleiman. Just north of the Sel juqs were the Karkhanis Turks and still north of them were the Ghuzz, parent body of the off-shoot Seljuqs. (Ref. 2, 3, 4)

Still farther north the Uigurs were active on the northwest China border. Little is known about the great expanse of Siberia specifically at this time, but certainly one must assume that it was sparsely inhabited with northern Mongoloid hunters.

Tibet, although previously influenced by Nepal and Kashmir of India, now began to show a character of its own, particularly in its art work, which demonstrated special talent in inlays of gold and silver. It was already a country full of missionaries, monks and monasteries. (Ref. 5, 6)

1 [144] MICHAUD, ROLAND AND SABRINA, "Afghanistan: A Record of a Timeless Culture now threatened with change", Smithsonian, Nov. 1980, page 48.

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [144] MICHAUD, ROLAND AND SABRINA, "Afghanistan: A Record of a Timeless Culture now threatened with change", Smithsonian, Nov. 1980, page 48.

4 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

6 [157] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Demons and Lamas in the High Himalayas", Great Religions of the World, National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition.

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1101 to 1200

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

In Khwarizm an enormous army had been built up by Khutbeddin Muhammad, a Turkish mercenary who had governed the area on behalf of the Seljuq Turks and then finally declared his independence. The basic population of this area was still Persian and no match for the fierce Turks and their Kipchak and Cuman bodyguards. In 1141 Transoxiana fell to the Karakhitai, Buddhist Mongolians whose khanate stretched over all of Turkistan. In Afghanistan the Turk Mahmud's empire fell to hordes of semi-barbarians from the mountainous region of central Afghan called Chor. Under Ala ad-Din Jahansoz, a powerful new Moslem dynasty was then established. (Ref. 1, 2)

When the Liao Dynasty was overthrown by the invading Jurchen in the northern area of China (See CHINA, this chapter), the Liaon Yeg-lu Ta-shih fled west and found protection among the Uigurs, finally establishing a Western Liao state in far inner Asia, subjecting the local Moslem Turkic people, who called the new state "Kara Khitae", meaning "Black Ch'i-tan". (Ref. 3)

Tibetan art work reached a high cultural level with still more beautiful gold and silver inlay productions. (Ref. 4)

1 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

2 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

3 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

4 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1201 to 1300

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA (See map this same section, next chapter)

At the turn of the century Ali-ad-Din came to the throne of Khwarizm as Muhammad II and he soon added southern Khurasan and its peaceful Persians to his empire. To the east was the Tranoxiana Empire and to the northeast of that the powerful Buddhist Empire of Kara Khitae, screening Islam from the new power developing in Mongolia around Karakorum. It was in 1206 that Temujin, leader of the Yakka tribe of Mongolians of the Gobi desert, in council with other tribal leaders of the region, took the title of Genghis1 Khan (meaning "Lord of the Earth") and started to lead his soldiers south. (Ref. 1) As the Mongols conquered Kara Khitai, Ali-ad-Din took Transoxiana with its great wealth and its 500,000 people. (Ref. 2)1

1 (Ref. 3)

It was the normal procedure of the Mongols to send emissaries ahead, bearing lavish gifts and suggesting trade, with new regions. Thus, before attacking Khwarizm in 1220, Mongolian merchants arrived with 500 camels laden with gold, silver, silk and sables. But Ali-ad-Din murdered the ambassador and the merchants and confiscated the gifts. When still another ambassador arrived at Samarkand to protest, the Shah, himself, burned the beards and hair of the escorts and sent the ambassador's head back to Karakorum. Then with 400,000 Turks and Persian auxiliaries, as well as thousands more armed slaves, Muhammad Shah sat back and awaited the arrival of the supposedly small, inferior Mongol army.

But the fate of Khwarizm had been sealed and the first attack occurred at the city of the original emissary massacre where Genghis Khan's two sons, Ogedei and Chagati, destroyed the city and killed everyone but the guilty governor, who was taken back to the Great Khan's headquarters where molten metal was poured into his eyes and ears until he died. A second Mongol force, led by Jebe Noyon2 went south with 20,000 men into Khurasan below the Amu Darya, to draw off any major force there, while Jochi (also Juchi), another son of the Great Khan, rode west destroying major fortifications. Genghis, himself, with Subedei Bahadur of the Reindeer people turned north and then came in from the flank at the Aral Sea while Jochi came up from the south in a flanking maneuver. After some very rough battles, the Khwarizmian army was annihilated and Genghis appeared at the gates of Bakhara, 400 miles behind the main battle lines. Samarkand fell shortly thereafter and only the Shah escaped, fleeing westward to the Caspian Sea. Jebe, Subedei and Toguchar followed him at the rate of 80 miles a day, accepting the surrender of various cities on the way. The Shah mercifully died of pneumonia before they caught him, so the Mongol task force then spent the winter on the edge of Azerbaijan. The city of Tabriz saved itself by the payment of an enormous amount of silver and thousands of horses. Subedei was summoned home and he covered the 1,200 miles back to Karakorum in seven days. It was on that occasion that the Great Khan instructed Subedei to take Jebe and make a reconnaissance through the western steppes of Asia and Russia during the next two years. (Ref. 4) At about this same time, other Mongol armies were completing the annexation of the Kara Khitae Khanate in Manchuria and were starting to conquer China. (Ref. 5)

This seems a good time to stop a moment and examine in a little more detail the method of living, the skill of fighting and traveling and other characteristics of these Mongol people. Their activities represent the last and most violent assault of nomadic barbarism on civilization. Ethnically their invasions resulted in the wide dispersal of Turkic peoples over western Asia, as from the beginning the Mongols augmented their sparse armies from Turkish tribes, sometimes the latter outnumbering the former and the Mongol language survived only in the homeland. Their original religion was an ancestral shamanism, embodied in the Yasa or Law of Genghis Khan, but early they tolerated Christians, Buddhists and Moslems. (Ref. 6) The Mongol army was composed of turnens, consisting each of 10,000 men and divided into 10 minghans of 1,000 men with each minghan further divided into 10 jaguns of 100 men each and finally down to arbans of 10 soldiers each. The commanders of both the minghans and tumens were called Noyans and were appointed by the khan, while the jaguns and arbans elected their own leaders. An army, commanded by an Orlok, consisted of 3 or more tumens of cavalry, several minghans of artillery and engineers. The more experienced soldiers of ten slashed their cheeks to make thick scars, thereby stopping beard growth and consequently eliminating the need for shaving. Each cavalryman carried two bows, at least 60 arrows, a lasso and a dagger. In addition the light cavalrymen carried a small sword and 2 or 3 javelins, while the heavy cavalrymen carried a scimitar, a battle-axe or a mace and a 12 foot lance. In their saddlebags were a change of clothing, cooking pot, field rations (yoghurt, millet, dried meat and kumiz), leather water bottles, fishing line, files for sharpening arrows, needle and thread and other tools. The composite bow had a pull of between 100 and 160 pounds and a range of over 350 yards. It was made from layers of horn and sinew and the string was pulled back by a stone ring worn on the right thumb for quick release. The horses were thickset, strong with short legs, but 13 to 14 hands high - at least a hand higher than the average Mongolian domestic horse of today. A few of these horses may have been even 16 hands high. All, from birth, were trained to follow each other. Mares were preferred as one could get milk as well as blood and as a last resort flesh, if necessary. (Ref. 7, 8)

According to Marco Polo3, the Mongols skimmed off cream (for butter), then dried the skim milk in the sun until dry. They would take this with them and each morning take a pound out and put it in a leather flask with water so that while they rode the milk would dissolve and they would soon have reconstituted milk for breakfast. For a rapid 10 day journey, each man had a string of 18 horses and would take no provisions, living on the blood of the horses - piercing veins and drinking about 5/8 pint every 10th day from each animal. In this way the rider could be sustained without impairing the mounts. On such a forced trip the soldier would use no fire, in part because of the danger of being seen and in part because there was probably no fuel. In general, the nomad diet was high in protein, fat and vitamins A and B but low in vitamin C (except in Scythian territory).

They got their vitamin C from mare's milk, which is 4 times as high in this as cow's milk. (Ref. 9) The Mongol fighting tactics were far ahead of their time. In World War II, both Rommel and Patton were students and admirers of Subedei, perhaps the greatest tactician of the Mongol generals. (Ref. 10)

We have discussed the original reconnaissance of the Russian steppe in the preceding paragraphs in the section on RUSSIA and we shall not repeat that here, but we need to pick up the narrative as the Mongols were retreating back to Asia. It has been noted that the Mongol armies had received 10,000 reinforcements under Genghis Khan's son, Jochi, as they defeated the Kama Bulgars on the upper Volga. They then rode on east to the lands of the eastern Cuman Kanglis, who had supplied so many soldiers to Muhammed II back in 1220 in the original Khwarizm war. Only when they had been annihilated and the Kangli khan killed were they ready to rejoin the Great Khan on the Irtish River. En- route Jebe died of a fever.

By this time Genghis was camped in a fertile valley, holding court on a golden throne in a huge, white pavilion that was capable of holding 2,000 people. Jochi gave his father a gift of over 100,000 horses that he had taken in tribute from the Kanglis. In two years, these Mongols had already ridden over 5,500 miles, and their real campaign of conquest into Europe had not even begun.

The career of that great instigator, Genghis Khan (1207-1227) is the most dramatic example in all history of the potentialities of nomad warfare. Superior generalship, mobility of cavalry and what today would be called "staff work", gave the Mongols superiority over every enemy they encountered. Genghis, although unbelievably cruel to his enemies and traitors, was in every other way a surprisingly enlightened and liberal ruler. His codified laws, eventually governing 50 nations, were far less cruel than the laws of Islam. Karakorum was a city where churches, mosques and temples stood side by side. This capital had been visited by William of Rubruck some forty years before Marco Polo's time, as an emissary of Louis IX of France. William described a giant silver fountain which had been constructed by Guillaume Houcher, a French goldsmith, which contained four spouts which dispensed respectively kumiss (fermented mare's milk4), wine, mead and rice wine. Genghis had nearly five hundred wives and concubines and a preoccupation with wine. On his death the homeland was bequeathed to his youngest son, Tolui, while the former empire of Muhammad II (Kh warizm) was given to Chagatai, all the eastern empire (China) to Ogedai and the western steppes to the sons of Jochi - Orda and Batu. At that time the Mongol armies were undefeated and the entire steppe from the Volga to the Amur had been welded into a single, vast, military confederacy. (Ref. 11, 12, 13)

The death of Genghis did not by any means signal the end of the Mongol supremacy. The title of Great Khan descended upon Ogedai and Karakorum was extended so that 500 wagon loads of food were brought in every day. These wagons, which brought in more than 500,000 bushels of grain each year from China, took 4 months to make the round trip but such deliveries supplemented the meat and milk products locally available. (Ref. 15) Ogedai had gold fountains in the shape of elephants, tigers and horses and kumiz continually poured from the mouths of each. But like his father, he too was fond of wine and gradually the control of the empire fell more and more into the hands of the chancellor, the Chinese Yeh-Lu Ch'u-Ts'ai5, a Cathayan philosopher, astronomer and physician. It was in Ogedai's reign that the great Mongol armies made their definitive attack on Russia and Europe, proper, and it was Ogedai 's death which necessitated the withdrawal of those forces from Europe, because much political maneuvering had to done before a new Great Khan could be selected. A camp was established a few miles from the capital where some 4,000 ambassadors and the retinues of all the Mongol lords and princes gathered. Finally Kuyuk, son of Toregene, was elected Great Khan. He had Nestorian clerks and eventually told the visiting friars - John of Italy and Stephen of Bohemia - that he preferred the Christian religion. However, the letter he sent back to the pope by these friars stated just the opposite, to the effect that unless he too (i.e. the pope) came to Karakorum to pay homage, he would be considered an enemy. These friars had returned as far as Kiev by June, 1247, some ten years before Marco Polo was born. Although Batu, of the Golden Horde in Russia had sent an ambassador to Karakoram for the khan election, he was murdered because Kuyuk did not trust him. A new army was sent out, not west, but south to complete the conquest of Sung China, a project which had been started in Genghis' time. (Ref. 16)

Mangku, son of Tolui (also Tuli), succeeded as supreme khan in 1251 after the alcoholic death of Kuyuk at age 42. By that time the great Mongol Empire, stretching from the Pacific to Europe, had been pretty well divided into four rather distinct components. Western and southern Russia was the Khanate of the Golden Horde, while about the Aral Sea was the Khanate of the White Horde and to their north was the Cheibanid Khanate. The 4th region was China, itself. To connect the whole empire, however, the Mongols had a communication system they called Yam, similar to the old American pony express. There were Yam stations 25 miles apart, guarded by detachments of soldiers, stretching clear across the empire and messengers rode at the rate of 120 miles a day. (Ref. 18) An interesting result of the vast communication network as well as the slower commercial caravans and armies that marched to and fro across those vast Euro-Asian distances on a northern route, which was much different than the old Silk Road, is that this was the apparent method of spread of a new disease to the West - bubonic plague. Mongol horsemen had penetrated Yunnan and Burma in 1252 and 1253 where plague was endemic and they apparently brought the organism back to the steppe where the wild rodents came in touch with carriers of this new disease and in later centuries that became the real source of the Pasteurella pestis, which was to repeatedly scourge Europe. (Ref. 19)

After the death of the Great Khan Mangku in 1259, succession for the first time was decided by armed conflict. For 4 years Kublai and Arik-Boke fought for the throne, and in the last part of that period Berke, then ruler of the Golden Horde also fought with Hulegu of Rum and Persia. Berke had convinced his troops that Hulegu had murdered the commanders of two Golden Horde tumens that had been with Hulegu's original forces and that the current attack was traditional revenge. Berke's forces crossed the Caucasus, led by Nogai. In the eastern conflict Kublai won but was immediately so completely absorbed in further fighting with the Sung Chinese and the Far East that he could not give much attention to the west. There was therefore a break-up in Asia and eastern Russia into several khanates, as we have detailed above. In addition to those previously listed we now add a separate Il-Khan Empire in Persia, proper. (Ref. 20) Kublai and his successors still apparently looked after the old capital at Karakorum, as over 500,000 bushels of grain continued to be brought there from China each year. Tibet remained a part of the empire of the Great Khan, although retaining its own king. It was in this century that the Tibetan king also became the lama and ruins of his vast 13th century fortress can still be seen with its cascading wall down a hillside at Shekar Dzong. The Tibetan lamas had great prestige and privilege under the Mongol rulers and their artisans reached a high point in independent precious metal work. (Ref. 21, 22, 23)

A diagram showing the genealogy of the Mongol khans will be given on the next page in an attempt to clarify the rather complicated relationships.

NOTE: Insert: Genealogy of the Conquering Mongol Khans

1 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

2 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

3 [292] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization & Capitalism - Volume II, The Wheels of Commerce. (English translation by Sian Reynolds), (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1982).

4 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

5 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

6 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

7 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

8 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

9 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

10 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

11 [139] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Rise of the West. (The University of Chicago Press, 1963).

12 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

13 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

14 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

15 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

16 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

17 [87] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, The World of the Past. (Two volumes). (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1927.

18 [27] CHAMBERS, JAMES, The Devil's Horsemen. (Atheneum, N.Y., 1979).

19 [140] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., Plagues and Peoples. (Anchor Press/Doubleday, Garden City, New York 1977).

20 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

21 [182] RIPLEY, S. DILLON, "Tibet: the high & fragile land behind the ranges", Smithsonian Jan. 1981, pp. 97-105.

22 [131] MASSIE, ROBERT K., Peter the Great. (Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1980).

23 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

1.  As noted in the introductory material, the spelling of this name varies with the source - Jenghis, Ginghis, Genghis, Ghingis etc.)

2.  Jebe had originally been an enemy of the Great Khan but now was a loyal supporter

3.  See map of Marco Polo's journeys on page 753

4.  This was called "cow's milk whiskey" by later Victorians. (Ref. 14)

5.  Lamb (Ref. 17) spelled this name "Ye Liu Chutsai"

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1301 to 1400

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

The old Kipchak area (Turkistan to South Russia) and most of Siberia fell in this century to the last tornado of nomadism – Timurlane1. This man, descended in the female line from Genghis Khan, but otherwise chiefly Turkish in origin, was born south of Samarkand in 1336 and developed into a nomad of the old savage school, creating an empire of desolation and piles of skulls. As a young man he was made governor of a large area under the Mongol conqueror, Tughlak Timor Khan and then drove the invaders out of Transoxiana (now Uzbekistan) by the time he was 33 years old. For four decades he rampaged through Asia. With one of the greatest armies ever seen on the- Siberian steppe, he campaigned against Toktamish of the Golden Horde and soon ruled a vast land south of Moscow. His warriors wore armor of link mail, carried two bows - one for rapid shooting and one for long distance, as well as 30 arrows, a small shield and a scimitar. Each man had two horses. Timur spoke both Turkic and Persian and surrounded himself with scholars, historians and poets. He resurrected Samarkand, bringing scientists and philosophers and building schools and libraries, wide avenues and glittering palaces and mosques. At its height his empire extended from Turkey to Moscow to Mongolia to Delhi. As the century ended he was temporarily in control of all of Iraq, Persia and central Asia - the area known as the Timurid Emirate. (Ref. 1)

In the meantime, the Chinese Ming armies had gained complete control of Inner Mongolia by 1370 and then they pushed the Mongols out of Manchuria and Outer Mongolia beyond Karakorum, almost to Lake Baikal and northwest to Hami, in modern Sinkiang province, opening the gateway to central Asia. In western Asia (and eastern Russia) the Mongols were not driven out but became assimilated into the numerically superior Turkish-speaking warrior population. Subordination to the Great Khan in Peking ceased to have even ritual significance.

NOTE: Insert Map 42. Asia c1300 and The Empires of Genghis Khan and Tamerlane

It has been mentioned several times in this outline that the Mongol horsemen brought plague-infected rodents or at least carried the disease organism from India into the Eurasian steppe. In this 14th century the bacillus became endemic among burrowing rodents in the steppe and the nomad populations became exposed to a lethal infection of a kind never known before. Radical depopulation and even abandonment of some excellent pasture land was the result. (Ref. 2)

Tibet remained quite isolated, but Chinese influence began to be evident in their paintings, side by side with Indian characteristics. It was in this century that Tibet evolved the theocracy which persisted into the 20th century, centering the religious and administrative power in one person, whose succession was assured by the people's belief in reincarnation. The name "Dalai Lama" was not used, however, until the 16th century. (Ref. 3, 4, 5)

1 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

2 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

3 [12] BERGAMINI, DAVID, Japan's Imperial Conspiracy" (Wm. Morrow & Co., Inc., N.Y., 1971).

4 [19] BRITISH MUSEUM GUIDE, (British Museum Publications Limited, 6 Bedford Sq., London).

5 [228] WARD, FRED, "In Long-Forbidden Tibet", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

1.  Also known as Timur-i-lend (the Persian for "Timur the Lame), Tamerlane or simply as Timur

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1401 to 1500

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

Transoxiana and Samarkand were each ruled by descendants of Timur and they became rival centers of prosperity and culture equal to any in Europe. Toynbee (Ref. 1), writing in the middle 1940s, described that culture along with that of Turkey as the "Turkish-Iranian Islamic Society", still existing. One cannot help but wonder, in the light of activities in the 1970s and 80s, if he still would describe these diverse areas as a single culture. Timur had lived just into this 15th century and was determined to conquer China and had moved north from Samarkand, with a horde of 800,000. Camping at Otrar, some 250 miles north of Samarkand in January of 1401, Timur became ill and died. It was his son Shah Rukh, whom we have seen took over Persia and a grandson Ulugh Beg, who kept the center land from India to Iraq, for awhile. Ulugh Beg set up a great observatory and constructed very accurate astronomical tables.

The battle which Timur had had with the remnants of the Golden Horde marked the final age of the Mongol conquests, but they were already in decline. The appearance of plague in humans across the steppe as a result of the establishment of the new reservoir for Pasteurella pestis in the area probably was a real factor in undermining Mongol military might, as their manpower dwindled. There was a decay of urban centers on the steppe, irrespective of external factors, such as Timur's destructive frays. Caravan personnel were particularly vulnerable to plague and from this time on new migrations from the steppe failed to materialize. The opening of the new sea route to the east around Africa was still another severe blow to the region and a final factor was the isolationist policies of the Ming Dynasty in China, which tended to dry up the silk route. The Ming even cut off grain supplies to Mongolia, as a means of pressuring the steppe people, but the Mongol response was to go to war and when the Ming retaliated by trying to invade Mongolia, the Chinese emperor was captured, in 1449. (Ref. 2) Thereafter the Ming reverted to a completely defensive strategy, withdrawing from Inner Mongolia, so that even the pretense of Chinese military domination of Central Asia was dropped. (Ref. 3, 4)

The Cheibanid Khanate, which had existed north of the Aral Sea for some time, collapsed in 1471 and the great Timurid Emirate finally had to split into the northern Timurid Emirate of Samarkand and the Southern Emirate of Herat. (Ref. 5)

In Tibet it was at this time that the theory of the reincarnation of the lamas was developed. The people were taught that when a lama dies his soul passes to a new-born boy and so an extensive search goes on each time, to find the new Dalai Lama. (Ref. 6)

1 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

2 [279] McNEILL, WILLIAM H., The Pursuit of Power. (University of Chicago Press, 1982).

3 [149] MOLINA MONTEZ, Augusto F., "The Building of Tenochtitlan", National Geographic 158: Dec. 1980.

4 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

5 [137] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Medieval History. (Rupert Hart-Davis and Crowell-Collier, U.S.A. 1978).

6 [157] NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY, "Demons and Lamas in the High Himalayas", Great Religions of the World, National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition.

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1501 to 1600

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

About 1505 the southern, central area of Samarkand, Bukhara and Tashkent (including the area also known as Khorezm) was invaded from the northwest by Muslim Uzbeks, formerly called "Sarts" and representing a remnant of the Golden Horde. Khorezm then became known as the Khanate of Khiva, after its capital. Kazan and Astrakhan were taken from Islam by Ivan IV, the Terrible, in mid-century, chiefly with the use of artillery. (Ref. 1) Later an Uzbek leader, Abdullah, extended his rule over parts of Persia, Afghanistan and even Chinese Turkistan, for a short period. The little empire then broke up into separate khanates and emirates. (Ref. 2, 3)

Farther north a revived Mongol power under Altan Khan (1550-73) was giving the Chinese considerable pressure. In the west, the first advance into Siberia by the Cossack chieftan, Yermak, heralded the Russian eastward migration. Yermak was backed by a rich merchant family, the Poyarskis, although the only profitable occupation in Siberia at that time was fur-trapping. That great land area was occupied sparsely by a great number of Turko-Mongolian tribes, including the Chukchi, Koryaks and Kamchadali of the far northeast; Lamuts, Yakuts, Tungusy and Ostyaks north of China; and Samoyeds, more Ostyaks and Tartars just east of the Ural Mountains. (Ref. 4, 5) In the arctic north of western Siberia around the mouth of the Yenisey River reindeer herders lived chiefly off those animals. They rode and milked the partially tamed ones and ate the wild ones. (Ref. 6)

In Tibet, the name "Dalai Lama" was given to the Tibetan theocrat by a 16th century Mongol ruler and the term has come to mean "Ocean of Wisdom". (Ref. 7)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [38] COLUMBIA ENCYCLOPEDIA, 3rd Edition. (Columbia University Press, New York and London, 1963).

3 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [122]  LEWINSOHN, RICHARD, Animals, Men and Myths. (Translated from German). (Harper & Brothers, New York 1954).

6 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

7 [228] WARD, FRED, "In Long-Forbidden Tibet", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1601 to 1700

CENTRAL ASIA

This great source of the dynamic, nomad hordes, which had periodically flooded both the East and the West, began to decline in energy. In the far north beyond the Arctic Circle the Evenk reindeer herders lived, particularly in the region at the mouth of the Yenissei. They rode their animals, sitting far forward on their- shoulders, not on their weak backs. As early as 1614 they paid heavy taxes of furs to the czars. Farther east, but still within the Arctic Circle, lived the Yakuts, relative newcomers to the region, apparently having migrated from a southern steppe. They lived in log houses and used iron, which disseminated from them to the Evenks, although the two people often clashed. (Ref. 1) South of these people in Siberia, fur was the thing tempting Russians deeper and deeper into the area and they reached the Pacific coast in 1649. Only the western portion of Mongolia (now called "Outer Mongolia") remained independent, while the southern and eastern part was eventually taken over by China. While the Manchu Ch'ing dynasty was busy suppressing southern rebels, eastern Mongols known as Tatars and Khalkas stormed northern China in 1675. Although at first thrown back by the Manchu emperor, next a western Mongol chief, Galdan, invaded Mongolia from Central Asia. The emperor's forces launched three campaigns against him, forcing Galdan to commit suicide in 1697, and allowing Chinese military colonies at Central Asian oases of Hami and Turfan. (Ref. 2) The Mongols and adjacent Calmuchs were converted to the Lamaistic form of Mahayan Buddhism.

Toynbee (Ref. 3) says that this represents an astonishing triumph of a fossilized relic of religious life of the long extinct primary Indic civilization, although the connection here escapes me. The old Uzbek areas northeast of the Caspian were now called the land of the Kalmuks and Kazakhs. In the old area of Khwarizm, Transoxiana, Ferghana and Chinese Turkistan there were now independent Turkish, military khanates. (Ref. 4)

In Tibet, the Potala - home, office, castle and fortress of the Dalai Lama – stands atop a mountain, rising 700 feet above the town of Lhasa. Although this was started under construction in the 7th century, most of it was built between 1645 and 1694 when, as indicated in the paragraph above, the Lamaistic form of Buddhism seemed to have a revival. The Potala is said to have more than 1,000 rooms, 10,000 altars and 200,000 statues. (Ref. 5) Late in the century the Chinese Manchus installed an anti-Mongol Dalai Lama as the ruler of Tibet. (Ref. 6)

1 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

2 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

3 [192] SCHWARTZ, GEORGE AND BISHOP, PHILIP W., Ibid. Volume II - The Development of Modern Science.

4 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

5 [228] WARD, FRED, "In Long-Forbidden Tibet", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

6 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1701 to 1800

CENTRAL AND NORTHERN ASIA

The so-called western Mongols (Eleuthes, Kalmuks or Dzungars) gave China a good deal of trouble early in the century, but finally in 1,735 the Mongols ceded the eastern end of Turkistan to the Ch'ing and then in 1,759 gave all of Chinese Turkistan, the area called Sinkiang (New Dominion) province. This then, resulted in China ruling all of outer Mongolia west to Lake Balkhash and then south to the Tarim basin and eastern Turkistan.

Farther south, just east of the Caspian Sea, a thousand miles of desert was fought over by two Moslem khans, one of Khiva and one of Bokhara. One of Peter I's Russian armies confronted the former and ended up being treacherously slain. There was continuous warfare also in the Afghanistan area. The Afghans started a campaign against the Persians at Kandahar in 1,711, with Mir Vais, a Sunnite Ghilzai chieftain leading them. By 1,722 Mahmud, another Afghan, had defeated a central Persian army and made himself shah of that land. Somewhat later, however, Nadir Kuli, a powerf ul chief of the Afshar tribe of Khorosan, defeated the Afghans (and later also the Turks, with Russian help) and then went on to invade India. After Nadir's death in 1,747 a general of his, Ahmed Shah, continued to rule Afghanistan, although by the end of the century he had lost all of Nadir's Indian territory. Ahmed Shah called his Afghan dynasty the Durani1 and the people still of ten use that name for themselves. It was in this century that an Indo-European speaking people, the Pathans, came up from Pakistan, elbowing out the inhabitants from the southern and southeastern parts of Afghanistan, forcing them off the best lands and thereafter living a half-Afghan half-Indian existence. (Ref. 1)

Siberia was being opened up by the Russians at about the same time that America was by the west Europeans. Wild animals (foxes, hares, beavers, bears, wolves) and innumerable birds (ducks, cranes, swans, pelicans, geese, bitterns, woodcocks and grouse) occupied the various waterways and swamps. Hunters and merchants were attracted even to the almost empty Kamchatka peninsula by fur bearing animals. The skins were taken to Irkutsk and thence either to China or to Moscow and the West. Taxes were collected in the form of precious and marketable furs for the czar. Sea otter fur became in world-wide demand and ships, built and outfitted at Okhotsk, used large crews to fight off hostile native Siberians2 as they worked their way even to the Aleutians, catching otters at the mouths of rivers. Expeditions were supplied for 4 year trips. When Kamchatka was cleared of its beautiful animals, the hunters went on to the American coast, even to the San Francisco area. (Ref. 3)

Early in the century (1717) Tibet had been invaded by the Mongols, but the Chinese emperor sent in armies to drive them out and Tibet became a political appendage of China by 1720. (Ref. 5) A definitive protectorate was established in 1750. At the end of the century expeditions were sent from southern Tibet into Nepal. (Ref. 6, 7)

1 [144] MICHAUD, ROLAND AND SABRINA, "Afghanistan: A Record of a Timeless Culture now threatened with change", Smithsonian, Nov. 1980, page 48.

2 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

3 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

4 [288] "PEOPLES OF THE ARCTIC", Cartographic Division, National Geographic, Feb. 1983.

5 [101] HUCKER, CHARLES O., China's Imperial Past. (Stanford University Press, Stanford, California, 1975).

6 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

7 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

1.  Trager (Ref. 2) says this is the Barkzai Dynasty.

2.  These were the Chukchi, who repeatedly defeated the Cossacks and were the last Siberian natives to submit to Russian rule. They were reindeer and sea hunters, who had adapted remarkably well to the severe Arctic climate. (Ref. 4)

Central and Northern Asia: A.D. 1801 to 1900

CENTRAL ASIA

We mentioned above something about the continual increase in Russian migration to Siberia in this century. Gold resources there were only worked after 1820. Going from west to east, the chief Arctic peoples of Siberia were Evenks, Yakuts, Yukaghir, Chuvan and Chukchi, the last reaching right to the Bering Strait. The population of that northern Asian region grew from about 500,000 in 1720 to 1,400,000 in 1811 and then increased again markedly by the end of the century.

Perhaps the center of greatest interest in Asia, however, was Afghanistan. The Pathans continued to sweep clear across the country, acting like feudal barons, becoming the dominant ethnic group and occupying virtually every post in government and administration, although they also became landowners, shopkeepers and peasants. The ruling Durani line ended in 1826 when Dost Mohammed of the Barakzais Dynasty gained power. Trouble almost immediately developed as the British attempted to use Afghanistan as a buffer between Russia and British holdings in India. This resulted in a series of wars in which Indian soldiers fought under their British officers against the Afghans.

In the First Afghan War of 1838 to 1842 the British took Kabul, along with other major cities, but the natives reorganized and soon massacred the British-Indian troops so that only 20 British survivors returned to India. But the British came back again in the

Second Afghan War of 1878-79, with the eventual ousting of the current Afghan, pro-Russian ruler and the establishment of Abdu-R-Rahuman Khan as a pro-British emir. With the western financial backing he did much to establish order in that rather unruly country, and he lived until just after the turn of the century, ruling under British supervision. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

To the north of Afghanistan, East Turkistan had been dominated by China until 1865 when Russian troops invaded the Khanate of Kokand and took Tashkent. On the east shore of the Caspian Sea, Khiva was an independent khanate until it too was taken over by Russia in 1873. Kokand, north-east of Khiva, held off the Russians only until 1876. The territories of the Kazakhs and Kirghiz had been consumed by Russia as early as 18541 (Ref. 5)

Most of the people of Tibet were serfs, attached to an estate by birth, although a few were tenant farmers with 95% of the land owned by 3 groups: Nobles, consisting of less than 200 families; monasteries, with 120,000 monks and 13,000 nuns; and the government, consisting of 333 lamas and 280 lay nobles. In outlying areas there was a nomadic culture. There was no shifting from one class to another, except that almost any boy could enter a monastery. Thus 3/4 of the Tibetan males labored to support the monastic 1/4. Since the monks were celibate, greatly reducing the number of potential male parents, polygamy was accepted among those who could afford it. Among the less wealthy, brothers shared a wife as a method of keeping the family intact. (Ref. 6)

1 [260] BRAUDEL, FERNAND, Civilization ~ Capitalism - Volume I, The Structures of Everyday Life. (Translated from French by Sian Reynolds). (Harper ~ Row, Publishers, New York, 1981.

2 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

3 [144] MICHAUD, ROLAND AND SABRINA, "Afghanistan: A Record of a Timeless Culture now threatened with change", Smithsonian, Nov. 1980, page 48.

4 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [228] WARD, FRED, "In Long-Forbidden Tibet", National Geographic 157: 218, Feb. 1980.

1.  Even Manchuria and Korea came under Russian influence until after war with Japan early in the next century

Europe:  Beginning to 8000 B.C.

EUROPE

We have mentioned earlier that one of the oldest skeletons of homo erectus is one from Swanscombe, England, found with simple tools made of flint pebbles and associated with elephants' vertebrae. Continental examples of a somewhat similar man have been found at Heidelberg and recently not far from Budapest. At the early state of the final glaciation (Wurm glacier), perhaps 50,000 to 60,000 years ago, there were wedge-shaped stones, axes and spears made in central Europe. This was the time of Neanderthal man, who apparently has no direct descendants today and who represented an evolutionary development of primitive man which for some unknown reason came to a dead end and disappeared. He used pointed scrapers, triangular knife blades, ceremonial burials and heated shelters as well as bone needles. Europe seemed to be the home of these men, although some have been identified in other areas. The archaeologists call their culture the "Mousterian" after Mousteir, France, the location of the original finds. Theirs was a reindeer-dependent culture, in which men used "kits" of some sixty-three different tools. They were basically cave dwellers, particularly in Spain and France. At this time there was a land bridge from England to France and the glacier covered the northern half of the British Isles and all Scandinavia, northern continental Europe and parts of Russia. The Black Sea, as mentioned earlier, was small and a fresh water lake that at some time was connected to the great sea extending through the Caspian to the Aral. H.G. Wells (Ref. 1) thought that this great sea might have been connected to the Arctic, but modern thought makes it a northern arm of Tethys. (Ref. 2, 3)

In the Lower Paleolithic Age back as far as 100,000 years ago there were flake tools of the Clactonian Culture and later the Acheulian Culture in Britain. There was some occupation in the Upper Paleolithic in perhaps about 12,000 B.C. and this homo sapiens culture which followed the Neanderthal Mousterian, showed an increased tool "kit" with ninety-three types of chipped stone tools, besides a large group of bone tools. Between 30,000 and 10,000 B.C. most of central and western Europe was probably uninhabitable because of cold and ice, except in the summer, but the waters of the Atlantic and its more southern latitude gave southwestern France respite from the cold and thus was a favorite place for the Paleolithic hunter. Early man here was a killer of game and part-time cannibal. In the "fish gorge" of the Dordogne region of France there appeared, about 25,000 B.C., short, baited toggles with tines attached,- the first fish hooks.

About 15,000 years ago huge herds of ruminant animals roamed the plains of central and Western Europe and they were most useful to early man as sources of meat, clothes, tent fabrics and frames and even as fuel (animal fat). The mammoth was hunted particularly in southern Russia and Czechoslovakia. Early man was already divided into subcultures in the Upper Paleolithic level with a Perigordian (Chatelperronian) level appearing as the earliest in western Europe about 35,000 B.C.; a Gravettian in Czechoslovakia about 27,000 B.C. (extending into southern Russia); and the Aurignacian culture of the Cro-Magnon man at 32,000 B.C. in Europe proper. The latter may, however, have originated in the Near East. Strangely marked bones and stones found all over in these periods and extending up to the Mesolithic period of the post-ice age have recently been interpreted as notational, probably related to tabulation of the lunar periodicity, and indicating skill and intelligence and sophistication, as we have previously mentioned.

It was after Neanderthal man, which is after 35,000 years ago, that clothing and ornamentation can be identified. The best example of the use of beads sewn on clothing comes from Russia, where a skeleton was accompanied by shells about the head, chest and on the legs, suggesting trousers. On the steppes, where wood was in short supply, many huts were made from the tusks and bones of mammoth, which also formed the major meat supply in Eastern Europe 25,000 years ago.

Two categories of European art are recognized, a mobile or home art (decorated tools, small carvings, etc.) and then the fixed works of caves and rock paintings, engravings and sculptures. The earliest art dates to the upper Paleolithic, between ten and thirty thousand years ago. The most developed art was in the so-called Magdalenian era, with the famous cave paintings of Spain and France, of which more than a hundred have been found, perhaps representing a period of over 20,000 years. The pigments used appear to be red and yellow ochre, manganese or carbon for black and china clay for white. Some of the color may have been mixed with fat and the paint was applied by finger, chewed sticks or fur for brushes. The high quality of this art, of essentially the same degree of excellence as that of today1 is further evidence that man of that day had the same brain and intellectual potential as today.

A short glacial period between 9,000 and 8,000 B.C. reached its peak in less than a century and disappeared rapidly, but for several hundred years the forests of England, West Germany and the Low Countries had a climate with tundras, howling winds and drifting snow. By about 8,000 B.C. fishing nets from twisted fibers or thongs had been invented. Turnips, onions and large radishes date back to prehistoric times. Ireland was probably uninhabited until about 8,000 B.C. The earliest inhabitants of southern Scandinavia entered between 12,000 and 8,000 B.C. following after the retreating ice, and forming primitive hunting communities. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11)

1 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

2 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

3 [100] HSU, KENNETH J., "When the Black Sea was Drained," Scientific American, 238: 53-63, May, 1978.

4 [220] TOYNBEE, ARNOLD J., A Study of History. An abridgement in two volumes by D.C. Somervell. (Oxford University Press, New York & London, 1957).

5 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

6 [226] WAECHTER, JOHN, Prehistoric Man. (Octopus Books Limited, London and Mandarin Publishers Limited, Hong Kong, 1977).

7 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

8 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

9 [130] MARSHACK, ALEXANDER, The Roots of Civilization. (McGraw-Hill Book Co., 1972).

10 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

11 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

1. This is Arnold Toynbee's opinion. (Ref. 4)

Europe: 8000 to 5000 B.C.

SOUTHERN EUROPE

Crete and the Aegean Islands were sites of agricultural settlements spreading over from Asia Minor between 7,000 and 6,000 B.C. (A little different view is suggested in the next chapter). A mysterious people whose place names and therefore language was not Greek, spread over the eastern Mediterranean perhaps as early as 6,000 B.C. Linguist Leonard Palmer believes there is a definite Middle Eastern flavor to the words left behind, and traces them to the Luvians, a people from the hills of Turkey. "Corinth", "Olympus" and "Knossos" are among those names that are not Greek. The oldest houses below Knossos on Crete, in a neolithic layer dated at 6,000 B.C., were made of mud bricks hardened in fire, a mid-eastern technique never seen later on the island. The first settlers of Crete, whoever they were, found a heavily forested land with vast stands of cypress, oak, chestnut and pine, unlike modern, denuded Crete. Cyprus had a Neolithic population by the 4th millennium B.C. (Ref. 1, 2, 3, 4)

The central mountains of Greece are a series of limestone ridges running southeast into the Aegean Sea where peaks form a series of islands. The cultivable valleys on the coast are more accessible from the sea than from each other or the rest of Europe. Therefore the east coast of Greece participated in the agricultural settlement of the Aegean via the sea from the east. Domesticated sheep were in Greece by 7,200 B.C. The Balkans had agricultural settlements and painted and impressed-ware cultures from 6,000 to 5,000 B.C. spreading up from Greece. The economy was based on sheep, wheat and legumes. Karanovo, Bulgaria, is an example, with mound settlement debris forty feet high. Similar culture spread all along the coasts of the Adriatic, Sicily and southern France. Excavations in the Maritsa Valley (Valley of the Roses) in central Bulgaria indicate plastered mud-houses over wood framework present by 6,000 B.C. Each generation of people, however, would demolish their old house and build a new one on the site, so that after several thousand years, some of the resulting mounds rose as high as fifty feet. These people at 6,000 B.C. had ovens to bake bread, graphite decorated pottery and by 5,000 B.C. had early smelting and casting of copper, perhaps entirely independently of similar developments in the Near East. Lepenski Vir, on the right bank of the Danube in present day Yugoslavia, was an ancient city site dating before 5,000 B.C. It is characteristic of the work of hunters and fishermen of a pure Old Stone Age tradition before houses took on a permanent form.

Genetic studies of European peoples have indicated that farming advanced from the Middle East into Europe, starting at about 7,000 B.C. with a radial rate of advance of about one kilometer a year, and this advance occurred by diffusion of the farmers themselves (demic diffusion) rather than by the simple spread of technology from one population to another (cultural diffusion). This is evidenced by the fanning out of certain alleles in gene frequencies, spreading in Europe from southeast to northwest and also from the Near East to North Africa, Arabia and East Africa - and from Southwest Asia to the Indus Valley.

Archeological evidence is also plentiful on the European continent, but not so in the other areas. Sardinia and northern Algeria are more nearly similar to the Near East than the rest of the Central Mediterranean, and Sardinia has very low Rh negative frequency and other frequencies that are most unusual. The archeology there shows first that the earliest occupation was Neolithic - with no Paleolithic antecedent and secondly that there was substantial colonization by both Phoenicians and Carthaginians. The first farmers, however, probably came from southern Italy. The island Melos, in the Aegean, has a distinctive variety of obsidian, and there is evidence that Greek and Cretan sailors exploited it and brought it to their own countries as early as 6,000 B.C. (Ref. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11)1

1  This was supposedly created by the "Dog Cult" people about 5000 B.C. (Ref. 12)

CENTRAL EUROPE

The majority of middle Europeans passed into the Mesolithic Age in this period. There were no longer large animals to hunt, perhaps only deer, and man augmented his diet with nuts and berries. The dog was present in the human encampments and boats were used. Farming, which appeared in the Danube basin about 6,000 B.C. spread to the North European plain about 5,000 B.C. They used wooden saws fitted with chipped flint teeth. Neolithic pottery called "Bandkeramik", which was characterized by incised parallel lines above the neck, appeared in areas of south and north central Europe and accompanied the gene gradient which we described above. Such farmer migrations involved more people and have a better potential for increase in population than "barbarian" invasions which have only limited numbers and not enough people to effect gene frequencies striking1y. This farming and the associated pottery spread rapidly along the main river valleys, especially the Danube and the Rhine, at the end of this period about 5,000 B.C. Although much controversy still exists, there is much evidence to suggest that the Indo-European speaking people were actually a single group or people at this time, living in the Danube Valley. We shall examine some other ideas about this later. (Ref. 13, 14, 15)

Swiss lake dwellers with domesticated dogs and plow oxen collected or grew flax for use in making fish lines and nets and general utility ropes by about 6,000 B.C. They also made a bread from crushed grain and had true pottery. (Continue on page 50)

WESTERN EUROPE

Central France and most of Spain had Mesolithic cultures while southern Spain had coastal agricultural settlements that were extensions of Adriatic and southern France cultures. The very southern part of England was not covered by the last glacier, and recent discoveries and dating techniques suggest a very early inhabitation of that area. Dogs were domesticated by tribes in the British Isles by 7,300 B.C. Churchill (Ref. 16) says that at 7,000 B.C. there was still no English channel and Britain was a promontory of Europe. There was land in what is today the North Sea, also, and men lived there at 6,000 B.C. when there was continuous tundra from Jutland across to Eng1and. These men of the north were reindeer hunters, coming up from central Europe. As the glaciers retreated the animals depending on snow water had to have salt. Where human beings accumulated, the reindeers would accept human urine as a source of salt and so semi-domestication became possible, although these animals never became subject to true domestication. Britain may have become separate from the continent by about 5,900 B.C. In Ireland wattle huts date back as far as 7,000 B.C. along the coastal routes and inland waterways. Most of the Irish, particularly in the north and west have blood type O, pointing to a strong pre-Celtic physical inheritance which is believed to have come via the Atlantic from the Mediterranean area. Hunter-gathers of Western Europe and probably the British Isles have close to 100% Rh negative genes, with later positive genes arriving from the east and southeast of Europe. (Ref. 17, 18, 19, 20) (Continue on page 51)

SCANDINAVIA

Even at 8,000 B.C. the last glacier had retreated sufficiently to leave all of Denmark and southern Sweden free of ice and there were men living there, eating oysters, fish and seal meat. Denmark and all islands guarding the approaches to the Baltic were settled by Lapps and Finns. These people were probably of European origin although both spoke a related Finno-Ugric tongue, originating in the Urals far to the east. Denmark was then one continuous stretch of land, not multiple islands and peninsulas as today, and there was one large water channel across Sweden via the great lakes to the Kattegat. The Baltic Sea and the Sound may not have existed as such. A Neolithic rather than a Mesolithic culture existed in this portion of the world. (Continue on page 53)

EASTERN EUROPE

There were good supplies of flint in eastern Poland, and the miles of rivers, lakes and timber afforded resources for early man. The great water system including the Black and Caspian Seas along with the Ural Mountains acted as a barrier between the Asiatic peoples and the Indo-Europeans. Some would locate the origin of the Indo-European speaking peoples at this time just north of the Black Sea, and certainly there were sparsely scattered people throughout all of northern European Russia up to the edge of the retreating glacier. McEvedy (Ref. 21) calls all of these northern Stone Age people "Finns", but most would probably prefer the term "Arctic peoples" or "Lapps". Certain scholars include the forefathers of present day Lapps among the Paleo-arctic groups, while others maintain that they are Alpine and came from central Europe and were pushed north. They do not all belong to a single physical type and do not belong to a single blood group. Their Finno-Ugric language is close to Finnish but the two are not mutually intelligible and there are three mutually unintelligible Lappish dialects. Today practically all Lapps are bilingual. (Ref. 22, 23, 24) (Continue on page 53)

1 [109] JUDGE, JOSEPH, "Minoans and Mycenaens: Greece's Brilliant Bronze Age", National Geographic 153: 142, Feb. 1978.

2 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

3 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

4 [41] COTTERELL, ARTHUR, The Minoan World. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, N.Y., 1980).

5 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

6 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

7 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

8 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

9 [170] PREBBEL, JOHN, The Lion in the North: One Thousand Years of Scotland's History. (Secker & Warburg, London, 1971).

10 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

11 [143] MENOZZIL, P., PIAZZA, L. AND CAVELLI-SFORZA, L., "Synthetic Maps of Human Gene Frequencies in Europeans", Science 201: 789-7921, Sept. 1978.

12 [299] ANATI, EMMANUEL, "Saving the World's Rock Art", Archaeology 36, No.2: 24-30, Mar./Apr. 1983.

13 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

14 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

15 [143] MENOZZIL, P., PIAZZA, L. AND CAVELLI-SFORZA, L., "Synthetic Maps of Human Gene Frequencies in Europeans", Science 201: 789-7921, Sept. 1978.

16 [29] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, A History of the English Speaking Peoples. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1956). Volume I - The Birth of Britain.

17 [143] MENOZZIL, P., PIAZZA, L. AND CAVELLI-SFORZA, L., "Synthetic Maps of Human Gene Frequencies in Europeans", Science 201: 789-7921, Sept. 1978.

18 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

19 [117] LA FAY, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

20 [29] CHURCHILL, WINSTON, A History of the English Speaking Peoples. (Dodd, Mead & Co., New York, 1956). Volume I - The Birth of Britain.

21 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

22 [229] WELLS, H.C., An Outline of History. (Garden City Books, 1956).

23 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

24 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

Europe: 5000 to 3000 B.C.

EUROPE

It was warmer in Europe after about 5,000 B.C. than at any time before or since. (Ref. 1) The origin of the original Indo-European language speakers remains an unsolved mystery, with some claiming these people started on the Baltic shores, others in the Balkan portion of the Danube and still others in the steppes of southern Russia and on north of the Caspian Sea. The date of origin also remains undecided with some believing it dates back to between 6,000 and 5,000 B.C. and others, particularly some linguists, to a much later date. We shall begin our discussion of these ideas in the next chapter.

SOUTHERN EUROPE

A race of dark whites, perhaps akin to the Iberians of Spain and the Georgians of the Caucasus, developed an island civilization as early as 4,000 B.C. centered on Crete, but apparently with colonies on Cyprus, Greece, Asia Minor, Sicily and southern Italy as important parts of the whole. Their language is uncertain and their early writing has not yet been deciphered, but they had early trade and contacts with Egypt and may very well have even preceded the classical known civilizations of Egypt and Mesopotamia. Reed boats and reed boat illustrations on pottery have been found throughout the Mediterranean from Mesopotamia, Egypt, the coast of Syria, Lebanon, Cyprus, Crete, Corfu, Malta, Italy, Sardinia, Libya, Algeria and out through the Straits of Gibralter. As mentioned in a previous chapter, recent carbon dating corrections indicate the possible presence of advance civilizations on some of these islands prior to the more classical ones on the continents. The old Roman belief that Lixus, on the Atlantic coast was the oldest city in the world, supports the possible hypothesis that civilization moved eastward toward Egypt and not the reverse.

An interesting side-light is the recent newspaper report from Russia, detailing the findings of ancient, buried human buildings and walls of a city far below the ocean surface about one-half way between Portugal and the Madeira islands. Again the question of the "Lost continent of Atlantis" is mentioned, but it is perhaps of some moment that the area described and allegedly photographed under water is almost directly out to sea from Lixus. We do know now that the spiral decorations of buildings on Malta date before 3,000 B.C. and that copper was mined on Cyprus probably as early as 4,000 to 3,000 B.C. (Ref . 2,3,4,5)

Just before the close of the period under review, a civilization called the "Cycladic" existed all along the shores of the Mediterranean Sea and seems to have been the highest culture of the times. Inland at about the same time the ancient Helladic or Mycenaean civilization began to develop on the northern plains of Greece. Professor Ivan Benedikov, Bulgarian archaeologist (Ref. 6), says that there is evidence of an ancient Thracian, Indo-European culture in the area of Bulgaria and that they produced gold ornaments, figurines and pottery. This is reinforced by the beliefs of Professor Colin Renfrew (Ref. 7) who feels that the fantastic gold ornaments, some weighing thirteen pounds, found at Verna, Bulgaria on the Black Sea, represent the oldest gold-working known, antedating anything of this type in the Near East. Copper tools were made in Romania, Hungary and Bulgaria as early as 4,500 B.C. This dating has been confirmed by the British Museum. (Ref. 8)

Now some very interesting theoretical propositions must be discussed with relation to the population of ancient Greece. Were the indigenous people known to inhabit the peninsula after 6,000 B.C. the same who later became known as the Mycenaeans, or were the latter invading conquerors who overcame the originals? If the former is true, then, since the Mycenaeans spoke an early Greek language, there must have been Indo-European speakers in the area by 6,000 B.C. But some linguists say this cannot be. Another alternative is the idea championed by Professor Marija Gimbutas, that Kurgans from the lower Volga steppes migrated by land and sea (Vikings of the 4th millennium B.C.)1 to all the Balkans and the Greek peninsula about 2,300 B.C. and became the Achaeans2. (Ref. 9, 10, 11, 12)

CENTRAL EUROPE

The Danubian I Neolithic Culture which spread from the Near East, now reached well up into Germany, and this is usually described as an Indo-European culture. Village-based agriculture was present in Hungary by 5,000 B.C. In Switzerland the lake dwellers, with houses on stilts, built either in the lakes or on adjacent marshy ground as early as 5,000 B.C. The extreme north of central Europe, however, was still subarctic, with only hunting tribes following the herds. New peoples introduced mixed farming in central Europe about 4,400 B.C. These Neolithic peoples lived in villages consisting of six to thirteen wooden longhouses averaging about 325 feet long, and they used the so-called Linear pottery. They grew wheat by a slash and burn method and kept cattle, sheep and pigs. This is the culture which spread into northern France and Belgium.

WESTERN EUROPE

Impressed-ware pottery people lived all along the coast of the western Mediterranean by 6,000 B.C. The island of Mallorca in the Balearics, about 125 miles from the eastern coast of Spain, was definitely inhabited by man in the 5th millennium B.C., co-existing with ruminant artiodactyl mammals. There were Bowl Culture agricultural settlements in France, northern Spain and England in the 4th millennium and these people were probably distinct from the Windmill Hill groups which we shall identify later, and of the old Iberian or Western Mediterranean race, which may have spread by boat up the Atlantic coast. Small boats were definitely in use for coastal transport by 5,000 B.C. In Belgium a flint mine of about 4,300 B.C. has been discovered which required the miners to go through about thirty feet of unstable gravel and sand to reach the flint. The tunnels were shored inside and at the bottom the mine fanned out into a web of galleries. The farmers of Belgium and northern France of this era came from Germany between 4,000 and 3,000 B.C. and built large farm houses and used Linear pottery of the tradition of central Europe. In contrast, the people of France, using Chassey pottery after 3,500 B.C. developed a separate Neolithic farming group.

The earliest flint mine of Britain was in Sussex and has been dated to about 4,300 B.C. The area of the Salisbury plain in southwestern England was inhabited by the Windmill Hill people by about 4,000 B.C., coming from the continent. They were a farming people with cattle, goats, pigs, sheep, dogs and wheat, who added fish and shell fish to their diet. They built at least seventeen known enclosures (and probably actually many more) in this area of England with the largest of these on top of Windmill Hill about one and one-half miles northwest of Avebury, and thus the origin of their archeological name. This particular causeway enclosure was built about 3,250 B.C. and originally consisted of three concentric circles, the largest being 1,200 feet in diameter, covering twenty-one acres. Some 1,300 pottery vessels have been recovered from this spot, and it is thought to have been more or less continuously used for over one thousand years. This, and the other similar constructions were probably used for ritual or ceremonial centers rather than for habitation. When these Windmill Hill people arrived in England, about 4,000 B.C., it was the end of the Mesolithic Age in Britain, and there were certainly other people already there living as semi-nomads, making flint and stone tools for cutting and shaping timber, red-deer antlers and skins. Most of southern England was heavily forested, but Wessex, with chalk and limestone, had lighter vegetation and was attractive to the immigrating stock breeders and agriculturalists. Some feel that cattle may have been shipped to England from the continent as early as 5,000 B.C.

The circular enclosures were not the only mysterious constructions of the Salisbury plains in those early times. The 4th millennium B.C. was the period of the "long barrows" of which there are some 260 in Britain with 148 of them in the Wiltshire country area. The best known of these is the West Kennet Long Barrow, located some one-half mile south of Avebury. Constructed at about 3,600 B.C. it is three hundred forty feet long and seventy-five feet wide at its widest eastern end and eight feet high. It was originally surrounded by a curb of stones. The eastern one-eighth of the barrow is a stone tomb with five carefully made chambers in which forty-five skeletons have been found. At the entrance are many upright stones, lined up at right angles to the axis of the mound. No function has been yet identified for the western seven-eighths of the barrow.

The first Neolithic Age sites of Ireland are found in County Tyrone, dating from about 3,700 B.C. onwards. The Sandhills Ware Pottery people there exploited the salmon from the Boyne River and by 3,250 lived in rectangular, timber houses. The forests were cleared and cereals, oxen, sheep, goats and pigs were raised, perhaps after the addition of the immigrants related to the Windmill Hill people mentioned above.

Next we must discuss the mysterious and problematical megaliths which have been found all over the Mediterranean islands, along the coasts of the Iberian peninsula, France, Britain and southern Scandinavia. Traditionally it has been taught that the 2,500 B.C. period was the one of this megalithic culture, but recent correction of carbon dating by bristle-cone pine correlation has put the Atlantic megaliths back another 800 years to before 3,000 B.C. One theory is that this culture was based on a religion spread by priests and merchants (perhaps from Malta?), but as we shall see when we discuss some of these remaining monuments in the next chapter, their function, at least in some, appears to have been far greater than any simple ritual. It has been estimated that there are at least 50,000 of these megaliths in Western Europe and countless numbers of others must have been destroyed through the ages. Recently there has been speculation that the original megalith builders may have spread from Britain southward, rather than the reverse.

These immigrants also settled in Ireland and western mainland coastal areas, but avoided the Midlands. In this period of global optimal climate, there were prehistoric farms in Scotland and Northern England in latitude elevations where today no agriculture is feasible. At about 3,000 B.C. this Eden terminated with a sharp return of colder weather (Ref. 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21)

SCANDINAVIA

At 5,900 B.C. there were stupendous geological changes still occurring in the north. Men had lived in the area now covered by the North Sea but as the glaciers melted and receded, the earth's crust, previously dented by the weight of the ice, began to rise and it is still rising throughout most of Sweden today. South of this, the waters poured into the North Sea and over much of Denmark, so that the main part of this land remained attached to Europe only by a thin stalk at Holstein and the Danish tribes became isolated and remained virtually so for some centuries. The Danes knew how to sail and canoe and had flint tools and weapons. All southern Scandinavia and the Baltic settlements of this era had the Funnel Rim pottery. Rock scribings of petroglyphs hewn into or occasionally painted on rock faces representing animals have been found all over the Scandinavian peninsula, as well as in Finland and Russia, dating back to at least 5,000 B.C. Most of these are life-size and are outline drawings in naturalistic style, although another type with stylized animals has been found at Vengen and Ausevik, Norway and Namforsen in Sweden. Just after 4,000 B.C. (some say earlier) contact with Europe proper increased with the result that new people growing barley and wheat and raising herds of cattle, sheep and pigs migrated into the Scandinavian area. (Were these the same as the Windmill Hill people in England?). Like other areas in Western Europe, this was also the era of megalithic tombs, of which some thousands still stand in southern Scandinavia. Due to the very warm climate which developed after 5,000 B.C., vines grew in southern Norway and the whole of Scandinavia had mixed and deciduous forests. (Ref. 22, 23)

EASTERN EUROPE

There is archeological evidence of human habitation on the southern plains of Russia dating far back into prehistoric times, and nomadic peoples roamed the country throughout the centuries of this chapter. Of particular interest are the Kurgans, known to live on the lower Volga even in 5,000 B.C. (See also SOUTHERN EUROPE, this chapter). They had horses, loved to fight and buried their dead under tumuli. They may later have migrated to Greece to become the Mycenaeans. Marija Gimbutas of U.C.L.A. thinks these people are the original Indo-Europeans and that about 4,000 B.C. they expanded into the Danube basin and down into the Balkan peninsula from there. Most archeologists would deny that they are the original Indo-Europeans but do agree that at sometime, probably 3,500 to 3,000 B.C., these people did over-run much of Europe, using wheeled carts and bronze weapons.

Wild grapes were brought under cultivation in the Caucasus in the 4th millennium B.C. The Finns (or Lapps?) were endemic in northern Russia and occupied all northern climes outside the area of Neolithic Culture. The Linear Pottery Culture spread from Hungary around the northern edge of the Carpathians into Russia in the mid-5th millennium and agriculture spread through the Volga-Don region from the Danube by about 4,500 B.C. Central, east Europe was in the late copper age after 3,500 B.C., as the Carpathians supplied plenty of copper and later gold and tin. (Ref. 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29)

1 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

2 [95] HEYERDAHL, THOR, Early Man and the Ocean. (Doubleday & Co. Inc., Garden City, New York, 1979).

3 [178] RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Europe is Older than we Thought", National Geographic 152: 615, Nov. 1977.

4 [224] VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

5 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

6 [171] PRIDEAUX, TOM, "Rich & Rugged Thracian life seen in a Glittering Show", Smithsonian 8: 42-51, June 1977.

7 [179] RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Bulgaria's Golden Treasures", National Geographic 158: 112, July, 1980.

8 [164] PAINTIN, ELAINE, "Radio-carbon Dating and the Archeologist", Pamphlet published by the Trustees of the British Museum, 1977).

9 [171] PRIDEAUX, TOM, "Rich & Rugged Thracian life seen in a Glittering Show", Smithsonian 8: 42-51, June 1977.

10 [179] RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Bulgaria's Golden Treasures", National Geographic 158: 112, July, 1980.

11 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

12 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

13 [227] WALDREN, WM. H., "Investigation of Cave Deposits of Quarternary and Holocene Origin: The Muleta Expedition", National Geographic Society Research Reports, Vol. 12, 1971 Projects, pp. 731-745. (National Geographic Society, Washington D.C. 1980).

14 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

15 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

16 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

17 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

18 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

19 [224] VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

20 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

21 [7] BALFOUR, MICHAEL, Stonehenge and its Mysteries, (Charles Scribners Sons, N.Y., 1980).

22 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

23 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

24 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

25 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

26 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

27 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

28 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

29 [222] TRAGER, JAMES, The Peoples Chronology. (Holt, Rinehart & Winston, New York, 1979).

1. Ref. 215, page 268

2. "Achaeans" is often used interchangeably with "Mycenaeans"

Europe: 3000 to 1500 B.C.

SOUTHERN EUROPE

EASTERN MEDITERRANEAN ISLANDS

The British Museum has displays indicating the original civilization in the Aegean and eastern Mediterranean should be called the "Cycladian", existing from 3,000 to 2,000 B.C. and to be considered separate from the Cretan or Minoan Civilization which followed1. Although, as noted in the last chapter, people with an advanced Neolithic Culture lived on Crete from 6,000 B.C. onward, the Bronze Age started only about 2,600 B.C.

There are some who believe that the Egyptian and Anatolian influences stimulated the development, but most now feel that this was a purely local progress over a thousand year period. For the first 600 years or so of this Bronze Age, civilization was rather low key, and it appears that there may have been folks of several different origins on the island. Homer was probably truthful when he described three peoples - the Eteocretans, the Kydonians and the Pelasgians. The first of these may be considered the initial truly Cretan people, perhaps of Luvian origin and speaking the as yet undeciphered Linear A language. The Bulgarian linguist, Vladimer Georgiev, claiming decipherment of the Phaestos Disc found on Crete in 1910, believes that that represented a Luvian language which was dominant on the island around 1,700 B.C. and that the Eteocretans and Pelasgians had similar languages. The Kydonians lived in western Crete, language unknown, but they were definitely not Greek in origin. The Pelasgians were an Aegean people who originally may have inhabited all of the Aegean, Thrace and the Greek mainland. Their language was mid-way between Thracian and Hittite-Luvian. Obviously Minoa was a multi-lingual civilization.

The first palaces and cities of Crete appeared about 2,000 B.C., including Knossus, Phaistos, Mallia and Zakros. The first had about 80,000 people2 and the vast palace for the king called "Minos", which was located there, was the largest and most elaborate of all. It had exquisite potteries and tiles, bath rooms with running water, toilets with drainage systems and evidences of rich appointments and jewelery. The construction of such palaces and its accouterments required any number of specialized craftsmen - architects, stone masons, carpenters, plasterers, painters, potters, sculptors, gem-cutters, glass makers, faience makers, smiths, weavers and probably others.

The five hundred years following 2,000 B.C. saw the ships of the Minoans roaming unchallenged on the Aegean Sea. The Cretan navy apparently cleared the seas of pirates and protected the homeland from invasion so that there was no necessity for any kind of fortification on the island. The commercial fleet was involved in extensive commerce with surrounding islands, the Near East and Egypt. The latter supplied scarab seals, carved ivories, copper and tin3 and Egyptian linen, while receiving olive oil, painted pottery, timber and woolen cloth. The Cretans are said to have had 100,000 sheep. An alabaster jar bearing the name of the Hyksos King Khyan has been found and confirms probable delegations and trade with Egypt. Perhaps from over-population, the Minoans sent colonists to various other islands and the mainland of Greece. The island Thera was an important Minoan satellite and a colony on the island of Kythera, between the western end of Crete and the Peloponnese, was started before 2,000 B.C. and was still occupied at 1,450 B.C. Cretan fashions spread throughout the islands and even to Greece and Asia Minor.

Recent excavations near Arkhanes, south of Knossos, have revealed a temple for the dead, dating to 1,800 B.C. with a noble woman burial which included such things as a gold signet ring with a cult scene confirming that Minoans, like other peoples of that time, had the ancient belief in the dying and resurrected god. There is evidence of animal sacrifice and apparently in times of great stress, as in the earthquake period about to be described, they even used human sacrifices. (Ref. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12)

About 1,700 B.C. violent earthquakes demolished the old palaces, but they were all rebuilt, for the most part on entirely new plans. During this rebuilding, Minoan civilization acquired its definitive character and the buildings developed their unique charm, elegance and grace. In the period of the new palaces, the population of Crete has been estimated at 256,000 with 50,000 under the direct rule of Knossos. The palaces had great store rooms and work shops and the earliest writing had to do with accounting for wheat, oil, barley, olives, figs, livestock, wine and honey. Horses are not documented on the island before the 15th century B.C. when the technique of using heat to bend wood for spoked wheels became available. The overall society was a stratified theocracy with the priest-king at Knossos supreme and lesser priest-kings in the other palaces. The latter, in turn, were surrounded by their nobles and their women and beneath them was the peasantry, still living essentially in a Stone Age economy. In contrast to most other ancient civilizations there were no slaves. Among the upper classes both sexes wore jewelry and participated in art, dancing, music and when young and supple, in the famous bull acrobatics. The meaning of the latter is still not clear.

A little north of Crete in the Aegean Sea is the peculiarly shaped island variously known as Thera or Sartorini. This is the remnant of a great volcano which had its first traceable eruption about 1,500 B.C. burying the island in ash and pumice. In 1967 Professor Marinatos discovered the tephra-preserved (covered with volcanic dust) town of Akrotiri on that island. In effect this Cretan extension was a Bronze Age "Pompeii" complete with terra cotta plumbing and town-house architecture. For fifty years or so after that first eruption Thera remained quiet, but we shall hear more of it in the next chapter. (Ref. 13)1

1C. Cyprus came into its own because of its geologic gift of copper. The Troodos Mountains of this island were once oceanic crust, thrust up some 70 million years ago by the advancing African and Arabian tectonic plates and they are loaded with copper and other metals. At first the ancients could simply pick copper nuggets off the ground. (Ref. 14)

GREECE

If one accepts the theory that the Kurgans of south Russia migrated to Greece to become the Mycenaeans, the date of 2,300 B.C. is probably appropriate. Some believe there were two waves of these Kurgans, with the second wave coming just before 1,600 B.C. These were a hard-riding warrior class who dominated their earlier brothers to become a small, powerful, rich, ruling class. The original inhabitants of both mainland Greece and the adjacent Aegean islands were perhaps related to the Cretans in speech and race, but the development of civilization on the mainland had been arrested by massive invasions at the end of the 3rd millennium by barbarous peoples from Anatolia, and a century or so later by invaders from the north. The latter may have been the Kurgans, the first "Greeks", although some authorities believe that the Greek-speakers arrived much later. Like the Minoans, the Bronze Age Greeks4 had passed through centuries of humble living in small villages, obviously poor and with limited trade, chiefly with Crete. Of the various tribes, the men of Mycenaea soon dominated by virtue of chariot warfare and by 1,600 B.C. there was an advanced style of life, centered in that community, but with influences extending to Crete and influenced by Crete, with ships of both vying for control of the Mediterranean. Pei (Ref. 15) says that the classical Greek language was well differentiated by that time. The sail had been used after about 2,000 and this had allowed for better fishing and increased maritime trade. With domestication of the grape and olive, new industries appeared and thrived. Magnificent tombs, with masses of gold art objects are dated to the 16th century B.C. (Ref. 16, 17, 18, 19)

UPPER BALKANS

Excavations at Maliq, Albania, have proved that people lived there in 2,800 B.C., perhaps before the arrival of the Indo-Europeans, and they may have maintained some relations with Mycenaea. In the third millennium B.C. and for awhile after 2,000 B.C. most of the Balkans was occupied by the Tumulus, Battle Axe and Corded Ware peoples (Please see B. CENTRAL EUROPE, this chapter) who may have descended from the copper and goldsmiths described in the previous chapter. In the early second millennium, however, the area was crisscrossed with migrating tribes, particularly the Greek peoples, described immediately above. The Illyrians, settling in Yugoslavia, were an Indo-European group related to the pre-Celts who were located just to the northwest in the present areas of Hungary and Austria. With the development of agriculture in the sandy, glacial soil of northern Europe at the end of this time-frame, the Balkans became something of a backwater. (Ref. 20, 21)

ITALY

The basic people of ancient Italy were the Western Iberians of the original Mediterranean race, and they were essentially the sole inhabitants of all Italy, Sicily, Sardinia and Corsica except for some coastal settlements by the eastern Mediterranean people, until about 2,000 B.C. when invaders descended from the north. The latter were the Italics, part of the western branch of early Indo-European speakers, related to the "Ligurian Celts". They built homes on foundations of piles (Terramara) and their descendants became the basic stock of present day Italy. By 1,850 B.C. these people had occupied all of Italy except the northwestern one-quarter which was occupied by Etruscans, who McEvedy (Ref. 22) insists, were remnants of the Western Iberians. Ancient peoples also remained on Sicily and the western islands, although by 1,600 B.C. so-called "Celto Ligurians" from southern France had occupied Corsica and Sardinia. (Ref. 23)

CENTRAL EUROPE

By 3,000 B.C. all Europe but northern Scandinavia had farming communities. Indo-European speaking groups lived throughout central Europe from the beginning of this period’s various modifications of the basic language. Professor Jan Filip (Ref. 24), patriarch of Celtic history of Charles University, Prague, described a "Corded Ware" or "Battle Axe" people representing the first Indo-European speakers of this area, living there about 2,300 B.C. as the precursors of the Celts, and dominating the earlier Neolithic Cultures of northern central and western Europe. The Austrian Salzkammergut was settled about 2,500 B.C. with the inhabitants getting salt from salt wells. (Ref. 25) As a general westward migration occurred the area became dominated about 1,850 B.C. by the Bell-beaker Culture, named from the bell shaped cups found in their graves. The origin of this pottery society has been much disputed, some claiming it started in Spain and spread east to Germany, and some the reverse, but if it was, indeed, a culture endemic with the early Indo-Europeans, then the expansion must have been westward from the original Indo-European zone. The Aunjetitz Culture, a variation of the Bell-beaker, flowered in southwestern Germany and Austria from the 18th to the 16th centuries B.C. Excavations in the latter country have revealed bronze needles, arm spirals, daggers and ceramics with intricate detail. As agriculture spread, sometimes as seeds were moved to new climes they would scarcely grow and weeds would take over the fields. On some of these occasions, however, it was discovered that the weeds themselves could be used and cultivated instead. In this manner rye and oats developed in northern Europe. (Ref. 26, 27, 28, 29, 30)

WESTERN EUROPE

There was a late Copper Age in Spain with techniques coming across southern Europe from the Caucasus, after 3,000 B.C. A source of tin was found in northwest Spain so that the area could readily participate in the bronze industries between 2,500 and 1,500 B.C. Some of the metal-using communities, such as those in southern Spain and Portugal about 2,500 had to be fortified and some had two high walls with outlying fortresses to give warning of attack. Defenders fought with bow and arrows. (Ref. 31)

In the last chapter we discussed the 4th millennium inhabitants of England, the Windmill Hill people. It was probably these who, at the beginning of the 3rd millennium, started to build a series of remarkable stone monuments in southern England. The best known and most thoroughly investigated, written about, photographed, painted and romanticized of these, is Stonehenge. The original structure, Stonehenge 1, dates to not later than 2,900 when there were already some 180 separate habitation centers in Wessex. At Stonehenge, first of all there was dug a circular ditch some 1,050 feet in circumference, 4 1/2 to 6 feet deep and 12 feet wide. The purpose of this was to supply the chalk soil for a bank which was thus built up along the inner side of the ditch. It has been estimated that this alone required about 28,000 man-hours of work, using red-deer antlers for picks and whatever for shovels. The bank measures 320 feet in diameter and was at least 6 feet high, although some say 20 feet, with a causeway entrance on the northeast. Only a few stones were used in Stage I, a couple at the causeway entrance and perhaps the four Station Stones, but a mysterious feature was a group of 53 post holes also in the causeway entrance.

Most modern scholars are convinced that these were used for precise and constant observation of the extreme northerly risings of the moon for a hundred years or more. It requires nineteen years for the moon to exactly repeat its course in relation to the earth and sun, so that predictions of moon positions, possible eclipses, etc. require long periods of observation. The average diameter of the post holes is 3 feet 6 inches, with a depth of 2 1/2 feet.

There is no evidence that they ever held stones or wooden posts. Some have yielded cremation remains, flakes of flint, cups, etc. all adding to the mystery. Professor Fred Hoyle (Ref. 32) believes that this was not built by local people, but by some who came especially to place the circle at the exact spot needed for some astronomical reasons.

After Phase I of Stonehenge was completed (but before Phase II) another enormous, strange construction appeared about one-half mile north of Stonehenge. This is a narrow horse-shoe shaped earthworks with each leg running for one and three-quarters miles, and which is called the "Cursus", because some have felt it represents a Neolithic race-track. There is some evidence that the bluestones which we shall see were used in Stonehenge II had earlier either been used for some purpose or stock-piled at the western end of this Cursus. There are about twenty similar constructions in Britain and this one is the second longest and it may even pre-date Stonehenge I. The longest Cursus is at Dorset and measures 6.2 miles in length. (Ref. 33) There are none of these constructions outside Britain.

Before the next phase of Stonehenge was constructed, the Bell-beaker people arrived from the continent (2,500-2,300 B.C.) with their copper working skills and their arrow-heads and daggers. Tin was discovered in Cornwall and a bronze industry could soon develop. It was these same Beaker folks who subsequently bridged the transition in Ireland from the Neolithic period to the Bronze Age between 2,000 and 600 B.C., introducing copper and gold ornamentation. These people also migrated into Scotland to fuse with the earlier flint users who had come from Ireland and Norway at about 3,000 B.C. McEvedy (Ref. 34) calls the Bell-beaker people of the continent "Celto-Ligurians" and although we dislike getting involved in semantics, we feel that they were definitely not Ligurians and probably not rightly called Celts, as the latter were not yet definitely separated from the general mass of Indo-European speaking peoples of central Europe.

But to return to Stonehenge, Phase II dates to about 2,100 B.C., with the placement of a double Bluestone Circle, with stones six feet apart in the center of the original construction. Part of this, however, was never completed. The amazing thing is that 82 of these ophitic dolorite stones were somehow brought from their only source, the Prescelly Mountains of Dyfed, Wales, - some 135 miles "as the crow flies" or 240 miles by sea and land, each weighing several tons, to Stonehenge. Professor Gerald Hawkins5 has calculated that 209,280 man-days were required to move these stones. In addition to the Blue Stone Circles an "Altar Stone" was added, the entrance was widened and a new axis alignment made or astronomical sightings. This Phase II may have been influenced by the Beaker people.

The most spectacular part of the Stonehenge display, however, is Phase III, which consists of the Sarsen Circle of thirty uprights and lintels, some weighing up to 45 tons. These massive stones came from near Avebury and almost of necessity had to be moved on ice about the year 2,000 B.C. when England was much colder than before or since.

Professor Alexander Thom, astronomer and mathematician, although differing from Hoyle as to many details, is equally sure that these ancient stone builders were able to predict eclipses, and after many years of study believes that all the menhirs (long stones) and cromlechs (curved stones) of Britain and Brittany as well, are similar in purpose. There are of course other stone circles, some 900 all together, to be found throughout the British Isles. One, known as Durrington Walls, is two miles north of Amesbury and was built by skilled carpenters of about 2,500 B.C. probably with a sloping, cone-shaped roof and a central courtyard open to the sky. It is 1,720 feet in diameter. Areton(?) warriors undoubtedly inhabited these regions after about 1,900 B.C. forming a ruling power aristocracy which lasted some 600 years. The mysterious stone ring of Brogar on one of the Orkney Islands as well as the great tomb at Maeshowe date to 2,300 B.C., the same time as the construction of the Egyptian pyramids. Later, at about 1,600 B.C., there was a time of high sea levels, and the coastal forests of Britain were inundated by the sea. (Ref. 36, 37, 38, 39)

The largest man-made mound of antiquity, rising to a height of 130 feet and spreading at its base well over 5 1/2 acres, representing an amazing surveying and engineering feat of Stone Age man, has recently been excavated at Silbury Hall, not far from Avebury, in Wiltshire, England. Multiple tunnels into this giant mound have failed to reveal any skeletons and its purpose remains unknown.

Recent figures show 4,350 dolmens (usually tombs), 2,070 menhirs, 30 cromlechs and 110 alignments in France. The most impressive of all may be the 3,000 units made up of 10 to 30 columns of menhirs stretched over two miles of countryside at Carnac, France. There may have been a select class of priests trained in studying the heavens, and these may have originated in England, with a later passing on of the secrets to the priests of the Celts, the Druids. Caesar wrote that the priestly discipline of the Celts was developed in Britain and was carried from there to Gaul, and by oral, not written, tradition. Professor Thom's studies indicate that all these stone monuments were built on multiples of a standard unit of measurement called the megalithic yard and which is the equivalent of 2.72 feet. Although men had worked on these monuments for 2,000 years, after about 1,500 B.C. no more were built. Professor Hoyle believes that later generations of astronomer-priests lost the ability to keep the astronomical systems up to date, began to make errors and then lost their followings. (Ref. 40, 41, 42, 43)

SCANDINAVIA

About 3,000 B.C. a few immigrants to Denmark brought agriculture and big, polished flint-stone axes to use as tools to clear the forest. These axes have been found by the tens of thousands. Dolmens of stone, such as we mentioned under WESTERN EUROPE, have been found in the range of three to four thousand and are more numerous in Denmark than anyplace in the world. Megalithic tombs were constructed and many dead were laid to rest in each, some of the dead wearing hundreds of amber beads.

Beginning about 2,500 B.C. there were people of at least four different cultures living side by side in south Scandinavia. They were:

The declining remains of the megalithic civilization.
The Single-grave Culture of Jutland, which was related to the next.
Boat-axe Culture of south Sweden.
Pitted Ware or Pit-comb Ware Culture, to be discussed below.

After 2,000 B.C. these various populations fused together in a Neolithic Culture which made beautiful daggers and other instruments of flint. By 1,500 metal work had appeared in a unique Northern Bronze Age.

After about 2,000 B.C. the amber beads no longer appeared in tombs, as the amber had begun to be traded to the Mediterranean civilizations. Stone cutting and flint quarries were early Danish industries. The Battle-axe people, later to be called "Teutons", appeared about 2,000 B.C., but they used no bronze for another thousand years. Farming communities were present all through southern Scandinavia throughout the third millennium B.C. and it was these Stone Age men who left the huge grave chambers. Finland and the far north were sparsely populated with the Pit-comb Ware Culture, characterized by ferocious looking, rod-like arrowheads. (Ref. 44, 45, 46)

EASTERN EUROPE

The Baltic area and western Russia were colonized chiefly by Indo-Europeans after 3,000 B.C. An exception was the nomadic ancestors of the Estonians who reached the Baltic from the valleys of the upper Volga. They were related to Finns and Hungarians, with a language which was not Indo-European. In the third millennium the Pit Grave Culture of the Ukranian steppes showed wheeled carts and domesticated horses. This may represent the site of the proto-Indo-Europeans, although as mentioned above, the argument goes on. Soviet and German philologists believe that the origin of these people and their language had to be near the mouth of the Volga at the north end of the Caspian Sea, with spread from there both westward into Europe proper and southward and easterly into Iran and then India. They refer to the people as "Ur-people" and the language as "Ur language". This concept has been seconded by the United States archeologist of Balt descent, Marija Gimbutas, after her study of the kurgans (burial mounds) of southern Russia. The Kurgan people seem to have left their homes between 2,400 and 2,300 B.C. to first invade the north shore of the Black Sea and then the territory of the Trans-Caucasus. The mountain people of the latter area had already had much contact with the Mesopotamian civilizations and had a civilizing influence on the barbarian Kurgans. The Hittites may have moved out from this culture in about 2,000 B.C. (Ref. 47) Old river names suggest that by 1,500 B.C. the entire region between the Baltic and the Alps, the British Isles and Hungary, was occupied by people speaking a single Indo-European idiom called "Old European Language" by the Indo-Europeanist, Hans Krahe6. A special section at the end of this chapter will give a more or less complete break down of the various Indo-European languages. In the meantime let us return to our narrative about eastern Europe in this particular time-frame.

The Ukraine and some areas farther east were soon colonized by pastoral groups, some of which were the ancestors of later-day Scythians. North of the steppe and desert belt in Russia, around fifty-five degrees north, there was a thin belt of deciduous forest with some farmers, and still north of that were scattered hunters of the reindeer. Copper working extended almost to the Arctic by 1,850 B.C. Peasant farmers from central Europe continued to push eastward along the forest belt of central Russia, growing the hardy cereals as crops and reaching Moscow and the southern Urals by 2,000 B.C. (Ref. 48, 49, 50, 51)

The Baltic linguistic group of northeastern Indo-Europeans came to the eastern Baltic and western Russia area before and about 2,000 B.C. as agriculturalists and cattle raisers. They originally reached northward to Finland and eastward to the upper Volga7, but only the southeastern Baltic groups survived through the Bronze Age, the Iron Age and down to about A.D. 500, living between the Oder and Dvina rivers. There are hundreds of Baltic loan words in the Finno-Ugrian languages. The Galindians (Golyad of Russian chronicles) were the easternmost Balts, extending up to the Moscow area and existing up until the 12th century of the Christian Era. Some islands of these people still existed around Smolensk, Vitebsk and Minsk, almost up until the present time. The only true survivors today, however, are some families in Latvia and Lithuania, probably mixed with invading Germans, Poles and Russians through the centuries. They at least still have Baltic languages. (Ref. 52, 53)

Even after 2,000 B.C. the Fatyanovo Culture existed in central Russia. By 1,800 three rather distinct peoples occupied their own zones in eastern Europe. In addition to the Balts, which we have described as occupying the Baltic area, to the south was a band of Slavs extending from far in Russia west to the Vistula, and finally the entire southern area west and just north of the Black Sea was occupied by the Thraco-Cimmerians. At 1,600 B.C. the Balts and Slavs were still without the use of bronze, although it was in common use to the west with the proto-Celts and to the south among the Thraco-Cimmerians. (Ref. 55)

1 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

2 [114] KITAGAWA, JOSEPH M., "The Eightfold Path to Nirvana", Great Religions of the World. (National Geographic Society, 1978 Edition).

3 [41] COTTERELL, ARTHUR, The Minoan World. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, N.Y., 1980).

4 [18] BRITISH MUSEUM, (Personal notes, 1978).

5 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

6 [129] MARINATOS, SPYRIDON, "Thera, Key to the Riddle of Minos", National Geographic 141: No. 5, page 702, May, 1972.

7 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

8 [109] JUDGE, JOSEPH, "Minoans and Mycenaens: Greece's Brilliant Bronze Age", National Geographic 153: 142, Feb. 1978.

9 [186] SAKELLARAKIS, YANNIS AND SAPOUNA-SAKELLARAKI, EFI, "Drama of Death in a Minoan Temple", National Geographic 159: 205-222, Feb. 1981.

10 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

11 [213] THOMAS, HUGH, A History of the World. (Harper & Row, Publ., New York, 1979).

12 [188] SAVILLE, CURTIS & KATHLEEN, "They row, row, row their boat across the Atlantic Ocean", Smithsonian, Oct. 1981, pp. 192-215.

13 [109] JUDGE, JOSEPH, "Minoans and Mycenaens: Greece's Brilliant Bronze Age", National Geographic 153: 142, Feb. 1978.

14 [281] GORE, RICK, "The Mediterranean: Sea of Man's Fate", National Geographic 162: 694-737, Dec. 1982.

15 [168] PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

16 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

17 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

18 [168] PEI, MARIO. The Story of Language. (Revised Edition). (J.P. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia & New York 1962.

19 [41] COTTERELL, ARTHUR, The Minoan World. (Chas. Scribner's Sons, N.Y., 1980).

20 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

21 [178] RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Europe is Older than we Thought", National Geographic 152: 615, Nov. 1977.

22 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

23 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

24 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

25 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

26 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

27 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

28 [194] SEVERY, MERLE, "The Celts", National Geographic 151: 582-634, May 1977.

29 [211] TANNAHILL, REAY, Food in History. (Stein & Day, New York 1973).

30 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

31 [175] READERS DIGEST, The Last Two Million Years. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., London New York, etc. 1973).

32 [99] HOYLE, FRED, On Stonehenge. (W. F. Freemon & Co., San Francisco, 1977).

33 [7] BALFOUR, MICHAEL, Stonehenge and its Mysteries, (Charles Scribners Sons, N.Y., 1980).

34 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

35 [7] BALFOUR, MICHAEL, Stonehenge and its Mysteries, (Charles Scribners Sons, N.Y., 1980).

36 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

37 [178] RENFREW, COLIN, "Ancient Europe is Older than we Thought", National Geographic 152: 615, Nov. 1977.

38 [224] VAN ANDEL, TJEERD, Tales of an Old Ocean. (The Portable Stanford, Stanford Alumni Assoc., Stanford, Calif. 1977).

39 [7] BALFOUR, MICHAEL, Stonehenge and its Mysteries, (Charles Scribners Sons, N.Y., 1980).

40 [99] HOYLE, FRED, On Stonehenge. (W. F. Freemon & Co., San Francisco, 1977).

41 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

42 [176] READERS DIGEST, The World's Last Mysteries. (Readers Digest Assoc., Inc., Pleasantville, New York, 1978).

43 [7] BALFOUR, MICHAEL, Stonehenge and its Mysteries, (Charles Scribners Sons, N.Y., 1980).

44 [215] THORDNDIKE, JOSEPH J., JR., (Editor). Mysteries of the Past. (American Heritage Publishing Co., Inc. New York, 1977, distributed by Simon & Schuster, N.Y.).

45 [117] LA FAY, HOWARD, "Ebla, Splendor of an Unknown Empire", National Geographic 154: 730, Dec. 1978.

46 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

47 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

48 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

49 [225] VESILIND, PRIT J. "Return to Estonia", National Geographic 157: 485-511, Apr. 1980.

50 [45] DANIEL, GLYN (Consulting Editor), Encyclopedia of Archeologv. (Thomas Y. Crowell Co. 10 East 53rd St., New York, 1977).

51 [88] HAWKES, JACQUETTA, (Editor), Atlas of Ancient Archaeology. (McGraw-Hill Book Co. New York, etc. 1974).

52 [8] BARRACLOUGH, GEOFFREY (Editor), The Times Atlas of World History, (Hammond, Inc., Maplewood, New Jersey, 1978).

53 [61] ENCYLOPEDIA BRITANNICA, (Encyclopedia Britannica, Inc., Wm. Benton, Publ.).

54 [91] HERM, GERHARD, The Celts. (English Translation by Weidenfeld and Nicholson Ltd.), (St. Martin's Press, New York 1976).

55 [136] McEVEDY, COLIN, The Penguin Atlas of Ancient History. (Fletcher & Son Ltd., Norwich, England 1967).

1.  Dr. Frank Stubbings (Ref. 1, page 2) believes that the Cycladic and Minoan originated at about the same time (2,800 B.C.) and existed side by side, along with the Mycenaean on the Greek mainland

2.  Cotterell (Ref. 3) says no less than 20,000 between the years 2,000 to 1,700 B.C.

3.  Cotterell (Ibid) reports that there was adequate copper available locally and that tin was imported from Bulgaria and Romania

4.  The terms "Mycenaeans" and "Achaeans" both simply mean "Bronze Age Greeks"

5.  As noted in Balfour (Ref. 35, page 90)

6.  "Volga" is a Baltic word meaning "long"

7.  As noted by Herm (Ref. 54), page 71